VI INTERVIEWS BETWEEN GLAUCUS AND DIOMED, AND HECTOR AND ANDROMACHE

Successes of the Greeks. — Hector recalled to Troy by Helenus, to appoint a Procession of the Trojan Matrons to the Temple of Minerva. — Meeting of Glaucus and Diomed, who recognize each other as old Friends. — Their Exchange of Weapons. — Meeting of Hector and Andromache, and Return of Hector and Paris to the Field.

NOW from that stubborn conflict of the Greeks And Trojans had the gods withdrawn. The fight Of men encountering men with brazen spears Still raged from place to place upon the plain Between the Xanthus and the Simois. s And first of all did Ajax Telamon, The bulwark of the Achaians, break the ranks Of Troy and raise the hopes of those who fought Beside him; for he smote the bravest man Of all the Thracian warriors, — Acamas, ,0 Son of Eussorus, strong and large of limb. His spear-head, through the plumed helmet's cone Entering the forehead of the Thracian, pierced The bone, and darkness gathered o'er his eyes. The valiant Diomed slew Axylus, 1s The son of Teuthras. To the war he came From nobly-built Arisba; great his wealth, And greatly was he loved, for courteously He welcomed to his house beside the way All comers. None of these could interpose » Between him and his death, for Diomed Page 152 152 The Iliad. Slew him and his,attendant charioteer, Calysius; both went down below the earth. And then Euryalus struck Dresus down, And smote Opheltius, and went on to slay ?s /Esepus and his brother Pedasus ;— A river-nymph, Abarbareia, bore Both children to Bucolion the renowned. Bucolion was the eldest of the sons Of great Laomedon. His mother reared r The boy in secret. While he fed his sheep, He with the river-nymph was joined in love And marriage, and she bore him twins ; and these, Brave and of shapely limb, Mecisteus' son Struck down, and from their shoulders tore the mail. The warlike Polypoetes overthrew * Astyalus; Ulysses smote to earth Pidytes the Percosian with the spear, And Teucer Aretaon, nobly born. The glittering javelin of Antilochus, *, The son of Nestor, laid Ablerus low; And Agamemnon, king of men, struck down Elatus, who on lofty Pedasus Dwelt, by the smoothly flowing Satnio's stream. Brave Leitus slew Phylacus in flight, « And by Eurypylus Melanthius fell. Then valiant Menelaus took alive Adrastus, whose two coursers, as they scoured The plain in terror, struck against a branch Of tamarisk, and, there entangled, snapped s0 Page 153 Book VI. 153 The chariot pole, and, breaking from it, fled Whither were others fleeing. From the car Adrastus to the dust beside the wheel Fell, on his face. There, lifting his huge spear, Atrides Menelaus o'er him stood. ss Adrastus clasped the warrior's knees and said :— "O son of Atreus, take me prisoner, And thou shalt have large ransom. In the house Of my rich father ample treasures lie, — Brass, gold, and tempered steel, — and he shall send Gifts without end when he shall hear that I Am spared alive and in the Grecian fleet." He spake, and moved the conqueror, who now Was minded to give charge that one among His comrades to the Grecian fleet should lead «s The captive. Agamemnon came in haste, And, lifting up his voice, rebuked him thus :— "O Menelaus, soft of heart, why thus Art thou concerned for men like these? In sooth, Great are the benefits thy household owes 70 The Trojans. Nay, let none of them escape The doom of swift destruction by our hands. The very babe within his mother's womb, Even that must die, and all of Ilium born Perish unburied, utterly cut off." 7s He spake; the timely admonition changed The purpose of his brother, who thrust back The suppliant hero with his hand ; and then King Agamemnon smote him through the loins, 7* Page 154 The Iliad. And prone on earth he fell. Upon the breast *, Of the slain man Atrides placed his heel, And from the body drew the ashen spear. Then Nestor to the Argives called aloud :— "Friends, Grecian heroes, ministers of Mars! Let no man here through eagerness for spoil * Linger behind the rest, that he may bear Much plunder to the ships; but let us first Strike down our enemies, and afterward At leisure strip the bodies of the dead." Thus speaking, he revived in every breast *, Courage and zeal. Then had the men of Troy Sought refuge from the Greeks within their walls, O'ercome by abject fear, if Helenus, The son of Priam, and of highest note Among the augurs, had not made his way ,» To Hector and /Eneas, speaking thus : — "O Hector and /Eneas, since on you Is laid the mighty labor to command The Trojans and the Lycians, — for the first Are ye in battle, and in council first, — «» Here make your stand, and haste from side to side, Rallying your scattered ranks, lest they betake Themselves to flight, and, rushing to their wives, Become the scorn and laughter of the foe. And then, so soon as ye shall have revived i»s The courage of your men, we here will bide The conflict with the Greeks, though closely pressed; For so we must. But, Hector, thou depart Page 155 Book VI. To Troy and seek the mother of us both, And bid her call the honored Trojan dames «o To where the blue-eyed Pallas has her fane, In the high citadel, and with a key Open the hallowed doors, and let her bring What she shall deem the fairest of the robes, And amplest, in her palace, and the one She prizes most, and lay it on the knees Of the bright-haired Minerva. Let her make A vow to offer to the goddess there Twelve yearling heifers that have never borne The yoke, if she in mercy will regard ,*, The city, and the wives and little ones Of its defenders; if she will protect Our sacred Ilium from the ruthless son Of Tydeus, from whose valor armies flee, And whom I deem the bravest of the Greeks. "s For not so greatly have we held in dread Achilles, the great leader, whom they call The goddess-born ; but terrible in wrath Is Diomed, nor hath his peer in might." He spake, and Hector of his brother's words ,*, Was not unmindful. Instantly he leaped, Armed, from his chariot, shaking his sharp spears; And everywhere among the host he went, Exhorting them to combat manfully; And thus he kindled the fierce fight anew. 13s They, turning from the flight, withstood the Greeks. The Greeks fell back and ceased to slay; they thought Page 156 The Iliad. That one of the immortals had come down From out the starry heaven to help the men Of Troy, so suddenly they turned and fought . tm Then Hector to the Trojans called aloud :— "O valiant sons of Troy, and ye allies Summoned from far! Be men, my friends; call back Your wonted valor, while I go to Troy To ask the aged men, our counsellors, ms And all our wives, to come before the gods And pray and offer vows of sacrifice." So the plumed Hector spake, and then withdrew, While the black fell that edged his bossy shield Struck on his neck and ankles as he went. is, Now came into the midst between the hosts Glaucus, the offspring of Hippolochus, And met the son of Tydeus, — both intent On combat. But when now the twain were near, And ready to engage, brave Diomed iss Spake first, and thus addressed his enemy :— "Who mayst thou be, of mortal men? Most brave Art thou, yet never in the glorious fight Have I beheld thee. Thou surpassest now All others in thy daring, since thou com'st Within the reach of my long spear. The sons Of most unhappy men are they who meet My arm ; but — if thou comest from above, A god — I war not with the gods of heaven; For even brave Lycurgus lived not long, The son of Dryas, who engaged in strife Page 157 Book VI. 157 With the celestial gods. He once pursued The nurses of the frantic Bacchus through The hallowed ground of Nyssa. All at once They flung to earth their sacred implements, 170 Lycurgus the man-slayer beating them With an ox-driver's goad. Then Bacchus fled And plunged into the sea, where Thetis hid The trembler in her bosom, for he shook With panic at the hero's angry threats. m Thenceforward were the blessed deities Wroth with Lycurgus. Him did Saturn's son Strike blind, and after that he lived not long, For he was held in hate by all the gods. So will I never with the gods contend. iso But if thou be indeed of mortal race, And nourished by the fruits of earth, draw near; And quickly shalt thou pass the gates of death." Hippolochus's son, the far-renowned, Made answer thus: "O large-souled Diomed, ^s Why ask my lineage? Like the race of leaves Is that of humankind. Upon the ground The winds strew one year's leaves; the sprouting grove Puts forth another brood, that shoot and grow In the spring season. So it is with man: w One generation grows while one decays. Yet since thou takest heed of things like these, And askest whence I sprang, — although to most My birth is not unknown, — there is a town Page 158 158 The Iliad. Lapped in the pasture-grounds where graze the steeds ,« Of Argos, Ephyra by name, and there Dwelt Sisyphus bolides, most shrewd Of men; his son was Glaucus, and the son Of Glaucus was the good Bellerophon, To whom the gods gave beauty and the grace Of winning manners. Proetus sought his death And banished him, for Proetus was the chief Among the Argives ; Jupiter had made That people subject to his rule. The wife Of Proetus, nobly-born Anteia, sought *,s With passionate desire his secret.love, But failed to entice, with all her blandishments, The virtuous and discreet Bellerophon. Therefore went she to Proetus with a lie, — "' Die, Proetus, thou, or put Bellerophon »-» To death, for he has offered force to me.' "The monarch hearkened, and was moved to wrath; And then he would not slay him, for his soul Revolted at the deed ; he sent him thence To Lycia, with a fatal tablet, sealed, »ts With things of deadly import writ therein, Meant for Anteia's father, in whose hand Bellerophon must place it, and be made To perish. So at Lycia he arrived Under the favoring guidance of the gods; ™ And when he came where Lycian Xanthus flows, Page 159 Book VI. 159 The king of that broad realm received his guest With hospitable welcome, feasting him Nine days, and offering up in sacrifice Nine oxen. But when rosy-fingered Morn «s Appeared for the tenth time, he questioned him And bade him show the token he had brought From Proetus. When the monarch had beheld The fatal tablet from his son-in-law, The first command he gave him was, to slay vt, Heaven-born Chimera, the invincible. No human form was hers: a lion she In front, a dragon in the hinder parts, And in the midst a goat, and terribly Her nostrils breathed a fierce, consuming flame ; =33 Yet, trusting in the portents of the gods, He slew her. Then it was his second task To combat with the illustrious Solymi, — The hardest battle he had ever fought — So he declared — with men ; and then he slew — His third exploit — the man-like Amazons. »«i Then he returned to Lycia; on his way The monarch laid a treacherous snare. He chose From his wide Lycian realm the bravest men To lie in ambush for him. Never one ws Of these came home again,.— Bellerophon The matchless slew them all. And when the king Saw that he was the offspring of a god, He kept him near him, giving him to wife His daughter, and dividing with him all »s» Page 160 16o The Iliad. His kingly honors, while the Lycians set Their richest fields apart — a goodly spot, Ploughlands and vineyards — for the prince to till. And she who now became his wife brought forth Three children to the sage Bellerophon,— »ss Isandrus and Hippolochus; and, last, Laodameia, who in secret bore To all-providing Jupiter a son, — Godlike Sarpedon, eminent in arms. But when Bellerophon upon himself ** Had drawn the anger of the gods, he roamed The Alcian fields alone, a prey to thoughts That wasted him, and shunning every haunt Of humankind. The god whose lust of strife Is never sated, Mars, cut off his son Isandrus, warring with the illustrious race Of Solymi; and Dian, she who guides Her car with golden reins, in anger slew His daughter. I am of Hippolochus; From him I claim my birth. He sent me forth »70 To Troy with many counsels and commands, Ever to bear myself like a brave man, And labor to excel, and never bring Dishonor on the stock from which I sprang, — The bravest stock by far in Ephyra m And the wide realm of Lycia. 'T is my boast To be of such a race and such a blood." He spake. The warlike Diomed was glad, And, planting in the foodful earth his spear, Page 161 Book VI. 161 Addressed the people's shepherd blandly thus :— "Most surely thou art my ancestral guest; For noble CEneus once within his halls Received the blameless chief Bellerophon, And kept him twenty days, and they bestowed Gifts on each other, such as host and guest *s Exchange; a purple baldric CEneus gave Of dazzling color, and Bellerophon A double golden goblet; this I left Within my palace when I came to Troy. Of Tydeus I remember nothing, since **, He left me, yet a little child, and went To Thebes, where perished such a host of Greeks. Henceforward I will be thy host and friend In Argos; thou shalt be the same to me In Lycia when I visit Lycia's towns; »« And let us in the tumult of the fray Avoid each other's spears, for there will be Of Trojans and of their renowned allies Enough for me to slay whene'er a god Shall bring them in my way. In turn for thee w Are many Greeks to smite whomever thou Canst overcome. Let us exchange our arms, That even these may see that thou and I Regard each other as ancestral guests." Thus having said, and leaping from their cars, 30s They clasped each other's hands and pledged their faith. Then did the son of Saturn take away Page 162 162 The Iliad. The judging mind of Glaucus, when he gave His arms of gold away for arms of brass Worn by Tydides Diomed, — the worth 31 Of fivescore oxen for the worth of nine. And now had Hector reached the Scaean gates And beechen tree. Around him flocked the wives And daughters of the Trojans eagerly; Tidings of sons and brothers they required, 3^ And friends and husbands. He admonished all Duly to importune the gods in prayer, For woe, he said, was near to many a one. And then he came to Priam's noble hall, — A palace built with graceful porticos, 3*, And fifty chambers near each other, walled With polished stone, the rooms of Priam's'sons And of their wives; and opposite to these Twelve chambers for his daughters, also near Each other; and, with polished marble walls, 3»s The sleeping-rooms of Priam's sons-in-law And their unblemished consorts. There he met His gentle mother on her way to seek Her fairest child, Laodice. She took r*, His hand and held it fast, while thus she spake :— "Why art thou come, my child, and why hast left The raging fight? Full hard these hateful Greeks Press us, in fighting round the city-walls. Thy heart, I know, hath moved thee to repair To our high citadel, and lift thy hands 33s In prayer to Jupiter. But stay thou here Page 163 Book VL 163 Till I bring pleasant wine, that thou mayst pour A part to Jove and to the other gods, And drink and be refreshed; for wine restores Strength to the weary, and I know that thou 3« Art weary, fighting for thy countrymen." Great Hector of the crested helm replied :— "My honored mother, bring not pleasant wine, Lest that unman me, and my wonted might And valor leave me. I should fear to pour us Dark wine to Jupiter with hands unwashed. Nor is it fitting that a man like me, Defiled with blood and battle-dust, should make Vows to the cloud-compeller, Saturn's son. But thou, with incense, seek the temple reared 3s» To Pallas the despoiler, — calling first Our honored dames together. Take with thee What thou shalt deem the fairest of the robes, And amplest, in thy palace, and the one Thou prizest most, and lay it on the knees vs Of the bright-haired Minerva. Make a vow To offer to the goddess in her fane Twelve yearling heifers that have never borne The yoke, if she in mercy will regard The city, and the wives and little ones y* Of its defenders; if she will protect Our sacred Ilium from the ruthless son Of Tydeus, from whose valor armies flee. So to the shrine of Pallas, warrior-queen, Do thou repair, while I depart to seek s*s Page 164 164 The Iliad. Paris, if he will listen to my voice. Would that the earth might open where he stands, And swallow him! Olympian Jupiter Reared him to be the bane of all who dwell In Troy, to large-souled Priam and his sons. v Could I behold him sinking to the shades, My heart would lose its sense of bitter woe." He spake. His mother, turning homeward, gave Charge to her handmaids, who through all the town Passed, summoning the matrons, while the queen 3,-3 Descended to her chamber, where the air Was sweet with perfumes, and in which were laid Her rich embroidered robes, the handiwork Of Sidon's damsels, whom her son had brought — The godlike Alexander — from the coast 3* Of Sidon, when across the mighty deep He sailed and brought the high born Helen thence. One robe, most beautiful of all, she chose, To bring to Pallas, ampler than the rest, And many-hued; it glistened like a star, 3ss And lay beneath them all. Then hastily She left the chamber with the matron train. They reached Minerva's temple, and its gates Were opened by Theano, rosy-cheeked, The knight Antenor's wife and Cisseus' child, 390 Made priestess to the goddess by the sons Of Troy. Then all the matrons lifted up Their voices and stretched forth their suppliant hands To Pallas, while the fair Theano took Page 165 Book VI. The robe and spread its folds upon the lap Of fair-haired Pallas, and with solemn vows Prayed to the daughter of imperial Jove :— "O venerated Pallas, Guardian-Power Of Troy, great goddess! shatter thou the lance Of Diomed, and let him fall in death Before the Scaean gates, that we forthwith May offer to thee in thy temple here Twelve yearling heifers that have never worn The yoke, if thou wilt pity us and spare The wives of Trojans and their little ones." So spake she, supplicating; but her prayer Minerva answered not; and while they made Vows to the daughter of Almighty Jove, Hector was hastening to the sumptuous home Of Alexander, which that prince had built With aid of the most cunning architects In Troy the fruitful, by whose hands were made The bed-chamber and hall and ante-room. There entered Hector, dear to Jove; he bore In hand a spear eleven cubits long: The brazen spear-head glittered brightly, bound With a gold circle. In his room he there Found Paris, busied with his shining arms,— Corselet and shield ; he tried his curved bow; While Argive Helen with the attendant maids Was sitting, and appointed each a task. Hector beheld, and chid him sharply thus : — "Strange man! a fitting time indeed is this, Page 166 166 The Iliad. To indulge thy sullen humor, while in fight Around our lofty walls the men of Troy vs Are perishing, and for thy sake the war Is fiercely blazing all around our town. Thou wouldst thyself reprove him, shouldst thou see Another warrior as remiss as thou In time of battle. Rouse thee, then, and act, 430 Lest we behold our city all in flames." Then answered Paris of the godlike form :— "Hector! although thou justly chidest me, And not beyond my due, yet let me speak. Attend and hearken. Not in sullenness, os Nor angry with the Trojans, sat I here Within my chamber, but that I might give A loose to sorrow. Even now my wife With gentle speeches has besought of me That I return to battle; and to me «0 That seems the best, for oft doth victory Change sides in war. Remain thou yet awhile, Till I put on my armor; or go thou, And I shall follow and rejoin thee soon." He ended. Hector of the beamy helm «s Heard him, and answered not ; but Helen spake, And thus with soothing words addressed the chief:— "Brother-in-law, — for such thou art, though I Am lost to shame, and cause of many ills, — Would that some violent blast when I was born «0 Had whirled me to the mountain wilds, or waves Of the hoarse sea, that they might swallow me, Page 167 Book VI. Ere deeds like these were done! But since the gods Have thus decreed, why was I not the wife Of one who bears a braver heart and feels 4ss Keenly the anger and reproach of men? For Paris hath not, and will never have, A resolute mind, and must abide the effect Of his own folly. Enter thou meanwhile, My brother; seat thee here, for heavily *so Must press on thee the labors thou dost bear For one so vile as I, and for the sake Of guilty Paris. An unhappy lot, By Jupiter's appointment, waits us both, — A theme of song for men in time to come." ♦« Great Hector of the beamy helm replied : — "Nay, Helen, ask me not to sit; thy speech Is courteous, but persuades me not. My mind Is troubled for the Trojans, to whose aid I hasten, for they miss me even now. 470 But thou exhort this man, and bid him haste To overtake me ere I leave the town. I go to my own mansion first, to meet My household, — my dear wife and little child; Nor know I whether I may come once more m To them, or whether the great gods ordain That I must perish by the hands of Greeks." So spake the plumed Hector, and withdrew, And reached his pleasant palace, but found not White-armed Andromache within, for she 4«0 Was in the tower, beside her little son End of Section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents Section 7 Page 168 168 The Iliad. And well-robed nurse, and sorrowed, shedding tears. And Hector, seeing that his blameless wife Was not within, came forth again, and stood Upon the threshold questioning the maids. 4ss "I pray you, damsels, tell me whither went White-armed Andromache? Has she gone forth To seek my sisters, or those stately dames, My brothers' wives? Or haply has she sought The temple of Minerva, where are met «0 The other bright-haired matrons of the town To supplicate the dreaded deity?" Then said the diligent housewife in reply :— "Since thou wilt have the truth, — thy wife is gone Not to thy sisters, nor those stately dames, 49s Thy brothers' wives ; nor went she forth to join The other bright-haired matrons of the town, Where in Minerva's temple they are met To supplicate the dreaded deity But to the lofty tower of Troy she went s00 When it was told her that the Trojan troops Lost heart, and that the valor of the Greeks Prevailed. She now is hurrying toward the walls, Like one distracted, with her son and nurse." So spake the matron. Hector left in haste sos The mansion, and retraced his way between The rows of stately dwellings, traversing The mighty city. When at length he reached The Sca?an gates, that issue on the field, His spouse, the nobly-dowered Andromache, s» Page 169 Bonk VL 169 Came forth to meet him, — daughter of the prince Eetion, w ho, among the woody slopes Of Placos, in the Hypoplacian town Of Thebe, ruled Cilicia and her sons, And gave his child to Hector great in arms. s»s She came attended by a maid, who bore A tender child — a babe too young to speak — Upon her bosom, — Hector's only son, Beautiful as a star, whom Hector called Scamandrius, but all else Astyanax, — s»o The city's lord, —since Hector stood the sole Defence of Troy. The father on his child Looked with a silent smile. Andromache Pressed to his side meanwhile, and, all in tears, Clung to his hand, and, thus beginning, said : — s--s "Too brave! thy valor yet will cause thy death. Thou hast no pity on thy tender child, Nor me, unhappy one, who soon must be Thy widow. All the Greeks will rush on thee To take thy life. A happier lot were mine, s0 If I must lose thee, to go down to earth, For I shall have no hope when thou art gone, — Nothing but sorrow. Father have I none, And no dear mother. Great Achilles slew My father when he sacked the populous town «s Of the Cilicians, — Thebe with high gates. T was there he smote Eetion, yet forbore To make his arms a spoil ; he dared not that, But burned the dead with his bright armor on, vol. 1. 8 Page 170 The Iliad. And raised a mound above him. Mountain-nymphs, Daughters of aegis-bearing Jupiter, sw Came to the spot and planted it with elms. Seven brothers had I in my father's house, And all went down to Hades in one day. Achilles the swift-footed slew them all hs Among their slow-paced bullocks and white sheep. My mother, princess on the woody slopes Of Placos, with his spoils he bore away, And only for large ransom gave her back. But her Diana, archer-queen, struck down ss0 Within her father's palace. Hector, thou Art father and dear mother now to me, And brother and my youthful spouse besides. In pity keep within the fortress here, Nor make thy child an orphan nor thy wife sss A widow. Post thine army near the place Of the wild fig-tree, where the city-walls Are low and may be scaled. Thrice in the war The boldest of the foe have tried the spot, — The Ajaces and the famed Idomeneus, s0 The two chiefs born to Atreus, and the brave Tydides, whether counselled by some seer Or prompted to the attempt by their own minds." Then answered Hector, great in war: "All this I bear in mind, dear wife ; but I should stand s:j Ashamed before the men and long-robed dames Of Troy, were I to keep aloof and shun The conflict, coward-like. Not thus my heurt Page 171 Book VI. 171 Prompts me, for greatly have I learned to dare And strike among the foremost sons of Troy, s70 Upholding my great father's fame and mine; Yet well in my undoubting mind I know The day shall come in which our sacred Troy, And Priam, and the people over whom Spear-bearing Priam rules, shall perish all. s7s But not the sorrows of the Trojan race, Nor those of Hecuba herself, nor those Of royal Priam, nor the woes that wait My brothers many and brave, — who all at last, Slain by the pitiless foe, shall lie in dust, — s», Grieve me so much as thine, when some mailed Greek Shall lead thee weeping hence, and take from thee Thy day of freedom. Thou in Argos then Shalt, at another's bidding, ply the loom, And from the fountain of Messeis draw sss Water, or from the Hypereian spring, Constrained unwilling by thy cruel lot. And then shall some one say who sees thee weep, 'This was the wife of Hector, most renowned Of the horse-taming Trojans, when they fought vr, Around their city.' So shall some one say, And thou shalt grieve the more, lamenting him Who haply might have kept afar the day Of thy captivity. O, let the earth Be heaped above my head in death before sm I hear thy cries as thou art borne away!" So speaking, mighty Hector stretched his arms Page 172 172 The Iliad. To take the boy; the boy shrank crying back To his fair nurse's bosom, scared to see His father helmeted in glittering brass, And eying with affright the horse-hair plume That grimly nodded from the lofty crest. At this both parents in their fondness laughed; And hastily the mighty Hector took The helmet from his brow and laid it down Gleaming upon the ground, and, having kissed His darling son and tossed him up in play, •Prayed thus to Jove and all the gods of heaven: "O Jupiter and all ye deities, Vouchsafe that this my son may yet become Among the Trojans eminent like me, And nobly rule in Ilium. May they say, 'This man is greater than his father was!' When they behold him from the battle-field Bring back the bloody spoil of the slain foe, — «,s That so his mother may be glad at heart." So speaking, to the arms of his dear spouse He gave the boy; she on her fragrant breast Received him, weeping as she smiled. The chief Beheld, and, moved with tender pity, smoothed &» Her forehead gently with his hand and said : — "Sorrow not thus, beloved one, for me. No living man can send me to the shades Before my time; no man of woman born, Coward or brave, can shun his destiny. fes But go thou home, and tend thy labors there, — Page 173 Book VI. 173 The web, the distaff, — and command thy maids To speed the work: The cares of war pertain To all men born in Troy, and most to me." Thus speaking, mighty Hector took again «*, His helmet, shadowed with the horse-hair plume, While homeward his beloved consort went, Oft looking back, and shedding many tears. Soon was she in the spacious palace-halls Of the min-queller Hector. There she found «3) A troop of maidens, — with them all she shared Her grief; and all in his own house bewailed The living Hector, whom they thought no more To see returning from the battle-field, Safe from the rage and weapons of the Greeks, w Nor waited Paris in his lofty halls, But when he had put on his glorious arms, Glittering with brass, he traversed with quick steps The city; and as when some courser, fed With barley in the stall, and wont to bathe u; In some smooth-flowing river, having snapped His halter, gayly scampers o'er the plain, And in the pride of beauty bears aloft His head, and gives his tossing mane to stream Upon his shoulders, while his flying feet a* Bear him to where the mares are wont to graze, — So came the son of Priam — Paris — down From lofty Pergamus in glittering arms, And, glorious as the sun, held on his way Exulting and with rapid feet. He found « End of Section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents Section 8 Page 174 174 The Iliad. His noble brother Hector as he turned To leave the place in which his wife and he Had talked together. Alexander then — Of godlike form — addressed his brother thus : — "My elder brother! I have kept thee here «*» Waiting, I fear, for me, though much in haste, And came less quickly than thou didst desire." And Hector of the plumed helm replied :— "Strange being, no man justly can dispraise Thy martial deeds, for thou art truly brave. «s But oft art thou remiss and wilt not join The combat. I am sad at heart to hear The Trojans — they who suffer for thy sake A thousand hardships — speak so ill of thee. Yet let us go: we will confer of this ino Another time, if Jove should e'er vouchsafe That to the immortal gods of heaven we pour In our own halls the cup of liberty When we have chased the well-armed Greeks from Troy.'

VII THE COMBAT OF HECTOR AND AJAX

Prowess of Hector. — Meeting of Minerva and Apollo near the Scaean Gates. — They incite Hector to challenge the Greeks to a Single Combat. — Ajax selected by Lot to meet Hector. — The Combat ended by the Night- — Proposal of An tenor to deliver Helen to the Greeks. — Refusal of Paris, who offers to restore her Wealth. — Rejection of this Offer by Agamemnon. — A Truce for burying the Dead. — The Greek Camp fortified.

THE illustrious Hector spake, and rapidly ￼Passed through the gate, and with him issued forth His brother Alexander, — eager, both, For war and combat. As when God bestows,
To glad the long-expecting mariners, A favorable wind while wearily They beat the ocean with their polished oars, Their arms all nerveless with their length of toil, Such to the expecting Trojans was the sight Of the two chiefs. P'irst Alexander slew Menesthius, who in Arne had his home, A son of Areithoiis the king. Large-eyed Philomedusa brought him forth To the mace-bearer Areithoiis. And Hector smote Eloneus, the spear Piercing his neck beneath the brazen casque, And straightway he dropped lifeless. Glaucus then Son of Hippolochus, and chief among The Lycians — in that fiery onset slew Iphinoiis, son of Dexius, with his spear. It pierced the warrior's shoulder as he sprang To mount his rapid car, and from the place He fell to earth, his limbs relaxed in death Now when Minerva of the azure eyes Beheld them in the furious combat thus Wasting the Grecian host, she left the peaks Of high Olympus, and came down in haste To sacred Ilium. Straight Apollo flew To meet her. for he marked from Pergamus Her coming, and he greatly longed to give The victory to the Trojans. As they met Beside the beechen tree, the son of Jove, The king Apollo, spake to Pallas thus : — Page 176 176 The Iliad. "Why hast thou, daughter of imperial Jove, Thus left Olympus in thine eager haste? Seek'st thou to turn in favor of the Greeks War's wavering chances ? — for I know too well Thou hast no pity when the men of Troy Are perishing. But, if thou wilt give ear To me, I shall propose a better way. Cause we the conflict for this day to cease, And be it afterward renewed until An end be made of Troy, since it hath pleased You, goddesses, to lay the city waste." And blue-eyed Pallas answered: "Be it so, 0 mighty Archer. With a like intent 1 left Olympus for this battle-field Of Greeks and Trojans. But by what device Think'st thou to bring the combat to a pause?" Then spake the king Apollo, son of Jove, In turn to Pallas: "Let us seek to rouse The fiery spirit of the Trojan knight Hector, that he may challenge in the field Some Greek to meet him, singly and alone, In mortal combat. Then the well-armed Greeks, Stung by the bold defiance, will send forth A champion against Priam's noble son." He spake. The blue-eyed goddess gave assent And straightway Helenus, beloved son Of Priam, in his secret mind perceived The purpose of the gods consulting thus, And came and stood by Hector's side and said: Page 177 Book VII. 177 "O Hector, son of Priam, and like Jove In council, wilt thou hearken to my words Who am thy brother? Cause the Trojans all «s And all the Greeks to sit, while thou shall stand Proclaiming challenge to the bravest man Among the Achaians to contend with thee In mortal combat. It is not thy fate To fall and perish yet, for thus have said 70 The ever-living gods, whose voice I heard." He spake ; and Hector, hearing him, rejoiced, And went between the hosts. He bore his spear, Holding it in the middle, and pressed back The ranks of Trojans, and they all sat down. 7s And Agamemnon caused the well-armed Greeks To sit down also. Meantime Pallas sat, With Phoebus of the silver bow, in shape Like vultures, on the boughs of the tall beech, — The tree of Father Jupiter who bears «0 The aegis, — and they looked with great delight Upon the array of warriors in thick rows, Horrid with shields and helrmand bristling spears. As when the west wind, rising fresh, breathes o'er The deep, and darkens all its face with waves, ss So seemed the Greeks and Trojans as they sat In ranks upon the field, while Hector stood Between the armies and bespake them thus :— "Ye Trojans, and ye well-armed Greeks, give ear To what my spirit bids me speak. The son •*, Of Saturn, throned on high, hath not vouchsafed 8» L Page 178 178 The Iliad. To ratify the treaty we have made, But meditates new miseries for us both, Till ye possess the towerycity of Troy, Or, vanquished, yield yourselves beside the barks m That brought you o'er the sea. With you are found The bravest sons of Greece. If one of these Is moved to encounter me, let him stand forth And fight with noble Hector. I propose, And call on Jove to witness, that if he 100 Shall slay me with the long blade of his spear, My arms are his to spoil and to bestow Among the hollow ships; but he must send My body home, that there the sons of Troy And Trojan dames may burn it on the pyre. m But if I take his life, and Phoebus crown My combat with that glory, I will strip His armor off and carry it away To hallowed Ilium, there to hang it high Within the temple of the archer-god no Apollo ; but his body I will send Back to the well-oared ships, that on the beach The long-haired Greeks may hold his funeral rites, And rear his tomb by the wide Hellespont. And then, in time to come, shall some one say, ,»s Sailing in his good ship the dark-blue deep, 'This is the sepulchre of one who died Long since, and whom, though fighting gallantly, Illustrious Hector slew.' So shall he say Hereafter, and my fame shall never die." Page 179 Book VII. 179 He spake; but utter silence held them all, — Ashamed to shun the encounter, yet afraid To meet it, — till at length, with heavy heart, Rose Menelaus from his seat, and thus Bespake the army with reproachful words :— "s "O boastful ones, no longer to be called Greek warriors, but Greek women! a disgrace Grievous beyond all others will be ours, If none be found in all the Achaian host To meet this Hector. May you, every one, m, There where ye now are sitting, turn to earth And water, craven as ye are, and lost To sense of glory! I will arm myself For this encounter. With the immortal gods Alone it rests to give the victory." 13s He spake, and put his glorious armor on. Then, Menelaus, had the Trojan's hand Ended thy life, for he was mightier far Than thou, had not the Achaian kings at once Uprisen to hold thee back, while Atreus' son, ,*, , Wide-ruling Agamemnon, took thy hand In his, and made thee listen while he spake :— "Sure, noble Menelaus, thou art mad. Such frenzied daring suits not with the time. Restrain thyself, though thou hast cause for wrath; Nor in thy pride of courage meet in arms ms One so much mightier, — Hector, Priam's son, Whom every other chief regards with fear, Whom even Achilles, braver far than thou, Page 180 18o The Iliad. Dreads to encounter in the glorious fight . is» Withdraw, then, to thy comrades, and sit down. The Greeks will send some other champion forth Against him ; and though fearless, and athirst For combat, he, I deem, will gladly bend His weary knees to rest should he escape ,» From that fierce conflict in the lists alive." With words like these the Grecian hero changed The purpose of his brother, who obeyed The prudent counsel; and with great delight The attendants stripped the armor from his breast. Then Nestor rose amid the Greeks and said :— "Ye gods! a great calamity hath fallen Upon Achaia. How the aged chief Peleus, the illustrious counsellor and sage, Who rules the Myrmidons, will now lament! — a* He who once gladly in his palace-home Inquired of me the race and pedigree Of the Greek warriors. Were he but to know That all of them are basely cowering now In Hector's presence, how would he uplift 170 His hands and pray the gods that from his limbs The parted soul might pass to the abode Of Pluto! Would to Father Jupiter And Pallas and Apollo that again I were as young as when the Pylian host 173 And the Arcadians, mighty with the spear, Fought on the banks of rapid Celadon And near to Phaea and Iardan's streams. Page 181 Book VII. 181 There godlike Ereuthalion stood among Our foremost foes, and on his shoulders bore 1«0 The armor of King Areithoiis, — The noble Areithoiis, whom men And graceful women called the Mace-bearer; For not with bow he fought, nor ponderous lance, But broke the phalanxes with iron mace. 1«s Lycurgus slew him, but by stratagem, And not by strength ; he from a narrow way, Where was no room to wield the iron mace, Through Areithoiis thrust the spear: he fell Backward; the victor took his arms, which Mars 190 The war-god gave, and which in after-time Lycurgus wore on many a battle-field. And when within his palace he grew old, He gave them to be worn by one he loved, — To Ereuthalion, who attended him »ss In battle, and who, wearing them, defied The bravest of our host. All trembled ; all Held back in fear, nor dared encounter him. But me a daring trust in my own strength Impelled to meet him. I was youngest then «» Of all the chiefs; I fought, and Pallas gave The victory over him, and thus I slew The hugest and most strong of men; he lay Extended in vast bulk upon the ground. Would I were young as then, my frame unworn *,s By years! and Hector of the beamy helm Should meet an adversary soon ; but now End of Section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents Section 9 Page 182 182 The Iliad. No one of all the chieftains here, renowned To be the bravest of the Achaian race, Hastens to meet in arms the Trojan chief." »10 Thus with upbraiding words the old man spake; And straight arose nine warriors from their seats. The first was Agamemnon, king of men; The second, brave Tydides Diomed; And then the chieftains Ajax, bold and strong; -ns And then Idomeneus, with whom arose Meriones, his armor-bearer, great As Mars himself in battle. After them, Eurypylus, Evaemon's valiant son, And Thoas, offspring of Andrcemon, rose, «o And the divine Ulysses, — claiming all To encounter noble Hector in the lists. But then spake Nestor the Gerenian knight: — "Now let us cast the lot for all, and see To whom it falls; for greatly will he aid ^3 The nobly-armed Achaians, and as great Will be his share of honor should he come Alive from the hard trial of the fight." Then each one marked his lot, and all were cast Into the helm of Agamemnon, son »*, Of Atreus. All the people lifted up Their hands in prayer to the ever-living gods, And turned their eyes to the broad heaven, and said: "Grant, Father Jove, that Ajax, or the son Of Tydeus, or the monarch who bears rule »3s . In rich Mycena e may obtain the lot.' Page 183 Book VII. 183 Such was their prayer, while the Gerenian knight, Old Nestor, shook the lots; and from the helm Leaped forth the lot of Ajax, as they wished. A herald took it, and from right to left Bore it through all the assembly, showing it To all the leaders of the Greeks. No one Knew it, and all disclaimed it. When at last, Carried through all the multitude, it came To Ajax the renowned, who had inscribed *u And laid it in the helmet, he stretched forth His hand, while at his side the herald stood, And took and looked upon it, knew his sign, And gloried as he looked, and cast it down Upon the ground before his feet, and said :— »s° "O friends! the lot is mine, and I rejoice Heartily, for I think to overcome The noble Hector. Now, while I put on My armor for the fight, pray ye to Jove, The mighty son of Saturn, silently, ass Unheard by them of Troy, or else aloud, Since we fear no one. None by strength of arm Shall vanquish me, or find me inexpert In battle, nor was I to that degree Ill-trained in Salamis, where I was born." *so He spake; and they to Saturn's monarch-son Prayed, looking up to the broad heaven, and said :— "O Father Jove! most mighty, most august! Who rulest from the Idaean mount, vouchsafe That Ajax bear away the victory Page 184 The Iliad. And everlasting honor; but if thou Dost cherish Hector and protect his life, Give equal strength to both, and equal fame." Such were their words, while Ajax armed himself In glittering brass; and, when about his limbs »70 The mail was buckled, forward rushed the chief. As moves the mighty Mars to war among The heroes whom the son of Saturn sends To struggle on the field in murderous strife, So the great Ajax, bulwark of the Greeks, m With a grim smile came forward, and with strides Firm-set and long, and shook his ponderous spear. The Greeks exulted at the sight; dismay Seized every Trojan : even Hector's heart Quailed in his bosom ; yet he might not now 2«0 Withdraw through fear, nor seek to hide among The throng of people, since himself had given The challenge. Ajax, drawing near, upheld A buckler like a rampart, bright with brass, And strong with ox-hides seven. The cunning hand Of Tychius, skilled beyond all other men In leather-work, had wrought it at his home In Hyla. He for Ajax framed the shield With hides of pampered bullocks in seven folds, And an eighth fold of brass, — the outside fold. »*, This Telamonian Ajax held before His breast, as he approached, and threatening said :— "Now shalt thou, Hector, singly matched with me, Page 185 Book VII. 185 Learn by what chiefs the Achaian host is led Besides Achilles, mighty though he be to To break through squadrons, and of lion-heart Still in the beaked ships in which he crossed The sea he cherishes his wrath against The shepherd of the people, — Atreus' son. But we have those that dare defy thee yet, *0 And they are many. Let the fight begin." Then answered Hector of the plumed helm : — "O high-born Ajax, son of Telamon, And prince among thy people, think thou not To treat me like a stripling weak ol arm, j,s Or woman all untrained to tasks of war. I know what battles are and bloody frays, And how to shift to right and left the shield. Of seasoned hide, and, unfatigued, maintain 'The combat; how on foot to charge the foe a» With steps that move to martial airs, and how To leap into the chariot and pursue The war with rushing steeds. Yet not by stealth Seek I to smite thee, valiant as thou art, But in fair open battle, if I may." vs He spake, and, brandishing his ponderous lance, Hurled it; and on the outer plate of brass, Which covered the seven bullock-hides, it struck The shield of Ajax. Through the brass and through Six folds of hides the irresistible spear 3^ Cut its swift way, and at the seventh was stopped. Then high-born Ajax cast his massive spear Page 186 The Iliad. In turn, and drove it through the fair, round shield Of Priam's son. Through that bright buckler went The rapid weapon, pierced the well-wrought mail, 3»s And tore the linen tunic at the flank. But Hector stooped and thus avoided death. They took their spears again, and, coming close, Like lions in their hunger, or wild boars Of fearful strength, joined battle. Priam's son 330 Sent his spear forward, striking in the midst The shield of Ajax, but it broke not through The brass; the metal turned the weapon's point. While Ajax, springing onward, smote the shield Of Hector, drave his weapon through, and checked His enemy's swift advance, and wounded him 33« Upon the shoulder, and the black blood flowed. Yet not for this did plumed Hector cease From combat, but went back, and, lifting up A huge, black, craggy stone that near him lay, 3» Flung it with force against the middle boss Of the broad sevenfold shield that Ajax bore. The brass rang with the blow. Then Ajax raised A heavier stone, and whirled it, putting forth His arm's immeasurable strength ; it brake us Through Hector's shield as if a millstone's weight Had fallen. His knees gave way; he fell to earth Headlong; yet still he kept his shield. At once Apollo raised him up; and now with swords, Encountering hand to hand, they both had flown 3s0 To wound each other, if the heralds sent Page 187 Book vn. 187 As messengers from Jupiter and men Had not approached, — Idseus from the side Of Troy, Talthybius from the Grecian host, — Wise ancients both. Betwixt the twain they held 3ss Their sceptres, and the sage Idteus spake : — "Cease to contend, dear sons, in deadly fray; Ye both are loved by cloud-compelling Jove, And both are great in war, as all men know. The night is come ; be then the night obeyed." 3&, And Telamonian Ajax answered thus :— "Idaeus, first let Hector speak of this, For he it was who challenged to the field The bravest of the Grecian host, and I Shall willingly obey if he obeys." s«s To him in turn the plumed Hector said :— "Ajax, although God gave thee bulk and strength And prudence, and in mastery of the spear Thou dost excel the other Greeks, yet now Pause we from battle and the rivalry 370 Of prowess for this day. Another time We haply may renew the fight till fate Shall part us and bestow the victory On one of us. But now the night is here, And it is good to obey the night, that thou rs Mayst gladden at the fleet the Greeks and all Thy friends and comrades, and that I in turn May give the Trojan men and long-robed dames, In the great city where King Priam reigns, Cause to rejoice, — the dames who pray for me, 330 Page 188 The Iliad. Thronging the hallowed temple. Let us now Each with the other leave some noble gift, That all men, Greek or Trojan, thus may say: 'They fought indeed in bitterness of heart, But they were reconciled, and parted friends.'" #s He spake, and gave a silver-studded sword And scabbard with its fair embroidered belt; And Ajax gave a girdle brightly dyed With purple. Then they both departed, — one To join the Grecian host, and one to meet 3» The Trojan people, who rejoiced to see Hector alive, unwounded, and now safe From the great might and irresistible arm Of Ajax. Straightway to the town they led Him for whose life they scarce had dared to hope. 39s And Ajax also by the well-armed Greeks, Exulting in his feats of arms, was brought To noble Agamemnon. When the chiefs Were in his tents, the monarch sacrificed A bullock of five summers to the son *» Of Saturn, sovereign Jupiter. They flayed The carcass, dressed it, carved away the limbs, Divided into smaller parts the flesh, Fixed them on spits, and roasted them with care, And drew them from the fire. And when the task Was finished, and the banquet all prepared, «a They feasted, and there was no guest who lacked His equal part in that repast. The son Of Atreus, Agamemnon, brave, and lord Page 189 Book VII. Of wide dominions, gave the chine entire 410 To Ajax as his due. Now when the calls Of thirst and hunger ceased, the aged chief Nestor, whose words had ever seemed most wise, Opened the council with this prudent speech : — "Atrides, and ye other chiefs of Greece! 41s Full many a long-haired warrior of our host Hath perished. Cruel Mars hath spilt their blood Beside Scamander's gentle stream; their souls Have gone to Hades. Give thou, then, command, That all the Greeks to-morrow pause from war, **, And come together at the early dawn, And bring the dead in chariots drawn by mules And oxen, and consume them near our fleet With fire, that we, when we return from war, May carry to our native land the bones, m And give them to the children of the slain. And then will we go forth and heap from earth, Upon the plain, a common tomb for all Around the funeral pile, and build high towers With speed beside it, which shall be alike 430 A bulwark for our navy and our host. And let the entrance be a massive gate, Through which shall pass an ample chariot-way. And in a circle on its outer edge Sink we a trench so deep that neither steeds 4n Nor men may pass, if these proud Trojans yet Should, in the coming battles, press us sore." He spake; the princes all approved his words. Page 190 190 The Iliad. Meanwhile, beside the lofty citadel Of Ilium and at Priam's palace-gates +w In turbulence and fear the Trojans held A council, and the wise Antenor spake : — "Hearken, ye Trojans, Dardans, and allies, To what my sober judgment bids me speak. Send we the Argive Helen back with all us Her treasures; let the sons of Atreus lead The dame away; for now we wage the war After our faith is broken, and I deem We cannot prosper till we make amends." He spake, and sat him down. The noble chief Paris, the fair-haired Helen's husband, rose 4si To answer him, and spake this winged speech : — "Thy words, Antenor, please me not. Thy skill Could offer better counsels. If those words Were gravely meant, the gods have made tliee mad. But let me here, amid these knights of Troy, 4s» Speak openly my mind. Give up my wife I never will ; but all the wealth I brought With her from Argos I most willingly Restore, with added treasures of my own." 4«0 He said, and took his seat, and in the midst Dardanian Priam rose, a counsellor Of godlike wisdom, and thus sagely spake : — "Hear me, ye Trojans, Dardans, and allies! I speak the thought that rises in my breast. 4's Take now, as ye are wont, your evening meal And set a watch and keep upon your guard; Page 191 Book VII. 191 But let Idaeus to the hollow ships Repair at morning, and to Atreus' sons — To Agamemnon and his brother king — 470 Make known what Paris, author of this strife, Proposes, and with fairly ordered speech Ask further if they will consent to pause From crual battle till we burn the dead: Then be the war renewed till fate shall part 4;s The hosts and give to one the victory." He spake. The assembly listened and obeyed; All through the camp in groups they took their meal. But with the morn Idaeus visited The hollow ships, and found the Achaian chiefs, Followers of Mars, in council near the prow Of Agamemnon's bark ; and, standing there, The loud-voiced herald spake his message thus :— "Ye sons of Atreus, and ye other chiefs Of all the tribes of Greece, I come to you «ss From Priam and the eminent men of Troy, To say, if it be pleasing to your ears, What Alexander, author of the war, Proposes. All the wealth which in his ships He brought to Troy—would he had perished first! — He will, with added treasures of his own, «. Freely restore ; but her who was the wife Of gallant Menelaus he denies To render back, though all who dwell in Troy Join to demand it . I am furthermore 49s Bidden to ask if you consent to pause Page 192 192 The Iliad. From cruel battle till we burn our dead: Then be the war renewed till fate shall part The hosts and give to one the victory." He spake; and all were silent for a space. ?90 Then spake at length the valiant Diomed :— "Let none consent to take the Trojan's goods, Nor even Helen ; for a child may see The utter ruin hanging over Troy." He spake. The admiring Greeks confirmed with shouts s,3 The words of Diomed the knight, and thus King Agamemnon to Idaeus said :— "Idaeus, thou thyself hast heard the Greeks Pronounce their answer. What to them seems good Pleases me also. For the slain, I give s10 Consent to burn them ; to the dead we bear No hatred; when they fall the rite of fire Should soon be paid. Let Juno's husband, Jove The Thunderer, bear witness to our truce." The monarch spake, and raised to all the gods s,s His sceptre, while Idaeus took his way To hallowed Ilium. There in council sat Trojans and Dardans, waiting his return. He came, and standing in the midst declared His message. Then they all went forth in haste, s™ Some to collect the slain and some to fell Trees in the forest. From their well-benched ships The Achaians also issued, some to bring The dead together, some to gather wood. Page 193 Book VII. 193 Now from the smooth deep ocean-stream the sun Began to climb the heavens, and with new rays s* Smote the surrounding fields. The Trojans met, But found it hard to know their dead again. They washed away the clotted blood, and laid — Shedding hot tears — the bodies on the cars. sv And since the mighty Priam's word forbade All wailing, silently they bore away Their slaughtered friends, and heaped them on the pyre With aching hearts, and, when they had consumed The dead with fire, returned to hallowed Troy. sss The nobly-armed Achaians also heaped Their slaughtered warriors on the funeral pile With aching hearts; and when they had consumed Their dead with fire they sought their hollow ships. And ere the morning came, while earth was gray With twilight, by the funeral pile arose »• A chosen band of Greeks, who, going forth, Heaped round it from the earth a common tomb For all, and built a wall and lofty towers Near it, —a bulwark for the fleet and host. s4s And in the wall they fitted massive gates, Through which there passed an ample chariot-way; And on its outer edge they sank a trench, — Broad, deep, — and planted it with pointed stakes. So labored through the night the long-haired Greeks. The gods who sat beside the Thunderer Jove w Admired the mighty labor of the Greeks; Vol. 1. 9 M Page 194 194 The Iliad. But Neptune, he who shakes the earth, began :— "O Father Jove, henceforth will any one Of mortal men consult the immortal gods? sss Seest thou not how the long-haired Greeks have reared A wall before their navy, and have drawn A trench around it, yet have brought the gods No liberal hecatombs? Now will the fame Of this their work go forth wherever shines *0 The light of day, and men will quite forget The wall which once we built with toiling hands — Phoebus Apollo and myself—around The city of renowned Laomedon." And cloud-compelling Jove in wrath replied : — "Earth-shaking power! what words are these? Some god s» Of meaner rank and feebler arm than thou Might haply dread the work the Greeks have planned. But as for thee, thy glory shall be known Wherever shines the day; and when at last s70 The crested Greeks, departing in their ships, Shall seek their native coasts, do thou o'erthrow The wall they built, and sink it in the deep, And cover the great shore again with sand. Thus shall their bulwark vanish from the plain." s73 So talked they with each other while the sun Was setting. But the Achaians now had brought Their labors to an end; they slew their steers Beside the tents and shared the evening meal, While many ships had come to land with store s&, Page 195 Book VII. 195 Of wine from Lemnos, which Euneus sent, — Euneus whom Hypsipyle brought forth To Jason, shepherd of the people. These Brought wine, a thousand measures, as a gift To Agamemnon and his brother king, s»s The sons of Atreus. But the long-haired Greeks Bought for themselves their wines ; some gave their brass, And others shining steel ; some bought with hides, And some with steers, and some with slaves, and thus Prepared an ample banquet. Through the night s90 Feasted the long-haired Greeks. The Trojan host And their auxiliar warriors banqueted Within the city-walls. Through all that night The Great Disposer, Jove, portended woe To both with fearful thunderings. All were pale sm With terror; from their beakers all poured wine Upon the ground, and no man dared to drink Who had not paid to Saturn's mighty son The due libation. Then they laid them down To rest, and so received the balm of sleep.

VIII

.

NOW morn in saffron robes had shed her light O'er all the earth, when Jove the Thunderer Summoned the gods to council on the heights Of many-peaked Olympus. He addressed The assembly, and all listened as he spake : — s "Hear, all ye gods and all ye goddesses! While I declare the thought within my breast. Let none of either sex presume to break The law I give, but cheerfully obey, That my design may sooner be fulfilled. » Whoever, stealing from the rest, shall seek To aid the Grecian cause, or that of Troy, Back to Olympus, scourged and in disgrace, Shall he be brought, or I will seize and hurl The offender down to rayless Tartarus, •s Deep, deep in the great gulf below the earth, With iron gates and threshold forged of brass, As far beneath the shades as earth from heaven. Then shall he learn how greatly I surpass All other gods in power. Try if ye will, *, Ye gods, that all may know: suspend from heaven A golden chain; let all the immortal host Cling to it from below: ye could not draw, Strive as ye might, the all-disposing Jove From heaven to earth. And yet, if I should choose To draw it upward to me, I should lift,
With it and you, the earth itself and sea Together, and I then would bind the chain Around the summit of the Olympian mount, And they should hang aloft. So far my power *, Surpasses all the power of gods and men." He spake ; and all the great assembly, hushed In silence, wondered at his threatening words, Until at length the blue-eyed Pallas said : — "Our Father, son of Saturn, mightiest as Among the potentates, we know thy power Is not to be withstood, yet are we moved With pity for the warlike Greeks, who bear An evil fate and waste away in war. If such be thy command, we shall refrain - * From mingling in the combat, yet will aid The Greeks with counsel which may be their guide, Lest by thy wrath they perish utterly." The Cloud-compeller Jove replied, and smiled: — "Tritonia, daughter dear, be comforted. « I spake not in the anger of my heart, And I have naught but kind intents for thee. He spake, and to his chariot yoked the steeds, Fleet, brazen-footed, and with flowing manes Of gold, and put his golden armor on, s» And took the golden scourge, divinely wrought, And, mounting, touched the coursers with the lash To urge them onward. Not unwillingly Flew they between the earth and starry heaven, Until he came to Ida, moist with springs
And nurse of savage beasts, and to the height Of Gargarus, where lay his sacred field, And where his fragrant altar fumed. He checked Their course, and there the Father of the gods And men released them from the yoke and caused A cloud to gather round them. Then he sat, Exulting in the fulness of his might, Upon the summit, whence his eye beheld The towers of Ilium and the ships of Greece. Now in their tents the long-haired Greeks had shared ,* A hasty meal, and girded on their arms. The Trojans, also, in their city armed Themselves for war, as eager for the fight, Though fewer; for a hard necessity Forced them to combat for their little ones 70 And wives. They set the city-portals wide, And forth the people issued, foot and horse Together, and a mighty din arose. And now, when host met host, their shields and spears Were mingled in disorder; men of might 7s Encountered, cased in mail, and bucklers clashed Their bosses; loud the clamor: cries of pain And boastful shouts arose from those who fell And those who slew, and earth was drenched with blood. While yet't was morning, and the holy light *, Of day grew bright, the men of both the hosts
ere smitten and were slain; but when the sun Stood high in middle heaven, the All-Father took His golden scales, and in them laid the fates «« Which bring the sleep of death, — the fate of those Who tamed the Trojan steeds, and those who warred For Greece in brazen armor. By the midst He held the balance, and, behold, the fate Of Greece in that day's fight sank down until *, It touched the nourishing earth, while that of Troy Rose and flew upward toward the spacious heaven. With that the Godhead thundered terribly From Ida's height, and sent his lightnings down Among the Achaian army. They beheld In mute amazement and grew pale wilh fear. *s Then neither dared Idomeneus remain, Nor Agamemnon, on the ground, nor stayed The chieftains Ajax, ministers of Mars. Gerenian Nestor, guardian of the Greeks, Alone was left behind, and he remained «» Unwillingly. A steed of those that drew His car was sorely wounded by a shaft Which Alexander, fair-haired Helen's spouse, Sent from his bow. It pierced the forehead where The mane begins, and where a wound is death. 10s The arrow pierced him to the brain ; he reared And whirled in torture with the wound, and scared His fellow-coursers. While the aged man Hastened to sever with his sword the thongs That bound him to the car, the rapid steeds
Of Hector bore their valiant master on With the pursuing crowd. The aged chief Had perished then, if gallant Diomed Had not perceived his plight. He lifted up His voice, and, shouting to Ulysses, said : — «s "High-born Ulysses, man of subtle shifts, Son of Laertes, whither dost thou flee? Why like a coward turn thy back? Beware, Lest there some weapon smite thee. Stay and guard This aged warrior from his furious foe." i»» So spake he; but the much-enduring man, Ulysses, heard not the reproof, and passed Rapidly toward the hollow ships of Greece. Tydides, single-handed, made his way Among the foremost warriors, till he stood «s Before the horses of the aged son Of Neleus, and in winged accents said : — "The younger warriors press thee sore, old chief! Thy strength gives way; the weariness of age Is on thee; thy attendant is not strong; Thy steeds are slow. Mount, then, my car, and see What Trojan horses are ; how rapidly They turn to right and left, and chase and flee. I took them from the terror of the field, ./Eneas. To our servants leave thine own, .e While we with these assault the Trojan knights, - And teach even Hector that the spear I wield Can make as furious havoc as his own." He spake; and Nestor, the Gerenian knight,
Complied. The two attendants, valiant men, — 1*, Sthenelus and the good Eurymedon, — Took charge of Nestor's steeds. The chieftains climbed The car of Diomed, and Nestor took Into his hand the embroidered reins and lashed The horses with the scourge. They quickly came To Hector. As the Trojan hastened on, .«s The son of Tydeus hurled a spear; it missed, But spared not Eniopeus, him who held The reins, the hero's charioteer, and son Of brave Thebaeus. In the breast between .s» The paps it smote him ; from the car he fell, And the swift horses started back; his soul And strength passed from him. Hector bitterly Grieved for his death, yet left him where he fell, And sought another fitting charioteer. 'ss Nor had the fiery coursers long to wait A guide, for valiant Archeptolemus, The son of Iphitus, was near at hand. And him he caused to mount the chariot drawn By his fleet steeds, and gave his hand the reins. ,, Then great had been the slaughter ; fearful deeds Had then been done ; the Trojans had been scared Into their town like lambs into the fold, — Had not the Father of the immortal gorls And mortal men beheld, and from on high ,sr Terribly thundered, sending to the earth A bolt of fire. He flung it down before
The car of Diomed ; and fiercely glared The blazing sulphur; both the frightened steeds Cowered trembling by the chariot. Nestor's hand Let fall the embroidered reins; his spirit sank n, With fear, and thus he said to Diomed :— "Tydides, turn thy firm-paced steeds, and flee. Dost thou not see that victory from Jove Attends thee not? To-day doth Saturn's son 173 Award the glory to the Trojan chief. Hereafter he will make it ours, if such Be his good pleasure. No man, though he be The mightiest among men, can thwart the will Of Jupiter, with whom abides all power." ,*, The great in battle, Diomed, replied :— "Truly, O ancient man, thou speakest well; But this it is that grieves me to the heart, — That Hector to the Trojan host will say, 'I put to flight Tydides, and he sought iss Shelter among his ships.' Thus will he boast Hereafter; may earth open then for me!" And Nestor, the Gerenian knight, rejoined :— "What, son of warlike Tydeus, hast thou said? Though Hector call thee faint of heart and weak, i*, The Trojans and Dardanians, and the wives Of the stout-hearted Trojans armed with shields, Whose husbands in their youthful prime thy hand Hath laid in dust, will not believe his words." Thus having said, he turned the firm-paced steeds Rearward, and mingled with the flying crowd.
And now the Trojans and their leader gave A mighty cry, and poured on them a storm Of deadly darts, and crested Hector raised His thundering voice and shouted after them :— *» "O son of Tydeus! the swift-riding Greeks Have honored thee beyond all other men, At banquets, with high place and delicate meats And flowing cups. They will despise thee now, For thou art like a woman. Timorous girl! 10s Take thyself hence, and never think that I Shall yield to thee, that thou mayst climb our towers And bear away our women in thy ships; For I shall give thee first the doom of death." He spake; and Diomed, in doubtful mood, »i0 Questioned his spirit whether he should turn His steeds and fight with Hector. Thrice the thought Arose within his mind, and thrice on high Uttered the all-forecasting Jupiter His thunder from the Idaean mount, a sign »is Of victory changing to the Trojan side. Then Hector to the Trojans called aloud : — "Trojans and Lycians all, and ye who close In deadly fight, the sons of Dardanus! Acquit yourselves like men, my friends ; recall »e Your fiery valor now, for I perceive The son of Saturn doth award to me Victory and vast renown, and to the Greeks
Destruction. Fools! who built this slender wan Which we contemn, which cannot stand before =s The strength I bring; our steeds can overleap The trench they digged. When I shall reach their fleet, Remember the consuming power of fire, That I may give their vessels to the flames, And hew the Achaians down beside their prows, »*, While they are wrapped in the bewildering smoke." He spake; and then he cheered his coursers thus : — "Xanthus, Podargus, Lampus nobly bred, And /Ethon, now repay the generous care, The pleasant grain which my Andromache, 23s Daughter of great Eetion, largely gives. She mingles wine that ye may drink at will Ere yet she ministers to me, who boast To be her youthful husband. Let us now Pursue with fiery haste, that we may seize m» The shield of Nestor, the great fame of which Has reached to heaven, — an orb of massive gold Even to the handles. Let us from the limbs Of Diomed, the tamer of fleet steeds, Strip off the glorious mail that Vulcan forged: v. This done, our hope may be that all the Greeks Will climb their galleys and depart to-night." So boasted he; but queenly Juno's ire Was kindled, and she shuddered on her throne Till great Olympus trembled. Thus she spake
To Neptune, mighty ruler of the deep . — "Earth-shaker! thou who rulest far and wide! Is there no pity for the perishing Greeks Within that breast of thine? They bring to thee At Helice and ^Egse costly gifts »ss And many, wherefore thy desire should be That they may win the victory. If the gods Who favor the Achaians should combine To drive the Trojans back, and hold in check High-thundering Jupiter, the God would sit In sullen grief on Ida's top alone." Earth-shaking Neptune answered in disdain :— "O Juno, rash in speech! what words are these? Think not that I can wish to join the gods In conflict with the monarch Jupiter, ass The son of Saturn, mightier than we all." So held they colloquy. Meanwhile the space Betwixt the galleys and the trench and wall Was crowded close with steeds and shielded men; For Hector, son of Priam, terrible «7» As Mars the lightning-footed, drave them on Before him. Jove decreed him such renown. And now would he have given that noble fleet To the consuming flame, if Juno, queen Of heaven, had not beheld, and moved the heart »7s Of Agamemnon to exhort the Greeks That they should turn and combat. With quick steps He passed beside the fleet, among the tents,
Bearing in his strong hand his purple robe, And climbed the huge black galley which had brought ,*, Ulysses to the war, — for in the midst It lay, and thence the king might send his voice To either side, as far as to the tents Of Ajax and Achilles, who had moored Their galleys at the different extremes »ss Of the long camp, confiding in their might Of arm and their own valor. Thence he called, With loud, clear utterance, to the Achaian host: — "O Greeks! shame on ye! cravens who excel In form alone! Where now are all the boasts »» Of your invincible valor, — the vain words Ye uttered pompously when at the feast In Lemnos sitting ye devoured the flesh Of horned beeves, and drank from bowls of wine, Flower-crowned, and bragged that each of you would be A match for fivescore Trojans, or for twice Fivescore? And now we all are not a match For Hector singly, who will give our fleet Soon to consuming flames. O Father Jove, Was ever mighty monarch visited y* By thee with such affliction, or so robbed Of high renown! And yet in my good ship, Bound to this luckless coast, I never passed By thy fair altars that I did not burn The fat and thighs of oxen, with a prayer
That I might sack the well-defended Troy. Now be at least one wish of mine fulfilled, — That we may yet escape and get us hence; Nor let the Trojans thus destroy the Greeks." He spake, and wept. The All-Father, pitying him, Consented that his people should escape 3" The threatened ruin. Instantly he sent His eagle, bird of surest augury, Which, bearing in his talons a young fawn, The offspring of a nimble-footed roe, ws Dropped it at the fair altar where the Greeks Paid sacrifice to Panomphaean Jove. And they, when they beheld, and knew that Jove Had sent the bird, took courage, rallying, And rushed against the Trojans. Then no chief v Of all theGreeks— though many they—could boast That he before Tydides urged his steeds To sudden speed and drave them o'er the trench, And mingled in the combat. First of all He struck down Agelaus, Phradmon's son, 3»s Armed as he was, who turned his car to fly, And as he turned, Tydides with his spear Transfixed his back between the shoulder-blades, And drave the weapon through his breast. He fell To earth, his armor clashing with his fall. »0 Then Agamemnon followed, and with him His brother Menelaus; after these The chieftains Ajax, fearful in their strength; Idomeneus, and he who bore his arms,—
Meriones, like Mars in battle-field; as Eurypylus, Evaemon's glorious son; And ninthly Teucer came, who bent his bow Beneath the shield of Ajax Telamon, — For Ajax moved his shield from side to side, And thence the archer looked abroad, and aimed w, His arrows thence. Whoever in the throng Was struck fell lifeless. Teucer all the while, As hides a child behind his mother's robe, Sheltered himself by Ajax, whose great shield Concealed the chief from sight. What Trojan first Did faithful Teucer slay? Orsilochus, -»* Daetor, and Ophelestes, Ormenus, Chromius, and Lycophontes nobly born, And Hamopaon, Polyremon's son, And Mel.*iippus, — one by one the shafts 3s0 Of Teucer stretched them on their mother earth. Then Agamemnon, king of men, rejoiced As he beheld him, with his sturdy bow, Breaking the serried phalanxes of Troy; And came, and, standing near, bespake him thus :—- "Beloved Teucer! son of Telamon, 3* Prince of the people! ever be thy shafts Aimed thus, and thou shalt be the light and pride Of Greece, and of thy father Telamon, Who reared thee from a little child with care s, In his own halls, though spurious was thy birth. Go on to do him honor, though he now Be far away. And here I say to thee,—
And I will keep my word, — if Jupiter The ^Egis-bearer and Minerva deign *s To let me level the strong walls of Troy, To thee will I assign the noblest prize After my own, — a tripod, or two steeds And chariot, or a wife to share thy bed." And thus the blameless Teucer made reply : — n« "Why, glorious son of Atreus, wouldst thou thus Admonish me, while yet I do my best, And pause not in the combat? From the time When we began to drive the enemy back To Ilium, I have smitten and have slain m Their warriors with my bow. Eight barbed shafts I sent, and each has pierced some warlike youth; But this fierce wolf-dog have I failed to strike." He spake, and sent another arrow forth At Hector with an eager aim. It missed Its mark, but struck Gorgythion down, the brave And blameless son of Priam; through his breast The arrow went. Fair Castianira brought The warrior forth, —a dame from /Esyma, Beautiful as a goddess. As within *s A garden droops a poppy to the ground, Bowed by its weight and by the rains of spring, So drooped his head within the heavy casque. And then did Teucer send another shaft At Hector, eager still to smite. It missed v Its aim again, for Phocbus turned aside The arrow, but it struck the charioteer
Of Hector, Archeptolemus the brave, When rushing to the fight, and pierced his breast Close to the nipple; from the car he fell, 39s The swift steeds started back, and from his limbs The life and strength departed. A deep grief For his slain charioteer came darkly o'er The mind of Hector, yet, though sorrowing, He left him where he fell, and straightway called **, Cebriones, his brother, who was near, To mount and take the reins. Cebriones Heard and obeyed. Then from the shining car Leaped Hector with a mighty cry, and seized A ponderous stone, and, bent to crush him, ran «s At Teucer, who had from his quiver drawn One of his sharpest arrows, placing it Upon the bowstring. As he drew the bow, The strong-armed Hector hurled the jagged stone, And smote him near the shoulder, where the neck And breast are sundered by the collar bone, — 4n A fatal spot. The bowstring brake ; the arm Fell nerveless ; on his knees the archer sank, And dropped the bow. Then did not Ajax leave His fallen brother to the foe, but walked 41s Around him, sheltering him beneath his shield, Till two dear friends of his — Menestheus, son Of Echius, and Alastor nobly born — Approached, and took him up and carried him, Heavily groaning, to the hollow ships. Then did Olympian Jove again inspire
The Trojan host with valor, and they drave The Achaians backward to the yawning trench. Then Hector came, with fury in his eyes, Among the foremost warriors. As a hound, es Sure of his own swift feet, attacks behind The lion or wild boar, and tears his flank, Yet warily observes him as he turns, So Hector followed close the long-haired Greeks, And ever slew the hindmost as they fled. o0 Yet now, when they in flight had crossed again The trench and palisades, and many a one Had died by Trojan hands, they made a halt Before their ships, and bade each other stand, And lifted up their hands and prayed aloud as To all the gods; while Hector, urging on His long-maned steeds, and with stern eyes that seemed The eyes of Gorgon or of murderous Mars, Hither and thither swept across the field. The white-armed Juno saw, and, sorrowing, «= Addressed Minerva with these winged words : — "Ah me! thou daughter of the God who bears The aegis, shall we not descend to aid The perishing Greeks m their extremity? A cruel doom is theirs, to fall, destroyed «s By one man's rage, — the terrible assault Of Hector, son of Priam, who has made Insufferable havoc in the field." And thus in turrt the blue-eyed Pallas spake:—
"That warrior long eie this had lost his life, 4s0 Slain by the Greeks on his paternal soil, But that my father's mind is warped by wrath. Unjust to me and harsh, he thwarts my aims, Forgetting all I did for Hercules, His son, — how often, when Eurystheus set va A task too hard for him, I saved his life. To heaven he raised his eyes and wept, and Jove Despatched me instantly to succor him. And yet if I, in my forecasting mind, Had known all this when he was bid to bring From strong-walled Erebus the dog of hell, He had not safely crossed the gulf of Styx. But now Jove hates me; now he grants the wish Of Thetis, who hath kissed his knees and touched His beard caressingly, and prayed that he Would crown the overthrower of walled towns, Achilles, with great honor. Well, the time Will come when he shall call me yet again His dear Minerva. Hasten now to yoke For us thy firm-paced steeds, while in the halls 470 Of aegis-bearing Jupiter I brace My armor on for war, — and I shall see If Hector of the beamy helm, the son Of Priam, will rejoice when we appear Upon the field again. Assuredly «s The men of Troy shall die, to feast the birds Of prey and dogs beside the Grecian fleet." She ended, and the white-armed deity
Juno obeyed her. Juno the august, The mighty Saturn's daughter, hastily «, Caparisoned the golden-bitted steeds. Meanwhile, Minerva on the palace-floor Of Jupiter let drop the gorgeous robe Or many hues, which her own hands had wrought, And, putting on the Cloud-compeller's mail, «ss Stood armed for cruel war. And then she climbed The glorious car, and took in hand the spear — Huge, heavy, strong —- with which she overthrows The serried phalanxes of valiant men Whene'er this daughter of the Almighty One «s» Is angered. Juno bore the lash, and urged The coursers to their speed. The gates of heaven Opened before them of their own accord, — Gates guarded by the Hours, on whom the care Of the great heaven and of Olympus rests, m To open or to close the wall of cloud. Through these they guided their impatient steeds. From Ida Jupiter beheld, in wrath, And summoned Iris of the golden wings, And bade her do this errand : " Speed thee hence, s00 Fleet Iris! turn them back; allow them not Thus to defy me : it is not for them To engage with me in war. I give my word, — Nor shall it lack fulfilment, — I will make The swift steeds lame that draw their car, and hurl The riders down, and dash the car itself s« To fragments. Ten long years shall wear away
Before they cease to suffer from the wounds Made by the thunderbolt. Minerva thus May learn the fate of those who strive with Jove s» With Juno I am less displeased, for she Is ever bent to thwart my purposes." He spake; and Iris, with the tempest's speed Departing, bore the message from the heights Of Ida to the great Olympus, where, s1s Among the foremost passes of the mount, All seamed with hollow vales, she met and stayed The pair, delivering thus the word of Jove :— "Now whither haste ye? What strange madness fires Your breasts? The son of Saturn surfers not s*, That ye befriend the Greeks. He threatens thus, — And will fulfil his threat, — that he will make The coursers lame that draw your car, and hurl The riders down, and dash the car itself To fragments, and that ten long years must pass s»s Ere ye shall cease to suffer from the wounds Made by the thunderbolt. So shalt thou leam, O Pallas! what it is to strive with Jove. With Juno is he less displeased, for she Is ever bent to thwart his purposes; s3° But thou, he says, art guilty above all, And shameless as a hound, if thou dare lift Thy massive spear against thy father Jove." So spake fleet-footed Iris, and withdrew; And thus again to Pallas Juno said:— as
"Child of the AEgis-bearer! let us strive With Jove no longer for the sake of men, But let one perish and another live, As chance may rule the hour, and let the God, Communing with his secret mind, mete out s40 To Greeks and Trojans their just destiny." She spake, and turned the firm-paced coursers back, The coursers with fair-flowing manes. The Hours Unyoked them, bound them to the ambrosial stalls, And leaned against the shining walls the car; 34s While Juno and Minerva went among The other deities and took their place Upon their golden seats, though sad at heart. Then with his steeds, and in his bright-wheeled car, Came Jove from Ida to the dwelling-place Of gods upon Olympus. There did he Who shakes the islands loose the steeds and bring The chariot to its place, and o'er it spread Its covering of lawn. The Thunderer Seated himself upon his golden throne, sss The great Olympus trembling as he stepped; While Juno and Minerva sat apart Together, nor saluted him, nor asked Of aught; but he perceived their thoughts and said : — "Juno and Pallas! why so sad? Not long s*, Ye toiled in glorious battle to destroy The Trojans, whom ye hold in bitter hate:
This strength of mine, and this invincible arm Not all the gods upon the Olympian mount Can turn to flight, while your fair limbs were seized With trembling ere ye entered on the shock sm And havoc of the war. Now let me say — And well the event would have fulfilled my words — That, smitten with the thunder from my hand, Your chariots never would have brought you back 370 To this Olympus and the abode of gods." He spake ; while Pallas and the queen of heaven Repined with close-pressed lips, and in their hearts Devised new mischiefs for the Trojan race. Silent Minerva sat, nor dared express as The anger that she bore her father Jove; But Juno could not curb her wrath, and spake :— "What words, austere Saturnius, hast thou said? Thou art, we know, invincible in might; Yet must we sorrow for the heroic Greeks, 380 Who, by a cruel fate, are perishing. We stand aloof from war, if thou require; Yet would we counsel the Achaian host, Lest by thy wrath they perish utterly." And then the Cloud-compeller, answering, said : — "O Juno, large-eyed and august, if thou s«. Look forth to-morrow, thou shalt then behold The all-powerful son of Saturn laying waste With greater havoc still the mighty host Of warlike Greeks. For Hector, great in war, s» Shall pause not from the conflict, till he rouse
The swift-paced son of Peleus at the ships, When, pent in narrow space, the armies fight For slain Patroclus: such the will of fate. As for thyself, I little heed thy rage: 593 Not even shouldst thou wander to the realm Where earth and ocean end, where Saturn sits Beside Iapetus, and neither light Of overgoing suns nor breath of wind Refreshes them, but gulfs of Tartarus «90 Surround them, — shouldst thou even thither bend Thy way, I shall not heed thy rage, who art Beyond all others shamelessly perverse." He ceased ; but white-armed Juno answered not. And now into the sea the sun's bright light «0s Went down, and o'er the foodful earth was drawn Night's shadow. Most unwillingly the sons Of Troy beheld the sunset. To the Greeks Eagerly wished the welcome darkness came. Then from the fleet illustrious Hector led «» The Trojans, and beside the eddying stream, In a clear space uncumbered by the slain, Held council. There, alighting from their cars, They listened to the words that Hector spake, — Hector, beloved of Jove. He held a spear, «is In length eleven cubits, with a blade Of glittering brass, bound with a ring of gold. On this he leaned, and spake these winged words: — "Hear me, ye Trojans, Dardans, and allies. But now I thought that, having first destroyed
The Achaian host and fleet, we should return This night to wind-swept Ilium. To their aid The darkness comes, and saves the Greeks, and saves Their galleys ranged along the ocean-side. Obey we, then, the dark-browed night; prepare ,*.$ Our meal; unyoke the steeds with flowing manes, And set their food before them. Bring at once Oxen and fatlings of the flock from town, And from your dwellings bread and pleasant wine. And let us gather store of wood, to feed A multitude of blazing fires all night, Till Morning, daughter of the Dawn, appear, — Fires that shall light the sky, lest in the hours Of darkness with their ships the long-haired Greeks Attempt escape across the mighty deep. «^ And, that they may not climb their decks unharmed. Let every foeman bear a wound to cure At home, — an arrow-wound or gash of spear,. Given as he leaps on board. So other foes Shall dread a conflict with the knights of Troy. «*• And let the heralds, dear to Jove, command That all grown youths and hoary-headed men Keep watch about the city in the towers Built by the gods ; and let the feebler sex Kindle large fires upon their hearths at home; ,*s And let the guard be strengthened, lest the foe Should steal into the city while its sons Are all abroad. Thus let it be till morn,
Brave Trojans! I but speak of what the time Requires, and on the morrow I shall speak 630 Of what the Trojan knights have then to do. My prayer to Jove and to the other gods, And my hope is, that I may drive away These curs, brought hither by an evil fate In their black ships. All night will we keep watch, And, arming, with the early morn renew «s' The desperate conflict at the hollow ships. Then shall I see if valiant Diomed Tydides has the power to make me leave The Grecian galleys for the city-walls, «, Or whether I shall slay him with my spear And take his bloody spoils. To-morrow's sun Will make his valor known, if he withstand The assault of this my weapon. Yet I think The sunrise will behold him slain among The first, with many comrades lying round. Would that I knew myself as certainly Secure from death and the decays of age, And to be held in honor like the gods Apollo and Minerva, as I know ,*, This day will bring misfortune to the Greeks!" So Hector spake, and all the Trojan host Applauded; from the yoke forthwith they looped The sweaty steeds, and bound them to the cars With halters; to the town they sent in haste «71 For oxen and the fatlings of the flock, And to their homes for bread and pleasant wine,
And gathered fuel in large store. The winds Bore up the fragrant fumes from earth to heaven. So, high in hope, they sat the whole night through In warlike lines, and many watch-fires blazed. osi As when in heaven the stars look brightly forth Round the clear-shining moon, while not a breeze Stirs in the depths of air, and all the stars Are seen, and gladness fills the shepherd's heart, «ss So many fires in sight of Ilium blazed, Lit by the sons of Troy, between the ships And eddying Xanthus : on the plain there shone A thousand ; fifty warriors by each fire Sat in its light. Their steeds beside the cars — Champing their oats and their white barley — stood, And waited for the golden morn to rise.

IX

.

THE Trojans thus kept watch ; while through JL the night The power of Flight, companion of cold Fear, Wrought on the Greeks, and all their bravest men Were bowed beneath a sorrow hard to bear. The north wind and the west, that suddenly Blow from the Thracian coast; the black waves rise At once, and fling the sea-weed to the shore, —Thus were the Achaians troubled in their hearts. Atrides, deeply grieving, walked the camp, ,» And bade the clear-voiced heralds call by name To council all the chiefs, but not aloud. The king himself among the foremost gave The summons. Sadly that assembly took Their seats ; and Agamemnon in the midst is Rose, shedding tears, — as down a lofty rock, Darkening its face, a fountain's waters flow, — And, deeply sighing, thus addressed the Greeks :— "O friends! the chiefs and princes of the Greeks 1 Saturnian Jove hath in an evil snare *, Most cruelly entangled me. He gave His promise once that I should overthrow This strong-walled Ilium, and return; but now He meditates a fraud, and sends me back To Argos without glory, and with loss 3s Of many warriors. Thus doth it seem good Doubtless to Jove Almighty, who hath cast The towers of many a city down to earth, And will cast others down, — his might excels All other might. But let us now obey, *, As I shall counsel you, and in our ships Haste to our own dear country; for I see That Troy with its broad streets can ne'er be ours." He spake; and all were silent. Silent long Remained the sorrow-stricken sons of Greece, ss Till Diomed, the brave in battle, spake :— "First of the chiefs I speak, to disapprove, Page 222 222 The Iliad. Atrides, thy rash purpose: 't is my right In council ; nor, O king, be thou displeased. Thou first among the Greeks hast taunted me « With lack of valor, calling me unapt For war and weak of arm. The young and old Have heard the taunt. One of two gifts the son Of wily Saturn hath bestowed on thee: High rank and rule o'er all the rest he gave, « But gave thee not the nobler quality Of fortitude. Dost thou then truly deem The Greeks unapt for war and weak of arm, As thou hast said? Thou longest to return: Go, then ; the way is open; by the sea s0 The barks that brought thee from Mycenae lie, A numerous fleet. Yet others will remain — Long haired Achaians — till we overthrow The city. Should they also pine for home, Then let them flee, with all their ships ; while I ss With Sthenelus fight on until we make An end of Troy, — for with the gods we came." He spake. The Greeks applauded; all admired The words of the horse-tamer Diomed. Nestor the knight then rose, and thus he spake :— "O son of Tydeus, eminently brave « Art thou among thy comrades in the field, And great in council. No one here condemns The sentence thou hast given ; among the Greeks Is no one who denies what thou hast said; Yet hast thou not said all. Thy years are few, — Page 223 Book IX. 223 So few, thou mightest be my youngest son; And yet thou speakest wisely to the kings Of Greece, and thy discourse is just and right. Now I, who boast of far more years than thou, r, Will speak of this that yet remains, and none — Not even Agamemnon — will gainsay What I advise. A wretch without a tie Of kin, a lawless man without a home, Is he who takes delight in civil .strifes. 7s But let us now give way to the dark night, And make our banquets ready. Let the guards Lie down within the trenches which we digged Without the wall: be this the young men's charge. And thou, Atrides, do thou now begin, a, Who art supreme, and make a feast for all The elder chiefs; it shall become thee well: Thy tents are full of wine, which ships from Thrace Bring every day across the mighty deep, And thou hast all things ready, and a host ss Of menials. Then, when many throng the board, Thou shalt defer to him who counsels thee Most wisely ; for the Greeks have urgent need Of prudent counsels, when the foe so close Beside our galleys lights his multitude 90 Of watch-fires. Who that sees them can rejoice r This night will rescue or destroy our host." He spake. They listened all, and willingly Obeyed him. Forth in armor went the guards, Led by the chieftain Thrasymedes, son »s Page 224 224 The Iliad. Of Nestor, by Ascalaphus, who claimed His birth from Mars, and by Ialmenus His brother, and Deipyrus, with whom There followed Aphareus, Meriones, And Lycomedes, Creon's noble son. 1«, Seven were the leaders of the guards; with each A hundred youths in warlike order marched, Bearing long spears; and when they reached the space Between the trench and wall they sat them down, And kindled fires and made their evening meal. tos Atrides brought the assembled elder chiefs To his pavilion, and before them set A generous banquet. They put forth their hands And shared the feast; and when the calls of thirst And hunger ceased, the aged Nestor first »o Began to counsel them ; the chief, whose words Had lately seemed of wisest import, now Addressed the assembly with well-ordered speech: — "Atrides Agamemnon, glorious king! What I shall say begins and ends with thee, 11s For thou dost rule o'er many nations. Jove Hath given to thee the sceptre, and the power To make their laws, that thou mayst seek their good. Thou, therefore, of all men, shouldst speak and hear In council, and shouldst follow willingly «° Another's judgment when it best promotes The general weal; for all depends on thee. Now let me say what seems to me most wise; Page 225 Book IX. 225 For better counsel none can give than this Which now I meditate, and which to give «s I purposed from the hour when thou, great king, Didst bear the maid Briseis from the tent Of the enraged Achilles, unapproved By me, who strove to change thy rash design. Then didst thou yield thee to thy haughty will, 130 And didst dishonor a most valiant man, Whom the immortals honor. Thou didst take And still dost keep the prize he fairly won. Let it be now our study to appease The hero with large gifts and soothing words." Then Agamemnon, king of men, replied :— "O ancient man, most truly hast thou named My faults. I erred, and I deny it not. That man indeed is equal to a host Whom Jupiter doth love and honor thus, ,*, Humbling the Achaian people for his sake. And now, since, yielding to my wayward mood I erred, let me appease him', if I may, With gifts of priceless worth. Before you all I number them, — seven tripods which the fire us Hath never touched, six talents of pure gold, And twenty shining caldrons, and twelve steeds Of hardy frame, victorious in the race, Whose feet have won me prizes in the games. No beggar would he be, nor yet with store Of gold unfurnished, in whose coffers lay The prizes those swift steeds have brought to me. 10 • o Page 226 226 The Iliad. Seven faultless women, skilled in household arts, I give moreover, — Lesbians, whom I chose When he o'erran the populous Lesbian isle, — ,ss Damsels in beauty who excel their sex. These I bestow, and with them I will send Her whom I took away, — Briseis, pure — I swear it with a mighty oath — as pure As when she left his tent. All these I give ,&, At once ; and if by favor of the gods We lay the mighty city of Priam waste, He shall load down his galley with large store Of gold and silver, entering first when we, The Greeks, divide the spoil. Then may he choose Twice ten young Trojan women, beautiful «s« Beyond their sex save Helen. If we come Safe to Achaian Argos, richly stocked With milky kine, he may become to me A son-in-law, and cherished equally 170 With my sole son Orestes, who is reared Most royally. Three daughters there, within My stately palace-walls, — Chrysothemis, Laodice, and Iphianassa, — dwell, And he may choose among them, and may lead ,n Home to the house of Peleus her who best Deserves his love. Nor need he to endow The bride, for I will give an ampler dower Than ever father to his daughter gave, — Seven cities with thronged streets, —Cardamyle, •*, Enope, grassy Hira, Pherae famed Page 227 Book IX. Afar, Antheia with rich pasture-fields, /Epeia beautiful, and Pedasus With all its vineyards; all are near the sea, And stand the last before you reach the coast Of sandy Pylos. Rich in flocks and herds Their dwellers are, and they will honor him As if he were a god, and, ruled by him, Will pay large tribute. These will I bestow, Let but his anger cool and his resolve Give way. 'T is Pluto who is deaf to prayer And ne'er relents, and he, of all the gods, Most hateful is to men. Now let the son Of Peleus yield at length to me, who stand Above him in authority and years." Then answered Nestor the Gerenian knight: - "Atrides Agamemnon! glorious king! Gifts not to be contemned thou offerest To Prince Achilles. Let us now despatch A chosen embassy, who shall proceed At once to where Pelides holds his tent . I name the men ; and cheerfully will they Perform the duty: Phoenix, dear to Jove, Shall be their leader, mighty Ajax next, And then high-born Ulysses; heralds twain Shall follow, — Hodius and Eurybates. And now be water brought to cleanse our hands, And charge be given that no ill-omened word Be uttered, while we pray that Jupiter, The son of Saturn, will assist our need." Page 228 228 The Iliad. He spake; and all approved the words he said. Then poured the heralds water on the hands Of those who sat. The young men crowned with wine The goblets, and in seemly order passed The brimming cups, distributing to each. «s Part to the gods they poured, and next they drank As each might choose, and then the embassy Hastened from Agamemnon's tent. To each Gerenian Nestor spake in turn, and fixed His eyes on each intently, — most of all « Upon Ulysses, — and with many a charge To turn Pelides from his angry mood. Along the edge of the resounding deep They went, and as they walked they offered prayer To earth-embracing Neptune, that their words "s Might move the great soul of ^Eacides. And now they came where lay the Myrmidons Among their tents and ships. Achilles there Drew solace from the music of a harp Sweet-toned and shapely, in a silver frame, **, Part of the spoil he took when he o'erthrew Eetion's town. To soothe his mood he sang The deeds of heroes. By him sat alone Patroclus, silent till the song should cease. On moved the messengers, — before them walked High-born Ulysses, — till they stood beside f Achilles. He beheld, and with the harp Sprang from his seat, surprised. Patroclus saw The heroes also, and arose. Their hands Page 229 Book IX. 229 The swift Achilles took in his, and said : — v» "Welcome! Ye come as friends. Some press- ing cause Must surely bring you hither, whom I prize, Wronged as I am, beyond all other Greeks." Thus speaking, the great son of Peleus led His guests still farther on, and seated them «s On couches spread with purple coverings, And thus addressed Patroclus, who was near: — "Son of Menoetius, bring a larger vase, And mingle purer wine, and place a cup For each, since these are most beloved friends, — »s, These warriors who now sit beneath my roof." He spake. Patroclus hearkened, and obeyed His well-beloved friend, who meantime placed A block beside the fire, and on it laid Chines of a sheep and of a fatling goat, ,ss And of a sow, the fattest of her kind. Automedon stood by and held them fast; Achilles took the knife and skilfully Carved them in portions, and transfixed the parts With spits. Patroclus, the divine in form, *» Woke to a blaze the fire ; and when the flame Had ceased to rise he raked the glowing coals Apart, and o'er them stretched the spits, and strewed, Raising the flesh, the sacred salt o'er all. And when he had made ready and had spread *t The banquet on the board, Patroclus took Page 230 230 The Iliad. The bread and offered it to all the guests In shapely canisters. Achilles served The meats, and took his seat against the wall, In front of great Ulysses. There he bade m His friend Patroclus offer sacrifice, Casting the first rich morsels to the flames. The guests put forth their hands and shared the feast; And when the calls of hunger and of thirst Were felt no longer, Ajax gave a nod »7s To Phoenix, which divine Ulysses saw, And filled his cup and drank to Peleus' son :— "Thy health, Achilles! Princely feasts like this Attend us both in Agamemnon's tent And here, —for here is all that makes a feast **, Complete ; yet now is not the time to think Of pleasant banquets, for our thoughts are turned — O Jove-born warrior ! — to a fearful time Of slaughter, and the fate of our good ships, — Whether we save them harmless, or the foe Destroy them, if thou put not on thy might. For now the haughty Trojans, and the troops Who come from far to aid them, pitch their camp Close to our fleet and wall, and all around Kindle their many fires, and boast that we No longer have the power to drive them back From our black galleys. Jupiter, the son Of Saturn, shows them favorable signs With lightnings from above; and, terrible Page 231 Book IX. In aspect and in valor, Hector makes m Sad havoc, trusting in the aid of Jove, And neither reverences gods nor men, — Such rage possesses him. He prays that soon The morn may rise, that he may hew the prows From all our ships and give them to the flames, *» And slay the Greeks, bewildered with the smoke. For me, I greatly fear the gods will grant That he fulfil his threat, and that our doom Will be to perish on the Trojan coast, And far away from Argos, famed for steeds. w Rise, then, though late, — rise with a resolute mind, And from the hard-pressed sons of Greece drive back The assailing Trojans. Thou wilt else lament Hereafter, when the evil shall be done And shall admit no cure. Bethink thee well 310 How from the Greeks thou mayst avert the day Of their destruction. O my friend, when first He sent thee forth to Agamemnon's help From Phthia's coast, thy father Peleus said : — "' My child, from Juno and Minerva comes 31s The gift of valor, if they choose to give.- But curb thou the high spirit in thy breast, For gentle ways are best, and keep aloof From sharp contentions, that the old and young Among the Greeks may honor thee the more.' m "Such was the old man's charge, forgotten now. Yield, then, and lay thy wrath aside. Large gifts Doth Agamemnon offer, to appease Page 232 232 The Iliad. Thy wounded spirit. Hear me, if thou wilt, Recount what gifts the monarch in his tent « Hath promised thee : — Seven tripods which the fire Hath never touched; six talents of pure gold; And twenty shining caldrons; and twelve steeds Of hardy frame, victorious in the race, Whose feet have won him prizes in the games. &, No beggar would he be, nor yet with store Of gold unfurnished, in whose coffers lay The prizes those swift-footed steeds have won. Seven faultless women, skilled in household arts, He offers, — Lesbians, whom he chose when thou Didst overrun the populous Lesbian isle, — n» In beauty eminent among their sex. These he bestows, and with them he will send Her whom he took away, — Briseis, pure — He swears it with a mighty oath — as pure 3*, As when she left thy tent. All these he gives At once ; and if, by favor of the gods, We lay the mighty city of Priam waste, Thou shalt load down thy galley with large store Of gold and silver, entering first when we, 34s The Greeks, divide the spoil. Then mayst thou choose Twice ten young Trojan women, beautiful Beyond their sex save Helen. If we come Safe to Achaian Argos, richly stocked With milky kine, thou mayst become to him 39 A son-in-law, and cherished equally Page 233 Book IX. 233 With his sole son Orestes, who is reared Right royally. Three daughters there, within The monarch's stately halls, — Chrysothemis, Laodice, and Iphianassa, —dwell, 35s And thou mayst choose among them, and mayst lead Home to the house of Peleus her who best Deserves thy love. Nor needest thou endow The bride, for he will give an ampler dower Than ever father to his daughter gave, — 3«0 Seven cities with thronged streets, — Cardamyle, Enope, grassy Hira, Pherae famed Afar, Antheia with rich pasture-grounds, ^Epeia beautiful, and Pedasus With all its vineyards ; all are near the sea, ses And stand the last before you reach the coast Of sandy Pylos. Rich in flocks and herds Their dwellers are, and they will honor thee As if thou wert a god, and, ruled by thee, Will pay large tribute. These will he bestow, x70 Let but thine anger cease. But if the son Of Atreus and his gifts still move thy hate, At least have pity on the afflicted Greeks, Pent in their camp, who now would honor thee As if thou wert a god; and thou shalt gain »s Great glory as their champion, and shalt slay This Hector, who even now is close at hand, And in a murderous frenzy makes his boast That none of all the chieftains whom the fleet Page 234 234 The Iliad. Of Greece brought hither equals him in might." The swift Achilles answered him and said : — "Son of Laertes, nobly born, and versed In wise devices, let me frankly speak Just as I think, and just as I shall act, And then ye will not importune me more. Hateful to me, as are the gates of hell, Is he who, hiding one thing in his heart, Utters another. I shall speak as seems To me the best; nor deem I that the son Of Atreus or the other Greeks can move My settled purpose, since no thanks are paid To him who with the enemy maintains A constant battle: equal is the meed Of him who stands aloof and him who fights Manfully; both the coward and the brave Are held in eqial honor, and they die An equal death, — the idler and the man Of mighty deeds. For me there is no store Of wealth laid up from all that I have borne, Exposing life in battle. As a bird Brings to her unfledged young the food she finds, Though she herself be fasting, so have I Had many a night unvisited by sleep, And passed in combat many a bloody day, Fighting beside these w.uriors for their wives. Twelve cities have I with my fleet laid waste, And with my Myrmidons have I o'erthrown Eleven upon this fertile Trojan coast. Page 235 Book IX. 235 Full many a precious spoil from these I bore, And to Atrides Agamemnon gave. 410 He, loitering in his fleet, received them all; Few he distributed, and many kept. To chiefs and princes he indeed assigned Prizes, which now they hold. From me alone Of all the Greeks he takes my prize; he takes -its My bride, whom well I loved ;— and let him keep The damsel. But what need is there that Greeks Wage war against the Trojans? For what cause Did Agamemnon, gathering from our realms An army, lead it hither? Was it not v0 Because of fair-haired Helen? Are the sons Of Atreus, then, the only men on earth Who love their wives? Nay, every good man loves And cherishes his spouse ; and mine I loved Tenderly, though the captive of my spear: 4»s And now, since he hath taken my reward Away and treacherously dealt with me, Let him not try again, for I am warned, And he will not persuade me. Let him take Counsel with thee, Ulysses, and the rest, «o How to drive back the enemy and save The fleet from flames. Already has he done Much without me ; a rampart he has raised, And round it dug a deep, broad trench, and filled The trench with palisades. Yet can he not - 433 Resist the man-destroyer Hector thus. This Hector, when I fought among the Greeks, Page 236 236 The Iliad. Never would fight at distance from the walls, And ventured not beyond the Scaean gates And beechen tree. There waited he for me v» Upon a time, and scarce escaped with life From my assault. Now, since I do not choose To fight with noble Hector, I shall pay, To-morrow, sacrifice to Jupiter And all the gods, and load my galleys well, 44s And draw them to the water. Then shalt thou See — if thou care for such a sight — my ships Sailing upon the fishy Hellespont At early morning, with their crews on board Eager to pull the oar; and if the god 4s» Of ocean grant a prosperous voyage, then On the third day we reach the fertile coast Of Phthia. Large possessions left I there When I came hither in an evil hour; And thither I shall carry with me gold 43s And ruddy brass, and women of fair forms, And burnished steel, — the spoils I won in war. The prize he gave me, Agamemnon, son Of Atreus, takes, with many insults, back. Bear him this message, —give it openly, 4«0 That others of the Greeks may be like me Indignant should he impudently dare To wrong them also :— Let him ne'er again, Though shameless, dare to look me in the face. I will not join in council or in act 4t* With him: he has deceived and wronged me once, Page 237 Book IX. 237 • And now he cannot wheedle me with words. Let once suffice. I leave him to himself, To perish. All-providing Jupiter Hath made him mad. I hate his gifts; I hold 470 In utter scorn the giver. Were his gifts Tenfold — nay, twenty-fold — the worth of all That he possesses, and with added wealth From others, — all the riches that flow in Upon Orchomenus, or Thebes, the pride 47s Of Egypt, where large treasures are laid up, And through whose hundred gates rush men and steeds, Two hundred through each gate ; — nay, should he give As many gifts as there are sands and dust Of earth, — not even then shall Atreus' son 4*, Persuade me, till I reap a just revenge For his foul contumelies. I will wed No child of Agamemnon Even though She vied with golden Venus in her charms, And with the blue-eyed Pallas in her skill, #s I would not wed her. Let him choose among The Greeks a fitter husband, — one whose rule Is wider than my own. For if the gods Preserve me, and I reach my home again, My father, Peleus, will bestow on me 4,» A consort. Many are the Achaian maids, Daughters of chiefs who hold our citadels In Hellas, and in Phthia, and of these, Page 238 238 T/u: Iliad. Her who shal! most delight me I will make My well-beloved wife. My soul has longed Earnestly, with a fitting spouse betrothed Duly, to make my dwelling there, and there Enjoy the wealth which aged Peleus won; For not to be compared with life is all The wealth which, as men say, was treasured up In Ilium's populous town in time of peace, Ere the Greeks came, nor all the stores contained Within the stony threshold of the god Who bears the bow, Apollo, on the coast Of rocky Pytho. We may gather spoil Of oxen and of fatling sheep, and bring Tripods from war, and yellow-maned steeds: The breath of man no force can seize or hold, And when it leaves the enclosure of the teeth It comes not back. My mother said to me — The goddess, silver-footed Thetis, said — A twofold fate conducts me to my death;— If I remain to fight beneath the walls Of Ilium, my return will be cut off, But deathless my renown ; if I return To the dear land in which my fathers dwell, My glory will be nought, but long my life, And late will come to me the stroke of death. And now I counsel all to sail for home, For never will ye see the overthrow Of lofty Ilium. Jove the Thunderer Stretches his great hand o'er her, and htr sonj Page 239 Book IX. 239 Take courage. Go ye now, and take with you This message to the princes of the Greeks, — As is the office of an embassy, — s»s And bid them meditate some wiser plan To save their galleys and the host of Greeks Within the hollow barks. The plan which brought You hither cannot serve you while I keep My anger unappeased. Let Phoenix stay «0 To pass the night with us, that he may sail To-morrow, if it please him, to the land We love; I take him not against his will." He ceased; and silent were the ambassadors, Astonished at his passionate words. At last ai Phoenix, the aged knight, with many tears And sighs, took up the word, in grief and fear Lest Hector should destroy the Grecian fleet: — "Illustrious son of Peleus, if indeed Thou wilt return, nor carest to repel s*, From our swift galleys the consuming fire, Because thou art offended, how shall I, Dear child, remain without thee? When at first Peleus, the aged knight, from Phthia sent Thee, yet a boy, to Agamemnon's aid, s4s Unskilled as then thou wert in cruel war And martial councils, — where men also gain A great renown, — he sent me with thee, charged To teach thee both, that so thou mightst become In words an orator, in warlike deeds ss, An actor. Therefore, my beloved child, Page 240 240 The Iliad. Not willingly shall I remain behind; Not even though a god should promise me That, overcoming the decays of age, I might become a beardless youth again, sss As when from Hellas and its companies Of lovely maids I came a fugitive, And left Amyntor, son of Ormenus,— My father, —angry with me for the sake Of a fair-tressed wanton, whom he loved, Treating my mother basely. To my knees My mother came and prayed me ceaselessly, First, to possess the woman, that she then Might loathe the elder one; and I obeyed. My father knew it, and with many a curse Invoked the hateful furies to forbid That any child who owed his birth to me Should ever sit upon his knees. The gods — The Jove of Hades and dread Proserpine — Confirmed his curse. To slay him with the sword s70 Was my first thought. Some god subdued my wrath, Reminding me of what the public voice Would say, and infamy that would ensue, — Lest I among the Achaians should be called A parricide. I could not brook to dwell s7s Within my father's palace while he thus Was wroth with me. My kindred and my friends Came round me, and besought me to remain, And stayed beside me. Many a fatling ewe And many a slow-paced ox with curving horns s*, Page 241 Book IX. They slew, and many a fattened swine they stretched Over the flame of Vulcan. From the casks Of the old chief his wine was freely drawn. Nine nights they slept surrounding me, while each Kept watch in turn : nor ever were the fires sfc Put out; one blazed beneath the portico Of the fair hall, and near the chamber-door Another glimmered in the vestibule. But when upon me rose the tenth dark night, I broke my aptly-jointed chamber-doors, s9» And issued forth, and easily o'erleaped The wall around the palace, quite unseen Of watching men and of the serving maids. I fled through spacious Hellas to the fields Of Phthia, nurse of flocks, and to her king, s,s Peleus, who kindly welcomed me, and loved Me as a father loves his only son, Born to large wealth in his declining years. He made me rich, and gave me sovereign rule Over much people. My abode was fixed In farthest Phthia, where I was the prince Of the Dolopians. As for thee, my care, Godlike Achilles, made thee what thou art . I loved thee from my soul: thou wouldst not go With any other to the feast, nor take &,s Thy food at home until upon my knees I placed thee, carved thy meats, and gave them thee, And poured thy wine. The tunic on my breast Was often wetted by thee when the wine vol. i. ii r Page 242 242 The Iliad. Gushed in thy petulant childhood from thy lips. Thus many things did I endure for thee, And many toils perform ; and since the gods Vouchsafed no son to me, it was my thought To train thee as a son, that thou mightst be, O godlike man! the bulwark of my age. «*s And now subdue that mighty spirit of thine: 111 it becomes thee to be merciless: The gods themselves are placable, though far Above us all in honor and in power And virtue. We propitiate them with vows, e~ Incense, libations, and burnt-offerings, And prayers for those who have offended. Prayers Are daughters of almighty Jupiter, — Lame, wrinkled, and squint-eyed, — that painfully Follow Misfortune's steps; but strong of limb *s And swift of foot Misfortune is, and, far Outstripping all, comes first to every land, And there wreaks evil on mankind, which prayers Do afterwards redress.' Whoe'er receives Jove's daughters reverently when they approach, *3, Him willingly they aid, and to his suit They listen. Whosoever puts them by With obstinate denial, they appeal To Jove, the son of Saturn, and entreat That he will cause Misfortune to attend The offender's way in life, that he in turn May suffer evil and be punished thus. Wherefore, Achilles! do thou also yield Page 243 Book IX. 243 The honor due Jove's daughters, freely given By other valiant men. If Atreus' son «*, Brought thee no gifts, nor promised others still, But kept his anger, I would never ask That thou shouldst lay aside thy wrath and come To help the Argives in their bitter need. But he bestows large gifts, and adds a pledge &ts Of others yet in store, and he hath sent The best men of the army, who to thee Are dearest, to entreat thee. Spurn thou not These, nor their embassy, although at first Thine anger was not causeless. We have heard «» The praise of heroes of the elder time, Inflamed to vehement anger, yet appeased By gifts, and yielding to persuasive words. One instance I remember: long ago It happened, and I will relate it here «ss Among my friends. Around the city-walls Of Calydon did the Curetes strive In battle with the /Etolians; they destroyed Each other fearfully. The /Etolians fought To save the pleasant town of Calydon, k», And the Curetes warred to lay it waste. Diana of the golden throne had caused The war, displeased with CEneus, who withheld From her the first-fruits of his fertile field: While hecatombs were burnt in sacrifice «s To feast the other gods, to her alone — Daughter of Jove — no offering was brought; Page 244 244 The Iliad. For either he forgot, or thought the rite Of little moment; but he greatly erred. And now the child of Jove, the archer-queen, Incensed, sent forth against him from the wood A white-tusked wild boar, which upon his lands Entered, and ravaged them, and brought to earth Many tall trees : tree after tree they fell, With roots uptorn, and all the blossoms on, That promised fruit. Him Meleager, son Of CEneus, slew, with many hunters called From neighboring cities, bringing many hounds. A few could not subdue him : he had made Many already mount the funeral pile. Diana kindled round the boar a strife For the beast's head and bristly hide, — a war 'Twixt the Curetes and the /Etolian band Of braves. The war, while Meleager fought, Went not with the Curetes, nor could they, Though many, keep the field. But wrath at last Seized Meleager, — wrath, which rages oft Even in prudent minds. Incensed against Althaea, his own mother, he remained At home with Cleopatra, his young wife, The beauteous, whom a delicate-footed dame, Marpessa, daughter of Evenus, bore To Idas, bravest in his time among The sons of men,— so brave that once he drew A bow against Apollo for the sake Of his neat-footed bride. The honored pair Page 245 Book IX. 245 Within the palace used to call their child Alcyone; for when the archer-god, Apollo, from her husband bore away The mother, Cleopatra sadly wailed, 700 As wails the halcyon. So beside his spouse Dwelt Meleager, brooding ever o'er The violent anger which his mother's curse Had kindled. Grieving for a brother's death, She supplicated heaven, and often struck 70s Her hands against the teeming earth, and called— Kneeling, her bosom all bedewed with tears — On Pluto and the cruel Proserpine, To put her son to death. From Erebus The pitiless Erinnys, wandering 710 In darkness, heard the prayer. Then straightway rose A sound of fearful tumult at the gates: The towers were battered,-and the elder chiefs Of the /Etolians hastened to entreat The aid of Meleager, and they sent 71s Priests of the gods, a chosen band, to pray That he would come to their defence. Large gifts They promised. Where the soil of Calydon Was best, they bade him choose a fruitful field Of fifty acres, half for vines, and half, 7» Cleared of the trees, for tillage. Earnestly Did aged CEneus, famed for horsemanship, Beseech him; to the chamber of his son, High-roofed, he climbed, and at the threshold shook Page 246 246 The Iliad. The massive doors with knocking as he sued. -m His sisters and his reverend mother joined Their supplications: he resisted still. And much his friends, the dearest and most prized, Besought him, but they vainly strove to swerve His steadfast mind, till his own chamber felt n, The assault, and the Curetes climbed the walls To fire the populous city. Then the nymph, His graceful wife, entreated him with tears, And spake of all the horrors which o'ertake A captured city, — all the men cut off 735 By massacre, the houses given to flames, The children and deep-bosomed women dragged Into captivity. Her sorrowful words He heard; his spirit was disturbed ; he went To gird his glittering armor on, and thus 7» He saved the /Etolians from a fearful doom, Obeying his own impulse. The reward Of rare and costly gifts they gave him not, Though thus he rescued them. Be not thy thought Like his, my friend ; let no invisible power m Persuade thee thus to act. Far worse it were To wait, and when our fleet is all on fire Offer thy aid. Accept the gifts at once: Then will the Greeks, as if thou wert a god, Hold thee in honor. If without the gifts 730 Thou enter later on the field of fight, Thou wilt not have like honor with the host, Although thou turn the assault of battle back." Page 247 Book IX. 247 Then did Achilles, swift of foot, reply : — "O ancient Phoenix, father, loved of Jove, • Such honor need I not; for the decree Of Jove, I deem, already honors me, And will detain me by my beaked ships While breath is in my lungs, and I have power To move these knees. Yet one thing I would say, — And bear it thou in mind, — vex not my soul With weeping and lamenting for the sake Of Agamemnon ; it becomes thee not — Thou who art loved by me — to yield thy love To him, unless thou wouldst incur my hate. its And thou shouldst be the enemy of him Who wrongs me. Reign thou equally with me, And share my honors. These will carry back My answer. Thou remain, and, softly couched, Sleep here: with early morn will we consult v, Whether to leave this region or remain." He spake, and, nodding to Patroclus, gave A signal to prepare an ample couch For Phoenix, while the other chiefs prepared To leave the tent. Then Ajax Telamon, 77s The godlike chief, addressed his comrades thus : — "Son of Laertes, nobly born, and skilled In sage devices, let us now depart, Since, as it seems, the end for which we came Cannot be compassed thus, and we must bear 7*, With speed the unwelcome answer to the Greeks, Who sit expecting us; while in his breast Page 248 248 The Iliad. The implacable Achilles bears a fierce And haughty heart, nor doth he heed the claim Of that close friendship of his fellow-chiefs, Which at the Grecian fleet exalted him Above all others. Unrelenting one! Even for a brother's death a price is paid, Or when a son is slain: the slayer dwells At home among his people, having made The appointed expiation. He to whom The fine is offered takes it, and his thirst Of vengeance is appeased. But in thy heart The gods have kindled an unquenchable rage, All for a single damsel, -— and behold, Seven more we offer, passing beautiful, With many gifts beside. Let, then, thy mood Be softened : have respect to thine own roof; For we are guests beneath it, sent from all The assembled host, and strong is our desire To be thy dearest and most cherished friends Of all the Achaians, many as they are." Achilles the swift-footed answered thus : — "Illustrious Ajax, son of Telamon, Prince of the people! all that thou hast said, I well perceive, is prompted by thy heart. Mine swells with indignation when I think How King Atrides mid the assembled Greeks Heaped insults on me, as if I had been A wretched vagabond. But go ye now And bear my message. I shall never think Page 249 Book IX. 249 Of bloody war till noble Hector, son Of Priam, slaughtering in his way the Greeks, Shall reach the galleys of the Myrmidons, To lay the fleet in flames. But when he comes 315 To my own tent and galley, he, I think, Though eager for the combat, will desist." He spake. Each raised a double cup and poured Libations to the gods; they then returned Beside the fleet. Ulysses led the way. &» Patroclus bade the attendant men and maids Strew with all speed a soft and ample bed For Phoenix. They obeyed, and spread the couch With skins of sheep, dyed coverlets, and sheets Of lawn; and there the old man lay to wait &s The glorious morn. Meantime Achilles slept Within the tent's recess, and by him lay Phorbas's daughter, whom he carried off From Lesbos, — Diomede, rosy-cheeked. Upon the other side Patroclus lay, «30 With slender-waisted Iphis by his side, Given by the great Achilles when he took Scyros the tall, where Enyeus ruled. Now when the ambassadors were come within The tent of Agamemnon, all the chiefs «3s Rose, one by one, and, lifting up to them Their golden goblets, asked the news they brought And first Atrides, king of men, inquired :— "Renowned Ulysses, glory of the Greeks! Tell me, will he protect our fleet from flames, a*, 11* Page 250 250 The Iliad. Or does he, in his wrath and pride, refuse?" Then spake the hardy chief Ulysses thus :— "Atrides Agamemnon, glorious king Of men! he will not let his wrath abate, But rages yet more fiercely, and contemns Thee and thy gifts. He leaves thee to consult With thine Achaians by what means to save The fleet and army; for himself he means To-morrow, with the early dawn, to launch His well-appoiuted galleys on the sea, And will advise the other Greeks to spread The sails for home, since they will never see The overthrow of lofty Troy, for Jove The Thunderer stretches his protecting hand Above her, and her sons have taken heart. Such are his words ; and those who went with me Are present, — Ajax and the heralds both, Sage men, — the witnesses to what I say. The aged Phoenix stays behind to sleep, And on the morrow to attend his chief To their beloved country, — if he will, For else by no means will he take him hence." He spake; and all were silent, all amazed At what they heard, for these were bitter words. Long sat the sons of Greece in silent thought, Till Diomed, the great in battle, spake :— "Atrides Agamemnon, glorious king Of men! I would thou hadst not deigned to ask The illustrious son of Peleus for his aid,With offer of large gifts; for arrogant a70 He is at all times: thou hast made him now More insolent. Now leave him to himself, To go or to remain : he yet will fight When his mood changes, or some god within Shall move him. Let us do what I advise :— «7s Betake we all ourselves to rest, but first Refresh ourselves with food and wine; in them Is strength and spirit. When the rosy morn Shall shine, command thou that the foot and horse Be speedily drawn up before the fleet, sso And thou encourage them with cheerful words, And fight among them in the foremost rank." He spake. The kings assented, and admired The words of the horse-tamer Diomed; And, pouring out libations, to their tents «s They all departed, and lay down to rest, And took into their souls the balm of sleep.

XI

.

NOW did the Morning from her couch beside Renowned Tithonus rise, that she might bring The light to gods and men, when Jupiter To the swift galleys of the Grecian host Sent baleful Strife, who bore in hand aloft 5 War's ensigns. On the huge black ship that brought Ulysses, in the centre of the fleet, She stood, where she might shout to either side, — To Telamonian Ajax in his tents And to Achilles, who had ranged their ships «o At each extreme of the Achaian camp, Relying on their valor and strong arms. Loud was the voice, and terrible, in which She shouted from her station to the Greeks, And into every heart it carried strength is And the resolve to combat manfully And never yield. The battle now to them Seemed more to be desired than the return To their dear country in their roomy ships. Atrides called aloud, exhorting them »o To gird themselves for battle. Then he clad Himself in glittering brass. First to his thighs He bound the beautiful greaves with silver clasps, Then fitted to his chest the breastplate given By Cinyras, a pledge of kind intent;— »s For, when he heard in Cyprus that the Greeks Page 277 Book XI. 277 Were bound for Ilium in their ships, he sent This gift, a homage to the king of men ; — Ten were its bars of tawny bronze, and twelve Were gold, and twenty tin ; and on each side 30 Were three bronze serpents stretching toward the neck, Curved like the colored bow which Saturn's son Sets in the clouds, a sign to men. He hung His sword, all glittering with its golden studs, About his shoulders. In a silver sheath » It nestled, which was .slung on golden rings. And then he took his shield, a mighty orb, And nobly wrought and strong and beautiful, Bound with ten brazen circles. On its disk Were twenty bosses of white tin, and one « Of tawny bronze just in the midst, where glared A Gorgon's-head with angry eyes, round which Were sculptured Fear and Flight. Along its band Of silver twined a serpent wrought in bronze, With three heads springing from one neck and formed « Into an orb. Upon his head he placed A helmet rough with studs on every side, And with four bosses, and a horse-hair plume That nodded fearfully on high. He took In hand two massive spears, brass-tipped and sharp, That shone afar and sent their light to heaven, s1 Where Juno and Minerva made a sound Like thunder in mid-sky, as honoring Page 278 278 The Iliad. The sovereign of Mycenae rich in gold. Each chief gave orders to his charioteer ss To stay his horses firmly by the trench, While they rushed forth in arms. At once arose, Ere yet the sun was up, a mighty din. They marshalled by the trench the men on foot; The horse came after, with short space between. ,so The son of Saturn sent among their ranks Confusion, and dropped down upon the host Dews tinged with blood, in sign that he that day Would send to Hades many a_ valiant chief. The Trojans, on their side, in the mid-plain »s Drew up their squadrons on a hill, around The mighty Hector, and Polydamas The blameless, and ^Eneas, who among The sons of Troy was honored like a god, And three sons of Antenor, who were named 70 Agenor and the noble Polybus And the young Acamas of godlike bloom, There Hector in the van uplifted bore His broad round shield. As some portentous star Breaks from the clouds and shines, and then again Enters their shadow, Hector thus appeared -s Among the foremost, issuing his commands, Then sought the hindmost. All in brass, he shone Like lightnings of the ^Egis-bearer, Jove. As when two lines of reapers, face to face, » In some rich landlord's field of barley or wheat Move on, and fast the severed handfuls fall, Page 279 Book XL So, springing on each other, they of Troy And they of Argos smote each other down, And neither thought of ignominious flight. They met each other man to man; they rushed Like wolves to combat. Cruel Strife looked on Rejoicing; she alone of all the gods Was present in the battle; all the rest, Par off, sat quiet in their palaces, The glorious mansions built for them along The summits of Olympus. Yet they all Blamed Saturn's son that he should honor thus The Trojans. The All-Father heeded not Their murmurings, but, seated by himself Apart, exulting in his sovereignty, Looked on the city of Troy, the ships of Greece, The gleam of arms, the slayers, and the slain. While yet't was morn, and still the holy light Of day was brightening, fast the weapons smote On either side, and fast the people fell; But at the hour when on the mountain-slope The wood cutter makes ready his repast, Weary with felling lofty trees, and glad To rest, and eager for the grateful meal. The Greeks, encouraging each other, charged And broke the serried phalanxes of Troy. Firs' Agamemnon, springing forward, slew The shepherd of his people and their chief, Bienor, and his trusty comrade next, — The charioteer Oileus, who had leaped Page 280 28o The Iliad. Down from his chariot to confront the king. Him Agamemnon with his trenchant spear Smote in the forehead as he came. The helm Of massive brass was vain to stay the blow: m The weapon pierced it and the bone, and stained The brain with blood ; it felled him rushing on. The monarch stripped the slain, and, leaving them With their white bosoms bare, went on to slay Isus and Antiphus, King Priam's sons, — ,*, One born in wedlock, one of baser birth, — Both in one chariot. Isus held the reins While Antiphus, the high-born brother, fought. These had Achilles once on Ida's height Made prisoners, as they fed their flocks ; he bound Their limbs with osier bands, but gave them up m For ransom to the Trojans. Now the king Of men, Atrides Agamemnon, pierced Isus above the nipple with his spear, And with his falchion smiting Antiphus '30 Beside the ear, he hurled him from his car. Then hastening up, and stripping from the dead Their shining mail, he knew them ; he had seen Both at the ships to which the fleet of foot, Achilles, brought them bound from Ida's side. ,3s As when a lion comes upon the haunt Of a swift hind, to make an easy prey Of her young fawns, and, with his powerful teeth Seizing them, takes their tender lives; while she, Though nigh, can bring no aid but yields herself ,*, Page 281 Book XI. 281 To mortal fear, and, to escape his rage, Flies swiftly through the wood of close-grown oaks, With sweaty sides, — thus none of all the host Of Trojans could avert from Priam's sons Their fate, but fled in terror from the Greeks. us Next on Pisander and Hippolochus Atrides rushed, — brave warriors both, and sons Of brave Antimachus, the chief who took Gold and rich gifts from Paris, and refused To let the Trojans render Helen back To fair-haired Mcnelaus. His two sons, Both in one car, and reining their fleet steeds, Atrides intercepted; they let fall The embroidered reins, dismayed, as, lion-like, Forward he came; and, cowering, thus they prayed : — 1ss "Take us alive, Atrides, and accept A worthy ransom, for Antimachus Keeps in his halls large treasures, — brass and gold. And well-wrought steel; and he will send, from these, Large ransom, hearing we are at the fleet '*, Alive." So prayed they with bland words, and met Harsh answer : " Since ye call Antimachus Your father, who in Trojan council once Proposed that Menelaus, whom we sent A legate with Ulysses the divine, «s Should not return to Greece, but suffer death, Your blood must answer for your father's guilt." So spake the king, and, striking with his spear Page 282 282 The Iliad. I'isander's breast, he dashed him from the car. Prone on the ground he lay. Hippolochus 170 Leaped down and met the sword. Atrides lopped His hands and drave the weapon through his neck, And sent the head to roll among the crowd. And then he left the dead, and rushed to where The ranks were in disorder; with him went 17s Hiswell-armed Greeks; there they who fought on foot Slaughtered the flying foot; the horsemen there Clove horsemen down : the coursers' trampling feet Raised the thick dust to shadow all the plain; While Agamemnon cheered the Achaians on, ,&, And chased and slew the foe. As when a fire Seizes a thick-grown forest, and the wind Drives it along in eddies, while the trunks Fall with the boughs amid devouring flames, So fell the flying Trojans by the hand . *$ Of Agamemnon. Many high-maned steeds Dragged noisily their empty cars among The ranks of battle, never more to bear Their charioteers, who lay upon the earth The vulture's feast, a sorrow to their wives. 190 But Jove beyond the encountering arms, the dust, The carnage, and the bloodshed and the din Bore Hector, while Atrides in pursuit Was loudly cheering the Achaians on. Meantime the Trojans fled across the plain ,qs Toward the wild fig-tree growing near the tomb Page 283 Book XI. 283 Of ancient Ilus, son of Dardanus, — Eager to reach the town ; and still the son Of Atreus followed, shouting, and with hands Blood-stained and dust-begrimed. And when they reached The Seaman portals and the beechen tree, They halted, waiting for the rear, like beeves Chased panting by a lion who has come At midnight on them, and has put the herd To flight, and one of them to certain death, — ~s Whose neck he breaks with his strong teeth and then Devours the entrails, lapping up the blood. Thus did Atrides Agamemnon chase The Trojans; still he slew the hindmost; still They fled before him. Many by his hand »10 Fell from their chariots prone, for terrible Beyond all others with the spear was he. But when he now was near the city-wall, The Father of immortals and of men Came down from the high heaven, and took his seat On many-fountained Ida. In his grasp ,•«, He held a thunderbolt, and this command He gave to Iris of the golden wings: — "Haste, Iris fleet of wing, and bear my words To Hector : — While he sees the king of men, m Atrides, in the van and dealing death Among the ranks of warriors, let him still Give way, encouraging his men to hold Unflinching battle with the enemy. Page 284 284 The Iliad. But when Atrides, wounded by a spear »»s Or arrow, shall ascend his chariot, then Will I nerve Hector's arm with strength to slay Until he come to the good ships of Greece, And the sun set, and hallowed night come down." He spake; and she, whose feet are like the wind In swiftness, heeded the command, and flew «3i From Ida's summit to the sacred town Of Troy, and found the noble Hector, son Of warlike Priam, standing mid the steeds And the strong chariots, and, approaching, said :— "O Hector, son of Priam, and like Jove rrs In council! Jove the All-Father bids me say, As long as thou shalt see the king of men, Atrides, in the van, and dealing death Among the ranks of warriors, thou shalt still wo Give way, encouraging thy men to hold Unflinching battle with the enemy; But when Atrides, wounded by a spear Or arrow, shall ascend his chariot, then Will Jove endue thy arm with strength to slay us Until thou come to the good ships of Greece, And the sun set, and hallowed night come down." So the fleet Iris spake, and went her way; While Hector, leaping from his car in arms, And wielding his sharp spears, went everywhere »s0 Among the Trojan ranks, exhorting them To combat, and renewed the stubborn fight. They rallied and stood firm against the Greeks. Page 285 Book XL 285 The Greeks, in turn, made strong their phalanxes. The battle raged again, as front to front ass They stood, while Agamemnon eagerly- Pressed forward, proud tc lead the van in fight. Say, Muses, dwellers of Olympus! who First of the Trojans or their brave allies Encountered Atreus' son? Iphidamas, **, Son of Antenor, strong and daring, bred On the rich soil of Thrace, the nurse of flocks. His grandsire Cisseus, from whose loins the fair Theano sprang, had reared him from a child Within his palace; and, when he attained *>s Youth's glorious prime, still kept him, giving him His child to wife. He wedded her, but left At once the bridal chamber when he heard Of the Greek war on Ilium, and set sail With twelve beaked galleys. These he afterward »70 Left at Percope, — marching on to Troy. And he it was who came to meet the son Of Atreus. As the heroes now drew near Each other, Agamemnon missed his aim; His thrust was parried. Then Iphidamas »7s Dealt him beneath the breastplate on the belt A vigorous blow, and urged the spear with all His strength of arm ; yet through the plated belt It could not pierce, for there it met a plate Of silver, and its point was turned like lead. * With lion strength, Atrides seized and drew The weapon toward him< plucked it from the hand Page 286 286 The Iliad. That held it, and let fall his falchion's edge Upon the Trojan's neck and laid him dead. Unhappy youth! he slept an iron sleep, — ^ Slain fighting for his country, far away From the young virgin bride yet scarcely his, For whom large marriage-gifts he made, — of beeves A hundred, — and had promised from the flocks That thronged his fields a thousand sheep and goats. Atrides Agamemnon spoiled the slain, *>i And bore his glorious armor off among The Argive host. Antenor's elder son, Illustrious Coon, saw, and bitter grief For his slain brother dimmed his eyes. He stood Aside, with his spear couched, while unaware The noble Agamemnon passed, and pierced The middle of the monarch's arm below The elbow; through the flesh the shining point Passed to the other side. The king of men, *■ Atrides, shuddered, yet refrained not then From combat ; but with his wind-seasoned spear He rushed on Ccon, who, to drag away His father's son Iphidamas, had seized The body by the feet, and called his friends, » The bravest, to his aid. Atrides thrust His brazen spear below the bossy shield, And slew him as he drew the corpse, and o'er The dead Iphidamas struck off his head. Thus were Antenor's sons — their doom fulfilled — Sent by Atrides to the realm of death. 3n Page 287 Book XI. 287 And then he ranged among the enemy's ranks With wielded lance and sword and ponderous stones, While yet the warm blood issued from his wound. But when the wound grew dry, and ceased to flow v% With blood, keen anguish seized his vigorous fram As when a woman feels the piercing pangs Of travail brought her by the Ilythian maids, Daughters of Juno, who preside at births, And walk the ministers of bitter pains, — 3*, Such anguish seized on Agamemnon's frame; And, leaping to his chariot-seat, he bade The guider of the steeds make haste to reach The roomy ships, for he was overcome y» With pain ; but first he shouted to the Greeks : — "O friends, the chiefs and princes of the Greeks! Yours is the duty to drive back the war From our good ships, since all-disposing Jove Forbids me, for this day, to lead the fight." He spake. The charioteer applied the lash, 330 And not unwillingly the long-maned steeds Flew toward the hollow ships; upon their breasts Gathered the foam ; beneath their rapid feet Arose the dust, as from the battle's din They bore the wounded warrior. Hector saw «s The flight of Agamemnon, and aloud Called to the Trojans and the Lycians thus : — "Trojan and Lycian warriors, and ye sons Of Dardanus, who combat hand to hand, Be men; be mindful of your fame in war. 340 Page 288 288 The Iliad. Our mightiest foe withdraws; Saturnian Jove Crowns me with glory. Urge your firm-paced steeds On the brave Greeks, and win yet nobler fame." He spake. His words gave courage and new strength To every .heart. As when a hunter cheers us His white-toothed dogs against some lioness Or wild boar from the forest, Hector thus, The son of Priam, terrible as Mars The slayer of men, cheered on the gallant sons Of Troy against the Greeks. Himself, inspired 3s» With fiery valor, rushed among the foes In the mid-battle foremost, like a storm That swoops from heaven, and on the dark-blue sea Falls suddenly, and stirs it to its depths. Who then was slain the first, and who the last, 3ss By Hector, Priam's son, whom Jove designed To honor? First, Asaeus; Uolops, son Of Clytis ; and Autonoiis; and then Opites and Opheltius; next to whom ^ssymnus, Agelaus, Orus fell, j&, And resolute Hipponoiis the last. All these, the princes of the Greeks, he slew, Then smote the common crowd. As when a gale Blows from the west upon the mass of cloud Piled up before the south-wind's powerful breath, 343 And tears it with a mighty hurricane, While the swoln billows tumble, and their foam Is flung on high before the furious blast, Page 289 Book XI. 289 So by the sword of Hector fell the heads Of the Greek soldiery; and there had been sro Ruin and ravage not to be repaired, And the defeated Greeks had flung themselves Into their ships, had not Ulysses then Exhorted thus Tydides Diomed :— "Tydides! what has quenched within our hearts Their fiery valor? Come, my friend, and take sv, Thy stand beside ma: foul disgrace were ours Should crested Hector make our fleet his prize." And thus the valiant Diomed replied :— "Most willingly I stand, and bear my part 3*, In battle; but with little hope, for Jove, The God of storms, awards the day to Troy.'' He spake, and pierced ThymbnEus with his spear Through the left breast, and dashed him from his car. Meanwhile Ulysses struck Molion down, 3»s The prince's stately comrade. These they left Never to fight again, and made their way Through the thick squadrons, carrying, as they went, Confusion with them. As two fearless boars Rush on the hounds, so, mingling in the war, i*, They bore the foe before them, and the Greeks Welcomed a respite from the havoc made By noble Hector. Next they seized a car Which bore two chiefs, the bravest of their host, — Sons of Percosian Merops, who was skilled 39s Beyond all men in portents. He enjoined His sons to keep aloof from murderous war. vol. 1. 13 a Page 290 290 The Iliad. Yet did they not obey him, for the fate That doomed the twain to death impelled them on; And Diomed, the mighty with the spear, *» Spoiled them of life, and bore their armor off, A glittering prize. Meantime Ulysses slew Hippodamus, and next Hypirochus. The son of Saturn looked from Ida's height, And bade the battle rage on either side *,s With equal fury : both the encountering hosts Slew and were slain. Tydides with his spear Smote on the hip the chief Agastrophus, The son of Paeon, thoughtless wretch, whose steeds Were not at hand for flight; his charioteer 410 Held them at distance, while their master rushed Among the foremost warriors till he fell. Hector perceived his fall, as through the files He looked, and straightway hastened to the spot With shouts; and after him came rapidly 41s The phalanxes of Trojans. Diomed, The great in battle, shuddered as he saw, And thus addressed Ulysses, who was near : — "Lo! the destroyer, furious Hector, comes! Let us stand firm, and face and drive him back." 4•0 He said, and cast his brandished lance, nor missed The mark : it smote the helm on Hector's head. The brass glanced from the brass ; it could not pierce To the fair skin; the high and threefold helm — A gift from Phoebus — turned the point aside. «s The chief fell back, and, mingling with the throng, Page 291 Book XI. 291 Dropped on one knee, and yet upheld himself With one broad palm upon the ground, while night Darkened his eyes. The son of Tydeus sprang To seize his spear, which now stood fixed in earth Among the foremost warriors. In that time «3, Did Hector breathe again, and, having leaped Into his chariot, he avoided death, By mingling with the crowd; while, spear in hand, Brave Diomed pursued him, shouting thus :— 43s "This time, thou cur, hast thou escaped thy doom, Though it was nigh thee. Phoebus rescues thee — The god to whom thou dost address thy prayers — Whene'er thou venturest mid the clash of spears. «0 Yet will I surely slay thee when we meet, If any god be on my side ; and now I go to strike where'er I find a foe." He spake, and struck the son of Pajon down, Skilful to wield the spear. But now the spouse Of fair-haired Helen — Alexander — stood w Leaning against a pillar by the tomb Of the Dardanian Ilus, who had been An elder of the people ; and he bent His bow against the monarch Diomed, Who at that moment knelt to strip the slain 4s0 Of the rich breastplate, and the shield that hung Upon his shoulders, and the massive ensque. The Trojan drew the bow's elastic horn, And sent an arrow that not vainly flew, Page 292 292 The Iliad. But, striking the right foot, pierced through, and reached 4ss The ground beneath. Then Paris, with a laugh, Sprang from his ambush, shouting boastfully :— "Lo, thou art smitten! Not in vain my shaft Has flown; and would that it had pierced thy groin And slain thee! Then the Trojans had obtained «» Reprieve from slaughter, — they whodread thee now As bleating goats a lion." • Undismayed, The valiant Diomed made answer thus : — "Archer and railer! proud of thy smart bow, And ogler of the women! wouldst thou make «ss Trial of valor hand to hand with me, Thy bow should not avail thee, nor thy sheaf Of many arrows. Thou dost idly boast That thou hast hit my foot. I heed it not . It is as if a woman or a child «o Had struck me. Lightly falls the weapon-stroke Of an unwarlike weakling. T is not so With me, for when one feels my weapon's touch, It passes through him, and he dies; his wife Tears with her hands her cheeks; his little ones 17s Are orphans ; earth is crimsoned with his blood; And flocking round his carcass in decay, More numerous than women, are the birds." He spake. Ulysses, mighty with the spear, Came near and stood before him while he sat * Concealed, and drew the arrow from his foot. Keen was the agony that suddenly Page 293 Book XL 293 Shot through his frame: he leaped into his car, And bade his charioteer make haste to reach The roomy ships: the pain had reached his heart . Ulysses, the great spearman, now was left «ss Alone, no Greek remaining by his side; For fear had seized them all. With inward grief The hero thus addressed his mighty soul : — "What will become of me? A great disgrace «0 Will overtake me if I flee in fear Before this multitude; and worse will be My fate if I am taken here alone, While Jove has driven away the other Greeks In terror. Why these questions, since I know 4-,s That cowards skulk from combat, while the brave, Wounded or wounding others, keeps his ground?" While thus he reasoned with himself, the ranks Of Trojans armed with bucklers came and closed Around their dreaded enemy. As when y» A troop of vigorous dogs and youths assail From every side a wild boar issuing forth From a deep thicket, whetting the white tusks Within his crooked jaws; they press around, And hear his gnashings, yet beware to come s»s Too nigh the terrible animal, — so rushed The Trojans round Ulysses, the beloved Of Jupiter. Then first the hero smote Deiopites on the shoulder-blade, And next struck Thoon down, and Ennomus, s" And in the navel pierced Chersidamas Page 294 294 The Iliad. With his sharp spear, below the bossy shield, When leaping from his chariot. In the dust He fell, and grasped the earth with dying hands. Ulysses left them there, and with his spear s1s He wounded Charops, son of Hippasus, And brother of brave Socus. Socus saw, And hastened to his aid, and, standing near, The godlike chief bespake Ulysses thus :— "Renowned Ulysses! of whose arts and toils s*, There is no end, thou either shalt to-day Boast to have slain two sons of Hippasus, Brave as they are, and stripped them of their arms, Or, smitten by my javelin, lose thy life." He spake, and smote the Grecian's orbed shield. The swift spear, passing through the shining disk, s»« And fixed in the rich breastplate, tore the skin From all his side; yet Pallas suffered not The blade to reach the inner parts. At once The chief perceived that Socus had not given s10 A mortal wound, and, falling back a step, Thus spake: "Unhappy youth, thy doom will soon O'ertake thee. Though thou forcest me to pause From combat with the Trojans, I declare, This day thou sufferest the black doom of death. s3s Thou, smitten by my spear, shalt bring to me Increase of glory, and shalt yield thy soul To the grim horseman Pluto." Thus he spake, While Socus turned to flee; and as he turned, Ulysses with the spear transfixed his back, w0 Page 295 Book XI. 295 And drave the weapon through his breast: he fell, With armor clashing, to the earth, while thus The great Ulysses gloried over him : — "O Socus! son of warlike Hippasus The horseman! death has overtaken thee, s»s And thou couldst not escape. Unhappy one! Now thou art dead thy father will not come To close thy eyes, nor she, the honored one Who gave thee birth; but birds of prey shall flap Their heavy wings above thee, and shall tear 3s» Thy flesh, while I in dying shall receive Due funeral honors from the noble Greeks." He spake, and from his wounded side drew forth, And from his bossy shield, the ponderous spear Which warlike Socus threw. A gush of blood sss Followed, and torturing pain. Now, when they saw Ulysses bleed, the gallant sons of Troy Called to each other, rushing in a crowd To where he stood. Retreating as they came, He shouted to his comrades. Thrice he raised s*, His voice as loud as human lungs could shout; Thrice warlike Menelaus heard the cry, And spake at once to Ajax at his side : — "Most noble Ajax, son of Telamon, Prince of thy people! to my ear is brought s»s The cry of that unconquerable man, Ulysses, seemingly as if the foe Had hemmed him round alone, and pressed him sore In combat. Break we through the crowd, and bring Page 296 296 The Iliad. Succor, lest harm befall him, though so brave, — 3-0 Fighting among the Trojans thus alone, — And lest the Greeks should lose their mighty chief." He spake, and led the way; his godlike friend Followed. They found Ulysses, dear to Jove, — The Trojans thronging round him like a troop s7s Of ravening jackals round an antlered stag Which one who hunts upon the mountain-side Hath stricken with an arrow from his bow: By flight the stag escapes, while yet the blood Is warm and easily the limbs are moved; ss» But when at last the shaft hath quelled his strength, The hungry jackals in the forest shade Among the hills attack him, till by chance The dreaded lion comes; alarmed, they flee, And he devours the prey. So in that hour, s«3 Many and brave, the sons of Troy pursued Ulysses, skilled in war and wiles; while he Wielded the spear and warded off the day Of death. Then Ajax, coming near him, stood, With his tall buckler, like a tower of strength s90 Beside him, and the Trojans fled in fear On all sides. Warlike Menelaus took Ulysses by the hand, and led him forth From the thronged spot, while his attendant brought The chariot near him. Ajax sprang upon »s The Trojans, slaying Doryclus, a son Of Priam basely born. Then Pandorus He wounded ; next he struck Lysander down, Page 297 Book XL 297 Pyrasus and Pylartes. As a stream, Swoln to a torrent by the showers of Jove. &» Sweeps down, from hill to plain, dry oaks and pines, And pours into the sea a muddy flood, So mighty Ajax routed and pursued The Trojans o'er the plain, and cut his way Through steeds and warriors. Hector knew not this. He fought where, on the battle's left, beside c*« The Xanthus, fastest fell the slain, and round Great Nestor and the brave Idomeneus Arose a mighty tumult. In that throng Did Hector mingle with his spear and steeds, «10 Performing feats of valor, and laid waste The ranks of youthful warriors. Yet the Greeks Would not have yielded ground, if Paris, spouse Of fair-haired Helen, had not forced the chief Machaon, fighting gallantly, to pause; «,s For with an arrow triple-barbed he pierced The chiefs right shoulder, and the valiant Greeks Feared lest the battle turn and he be slain. And thus Idomeneus to Nestor said: — "Neleian Nestor, glory of the Greeks, Haste, mount thy chariot; let Machaon take A place beside thee ; urge thy firm-paced steeds Rapidly toward the fleet; a leech like him, Who cuts the arrow from the wound and soothes The pain with balms, is worth a host to us." «s He spake; and the Gerenian knight obeyed, And climbed the car in haste. Machaon, son I3» Page 298 298 The Iliad. Of /F.sculapius the peerless leech, Mounted beside him; Nestor lashed the steeds, And toward the roomy ships, which well they knew, And longed to reach, they flew with eager speed. Meantime Cebriones, who had his seat *m By Hector in the chariot, saw the ranks Of Troy disordered, and addressed the chief: — "While we, O Hector, here are mid the Greeks Just in the skirts of the tumultuous fray, «* The other Trojans, men and steeds, are thrown Into confusion where the warriors throng, For Telamonian Ajax puts their ranks To rout; I know him well by that broad shield »« Borne on his shoulders. Thither let us drive Our steeds and chariot, where in desperate strife Meet horse and foot and hew each other down, And a perpetual clamor fills the air." «u He spake ; and with the whistling lash he struck The long-maned steeds, and, as they felt the stroke, Forward they flew with the swift car among The Greeks and Trojans, trampling in their way Corpses and shields. The axle underneath «« Was steeped in blood ; the rim of the chariot-seat Was foul with the red drops which from their hoofs The coursers sprinkled and the wheels threw up. Then Hector strove, by rushing on the crowd, To pierce it and break through it. To the Greeks His coming brought destruction and dismay; «ss And well his spear was wielded. Through the ranks Page 299 Book XI. 299 Of other warriors with the spear he ranged, With sword and ponderous stones; yet warily He shunned the fight with Ajax Tel.imon. Then Father Jove Almighty touched with fear «*, The heart of Ajax. All amazed he stood, And cast his sevenfold buckler of bull's-hide Upon his back, and, terrified, withdrew. Now casting glances like a beast of prey From side to side, he turned to right and left, «3 And, slowly yielding, moved knee after knee. As when the rustics with their hounds drive off A hungry lion from their stalls of kine, Whom, watching all the night, they suffer not To make their herd a prey ; but he, intent «70 On ravin, rushes forward, yet in vain; For many a javelin flies from daring hands Against him, many a blazing torch is swung, At which, though fierce, he trembles, and at morn Stalks off in sullen mood ;— so Ajax, sad «7s At heart, and fearing for the Grecian fleet, Unwillingly fell back before the foe. And as, when entering in a field, an ass Slow-paced, whose flanks have broken many a shaft To splinters, crops the harvest as it grows, «--0 And boys attack him with their rods, — though small Their strength, — but scarce, till he has browsed his fill, Can drive him forth, — so did the gallant sons Of Troy, and their allies from distant lands, Page 300 300 The Iliad. Continually pursue the mighty son «s Of Telamon, and hurl their spears against The centre of his shield. And now he wheeled, As conscious of great valor, and repulsed The crowding phalanxes; and now again He turned to flee. And thus he kept the foe ,&, From reaching the swift galleys, while he stood Between the Greeks and Trojans, terrible In wrath. The javelins hurled by daring hands Against him—some hung fixed in his broad shield; And many, ere they came to his fair skin, «93 Fell midway, — eager though they were to pierce The warrior's side, — and plunged into the earth. Eurypylus, Evaemon's noble son, Saw Ajax sorely pressed with many darts, And came and stood beside him, taking aim -,», With his bright spear, and in the liver smote, Beneath the midriff, Apisaon, son Of Phausias, and a prince among his tribe. His knees gave way, and down he sank in death. But godlike Alexander, who beheld 70s The slayer stripping Apisaon's corpse Of armor, at that moment bent his bow, And pierced Eurypylus in the right thigh. The reed brake in the wound. He writhed with pain, And mingled with his fellows in the ranks, 710 Avoiding death, yet shouting to the Greeks :— "O friends, the chiefs and leaders of the Greeks, Rally and keep your ground; ward off the fate Page 301 Book XI. 301 Of death from Ajax, who is sorely pressed With darts, and, much I fear, may not escape 71s Safe from this stormy conflict. S'and ye firm Around the mighty son of Telamon." So spake the wounded warrior; while his friends Rallied around him, with their shields inclined Against their shoulders, ?.nd with lifted spears. 7»0 And Ajax came and joined them; then he turned, And firmly faced the foe. The Greeks renewed The combat with a rage like that of fire. Now meantime the Neleian coursers, steeped In sweat, were bearing Nestor and the prince 7»s Machaon from the battle. On the prow Of his great ship, Achilles, swift of foot, Looked forth, and, gazing on the hard-fought fray And the sad A;ut, beheld them. Then he called His friend Patroclus, shouting from the ship. 730 Patroclus heard, within the tent, and came, Glorious as Mars ; — yet with that day began His woes. The gallant Menoetiades Made answer thus: "Why callest thou my name, Achilles, and what needest thou of me?" ns And thus rejoined Achilles, swift of foot: — "Son of Menoetius, nobly born, and well Beloved by me, the Greeks, I deem, will soon Be at my knees, imploring aid ; for now A hard necessity besets their host. 7« But go, Patroclus, dear to Jove, and ask Of Nestor who it is that he hath brought Page 302 302 The Iliad. Thus wounded from the field. Seen from behind, His form was like Machaon, — wholly like That son of /Esculapius; but the face 743 I saw not, as the rapid steeds flew by." He spake. Patroclus hearkened to his friend, And hastened to the Grecian tents and ships. Now when they reached the tent of Neleus' son, The warriors in the chariot set their feet 730 Upon the nourishing earth. Eurymedon, The old man's charioteer, took from the mares Their harness; while the chieftainscooled themselves, And dried their sweaty garments in the breeze, Facing the border of the sea, and then, 7ss Entering the tent of Nestor, sat them down On couches. Hecamede, bright of hair, Prepared for them a mingled draught; the maid, A daughter of the great Arsinoiis, came From Tenedos with Nestor, when the town 7&, Was ravaged by Achilles, and the Greeks Gave her to Nestor, chosen from the rest For him, as wisest of their counsellors. First she drew forth a table fairly wrought, Of polished surface, and with steel-blue feet, *s And on it placed a brazen tray which bore A thirst-provoking onion, honeycomb, And sacred meal of wheat. Near these she set A noble beaker which the ancient chief Had brought from home, embossed with studs of gOld. 770 Page 303 Book XI. 303 Four were its handles, and each handle showed Two golden turtles feeding, while below Two others formed the base. Another hand Could scarce have raised that beaker from its place, But Nestor lifted it with ease. The maid, 77s Fair as a goddess, mingled Pramnian wine, And grated o'er it, with a rasp of brass, A goat's-milk cheese, and, sprinkling the white flour Upon it, bade them drink. With this they quenched Their parching thirst, and then amused the time t*, With pleasant talk. Patroclus to the door Meantime, a godlike presence, came, and stood. The old man, as he saw him, instantly Rose from his princely seat and seized his hand, And led him in and bade him sit; but he 7«s Refused the proffered courtesy, and said: — "Nay, 't is no time to sit : persuade me not, Nursling of Jove ; for he is to be feared, And prone to wrath, who sent me to inquire What wounded man is with thee ; but I know, — 790 Now that I see Machaon sitting here, The shepherd of the people. I must haste Back to Achilles, bearing my report. Thou knowest, ancient chief, how quick he is To take offence and blame the innocent." m Then Nestor, the Gerenian knight, rejoined :— "Why does Achilles pity thus the sons Of Greece when wounded? Little can he know What sorrow reigns throughout the Grecian host Page 304 3°4 The Iliad. While, smitten in the close or distant fight, &» Our bravest lie disabled in their ships. The valiant son of Tydeus — Diomed — Is wounded — wounded Agamemnon lies, And the great wielder of the javelin, Ulysses. By an arrow in the thigh «05 Eurypylus is smitten, and I now Bring home this warrior with an arrow-wound. Yet doth Achilles, valiant as he is, Care nothing for the Greeks. Will he then wait Till our swift galleys, moored upon the shore, After a vain defence shall feed the flames Lit by the enemy's hand, and we be slain, And perish, heaps on heaps? My strength is now Not that which dwelt in these once active limbs. Would I were strong and vigorous as of yore, «,s When strife arose between our men and those Of Elis for our oxen driven away, And, driving off their beeves in turn, I slew The Elean chief, the brave Itymoneus, Son of Hypirochus! For, as he sought sM To save his herd, a javelin from my arm Smote him the first among his band. He fell; His rustic followers fled on every side; And mighty was the spoil we took: of beeves We drave off fifty herds, as many flocks &s Of sheep, of swine as many, and of goats An equal number, and of yellow steeds Thrice fifty ; — these were mares, and by their siues Page 305 Book XL 305 Ran many a colt. We drave them all within Neleian Pylos in the night. Well pleased t& Was Neleus, that so large a booty fell To me, who entered on the war so young. When morning brake, the heralds' cry was heard Summoning all the citizens to meet To whom from fruitful El is debts were due; is And then the princes of the Pyleans came, And made division of the spoil. For much The Epeians owed us: we were yet but few In Pylos, and had suffered grievously. The mighty Hercules in former years ««0 Had made us feel his wrath, and of our men Had slain the bravest : of the twelve who drew Their birth from Neleus, I alone am left; The others fell. The Epeians brazen-mailed Saw this, delighted, and insulted us «.s And did us wrong. When now the spoil was shared The old man for himself reserved a herd Of oxen, and a numerous flock of sheep, — Three hundred, with their shepherds, —for to him Large debts were due in Elis. He had sent »sp Four horses once, of peerless speed, with cars, To win a tripod, the appointed prize. Augeias, king of men, detained them there, And sent the grieving charioteer away. My father, angered at the monarch's words «ss And acts, took large amends, and gave the rest To share among the people, that no one T Page 306 306 The Iliad. Might leave the ground, defrauded of his right. All this was justly done, and we performed Due sacrifices to the gods, throughout «so The city ;— when the third day came, and brought The Epeians all at once, in all their strength, — Both men on foot and prancing steeds. With these Came the Molions twain, well armed, though young And yet untrained to war. There is a town «s Named Thryoessa, on a lofty hill Far off beside Alpheius, on the edge Of sandy Pylos. They beleaguered this, And sought to overthrow it. As they crossed The plain, Minerva came, a messenger, s7o By night from Mount Olympus, bidding us Put on our armor. Not unwillingly The Pyleans mustered, but in eager haste For battle. Yet did Neleus not consent That I should arm myself, — he hid my steeds; «7s For still he deemed me inexpert in war. Yet even then, although I fought on foot, I won great honor even among the knights; For so had Pallas favored me. A stream Named Minyeius pours into the sea «&, Near to Arena, where the Pylean knights Waited the coming of the holy morn, While those who fought on foot came thronging m. Thence, with our host complete, and all in arms, We marched, and reached at noon the sacred stream at Page 307 Book XI. 307 Alpheius, where to Jove Omnipotent We offered chosen victims, and a bull To the river-god, another to the god Of ocean, and a heifer yet unbroke To blue-eyed Pallas. Then we banqueted, «90 In bands, throughout the army, and lay down In armor by the river-side to sleep. Meantime the brave Epeians stood around The city, resolute to lay it waste. But first was to be done a mighty work «9s Of war; for as the glorious sun appeared Above the earth we dashed against the foe, Praying to Jove and Pallas. When the fight Between the Eleans and the Pylean host Was just begun, I slew a youthful chief, — soo Mulius, —- and bore away his firm-paced steeds. The fair-haired Agamcde, eldest-born Of King Augeias' daughters, was his spouse; And well to her each healing herb was known That springs from the great earth. As he drew near, I smote him with my brazen lance: he fell To earth: I sprang into his car, and stood Among the foremost warriors; while, around, The brave Epeians, as they saw him fall, — The leader of their knights, their mightiest «,» In battle, — turned and, panic-stricken, fled, Each his own way. I followed on their flight Like a black tempest; fifty cars I took, And from each car I dashed two warriors down, Page 308 3o8 The Iliad. Pierced by my spear. And now I should have slain The young Molions also, Actor's sons, 91« Had not their father, he who shakes the earth, Enshrouded them in mist, and hidden them From all pursuit. Then with victorious might Did Jove endue our arms, while we pursued *.» The foe across a region strewn with shields, — Slaying, and gathering spoil, — until our steeds Came to Buprasium, rich in fields of wheat, And to the Olenian rock, and to the hill Alesium in Colone. Pallas there 9»s Stayed our pursuit, and bade our host return. There slew I the last man, and left him there. And then the Achaians, guiding their swift steeds Homeward to Pylos from Euprasium, gave Great thanks to Jupiter among the gods, 930 And Nestor among men. Such was I then Among the heroes; but Achilles keeps His valor for himself alone, — and yet Bitterly must he grieve when he beholds Our people perish. O my friend! how well 93s Menoetius charged thee when he sent thee forth, From Phthia, to Atrides! We were both — The nobly born Ulysses and myself— Within the palace, and we clearly heard What he commanded thee. For we had come w To Peleus' stately dwelling, on our way Gathering a host in fertile Greece, and saw The great Menoetius there, and there we found Page 309 Book XI. 309 Achilles with thee. There the aged knight Peleus was burning, in the palace-court, «s A steer's fat thighs to Jove the Thunderer, And lifted up a golden cup and poured Dark wine upon the blazing sacrifice. And both of you were busy with the flesh When we were at the threshold. As he saw 9*, Our coming, in surprise Achilles sprang Toward us, and took our hands and led us in, Bade us be seated, and before us placed The generous banquet due to stranger-guests. Then, having feasted, I began discourse, 9ss Exhorting you to join us. Both of you At once consented, and your fathers gave Their admonitions. Aged Peleus charged His son Achilles to excel the rest In valor, while Menoetius, in his turn, sks0 The son of Actor, gave thee this command : — "' My son, Achilles is the nobler born, But thou art elder. He surpasses thee By far in warlike might, but thou must prompt His mind with prudent counsels ; thou must warn #s And guide him ; he will hearken to thy words Meant for his good.' The old man charged thee thus. Thou hast forgotten it. Yet speak thou now To Peleus' warlike son; and haply he May heed thy counsels. Thou perchance mayst bend • wo Page 310 The Iliad. His will — who knows ? — by thy persuasive words „ For wholesome are the warnings of a friend. Yet, if he shrink from some predicted doom, Or if his goddess-mother have revealed Aught of Jove's counsels to him, then, at least 97s Let him send thee to war, and let his troop Of Myrmidons go with thee, so that thou Mayst carry succor to the Greeks. Yet more, — Let him permit thee in the field to wear His glorious armor, that the Trojan host, »&, Beholding thee so like to him, may shun The combat, and the warlike sons of Greece, Hard-pressed, may breathe again, and find at length A respite from the conflict. Ye, who still Are fresh and vigorous, shall assault and drive 9«s Townward the weary foe from camp and fleet." He spake. The spirit of the youth took fire, And instantly he hastened toward the ships Of P.eleus' son. But when he came where lay The galleys of Ulysses the divine, w Where was the assembly-place and judgment-seat, And where the altars of the immortals stood, Evfemon's noble son, Eurypylus, Met him as from the battle-field he came Halting, and with an arrow in his thigh. 99s The sweat ran down his shoulders and his brow, And the black blood was oozing from his wound, Yet was his spirit untamed. The gallant youth, Son of Menoetius, saw with grief, and said :— Page 311 Book XI. "Unhappy chiefs and princes of the Greeks! ™ Are ye then doomed to feast with your fair limbs The famished dogs of Ilium, far away From friends and country? Tell me, child of Jove, Gallant Eurypylus, will yet the Greeks Withstand the mighty Hector, or give way 100s And perish, overtaken by his spear?" And thus the wise Eurypylus replied :— "Nursling of Jove, Patroclus! for the Greeks There is no help, and all at their black ships Must perish; for within them even now ioio All those who were our bravest warriors lie, Wounded in close encounter, or from far, By Trojan hands, whose strength with every hour Becomes more terrible. Give now thine aid And take me to my ship, and cut away 101s The arrow from my thigh, and from the part Cleanse with warm water the dark blood, and shed Soothing and healing balms upon the wound, As taught thee by Achilles, who had learned The art from Chiron, righteous in his day i.=o. Beyond all other Centaurs. Now the leech Machaon lies, I think, among the tents, Wounded, and needs the aid of others' skill, And Podalirius out upon the plain Helps stem the onset of the Trojan host." i,»s Then spake the valiant Menoetiades :— "O brave Eurypylus! what yet will be The end of this, and what are we to do? End of Section 13. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents Section 14 Page 312 3i2 The Iliad. Even now I bear a message on my way From reverend Nestor, guardian of the Greeks, 10*, To the great warrior, Peleus' son ; and yet I must not leave thee in thine hour of need." He spake; and, lifting in his arms the prince, He bore him to his tent. A servant spread, Upon his entering, hides to form a couch; ioss And there Patroclus laid him down and cut The rankling arrow from his thigh, and shed Warm water on the wound to cleanse away The purple blood, and last applied a root Of bitter flavor to assuage the smart, 1* Bruising it first within his palms : the pangs Ceased ; the wound dried ; the blood no longer flowed.

XIII

.

EN Jove had brought the Trojans and Hector, beside the ships, he left them there To toil and struggle and endure, while he Turned his resplendent eyes upon the land Of Thracian horsemen, and the Mysians, skilled s To combat hand to hand, and the famed tribe Of long-lived Hippomulgi, reared on milk, And the most just of men. On Troy no more He turned those glorious eyes, for now he deemed That none of all the gods would seek to aid 10 Either the Greeks or Trojans in the strife. The monarch Neptune kept no idle watch; For he in Thracian S.imos, dark with woods, Aloft upon the highest summit sat O'erlooking thence the tumult of the war; i» For thence could he behold the Idaean mount, And Priam's city, and the Grecian fleet. There, coming from the ocean-deeps, he sat, vol.. 11. 1 A their chief, Page 2 2 The Iliad. And pitied the Greek warriors put to rout Before the Trojans, and was wroth with Jove. Soon he descended from those rugged steeps, And trod the earth with rapid strides; the hills And forests quaked beneath the immortal feet Of Neptune as he walked. Three strides he took, And at the fourth reached JEgzc, where he stopped, And where his sumptuous palace-halls were built, * Deep down in ocean, golden, glittering, proof Against decay of time. These when he reached, He yoked his swift and brazen-footed steeds, With manes of flowing gold, to draw his car, so And put on golden mail, and took his scourge, Wrought of fine gold, and climbed the chariot-seat, And rode upon the waves. The whales came forth From their deep haunts, and frolicked round his way: They knew their king. The waves rejoicing smoothed A path, and rapidly the coursers flew; *s Nor was the brazen axle wet below. And thus they brought him to the Grecian fleet. Deep in the sea there is a spacious cave, Between the rugged Imbrus and the isle Of Tenedos. There Neptune, he who shakes The shores, held back his steeds, took off theiryoke, Gave them ambrosial food, and, binding next Their feet with golden fetters which no power Might break or loosen, so that they might wait « Their lord's return, he sought the Grecian host. Still did the Trojans, rushing on in crowds, Page 3 Book XIII. 3 Like flames or like a tempest, follow close Hector, the son of Priam ; still their rage Abated not; with stormy cries they came; ,/ They hoped to seize the fleet and slay the Greeks Beside it. But the power who swathes the earth And shakes it, Neptune, coming from the deep, Revived the valor of the Greeks. He took The shape of Calchas and his powerful voice, ss And thus to either Ajax, who yet stemmed The battle with a resolute heart, he spake :— "O chieftains! yours it is to save the host, Recalling your old valor, with no thought Of fatal flight. Elsewhere I feel no dread «0 Of what the daring sons of Troy may do Who climb the wall in throngs; the well-greaved Greeks Will meet them bravely. But where Hector leads, Fierce as a flame, his squadrons, he who boasts To be a son of sovereign Jove, I fear «s Lest we should sorely suffer. May the gods Strengthen your hearts to stand against the foe, And flinch not, and exhort the rest to stand, And drive him back, audacious as he is, From the swift ships, though Jove should urge him on." Thus earth-surrounding Neptune said, and touched Each hero with his sceptre, filled their hearts With valor, gave new lightness to their limbs Page 4 4 The Iliad. And feet and hands, and then, as when a hawk Shoots swiftly from some lofty precipice n And chases o'er the plain another bird, So swiftly Neptune, shaker of the shores, Darted from them away. Oileus' son Perceived the immortal presence first, and thus At once to Telamonian Ajax spake : — s0 "Some god, O Ajax, from the Olympian hill, Wearing the augur's form, hath bid us fight Beside the ships; nor can it be the seer Calchas, for well I marked his feet and legs As he departed; easily by these •\> The gods are known. I feel a spirit roused In my own bosom eager to engage In the fierce strife; my very feet below, And hands above, take part in the desire." And thus the son of Telamon replied :— 90 "So also these strong hands that grasp the spear Burn eagerly to wield it, and my heart Is full of courage. I am hurried on By both my feet, and vehemently long To try alone the combat with this chief 9s Of boundless valor, Hector, Priam's son." Thus they conferred, rejoicing as they felt That ardor for the battle which the god Had breathed into their hearts. Meantime he roused The Achaians at the rear, who in their ships too Sought respite, and whose limbs were faint with toil, And their hearts sad to see the Trojan host Page 5 Book XIII. 5 With tumult pouring o'er the lofty wall. As they beheld, the tears came gushing forth From underneath their lids; they little hoped i0s For rescue from destruction; but when came The power that shakes the shores, he woke anew The spirit of their valiant phalanxes. Teucer he first addressed, and Leitus, The hero Peneleus and Thoas next, n0 Deipyrus, Meriones expert In battle, and Antilochus his peer, And thus exhorted them with winged words :— "Shame on you, Argive youths! I put my trust In your tried valor to defend our fleet; «s But if ye fear to face the perilous fight, The day has risen which shall behold us fall Vanquished before the Trojans. O ye gods! These eyes have seen a marvel, a strange sight And terrible, which I had never thought ,» Could be, — the Trojans close upon our ships, They who, erewhile, were like the timid deer That wander in the wood an easy prey To jackals, pards, and wolves, —weak things, unapt For combat, fleeing, but without an aim. "i Such were the Trojans, who till now ne'er dared Withstand the might and prowess of the Greeks Fven for an hour. But now. afar from Troy They give us battle at the hollow ships, All through our general's fault, and through the sloth Of the Greek warriors, who, displeased with him, is, Page 6 6 The Iliad. Fight not for their swift galleys, but are slain Beside them. Yet although our sovereign chief, Atrides Agamemnon, may have done Foul wrong, dishonoring the swift-footed son ijs Of Peleus, still ye cannot without blame Decline the combat. Let us then repair The mischief done ; the hearts of valiant men Are soon appeased. And not without the loss Of honor can your fiery courage sleep, ,» Since ye are known the bravest of the host. I would not chide the weak, unwarlike man For shrinking from the combat; but for you, — I look on you with anger in my heart. Weaklings! ye soon will bring upon yourselves us Some sorer evil if ye loiter thus. Let each of you bethink him of the shame And infamy impending. Terrible The struggle is before us. Hector storms The ships, loud-shouting Hector; he has burst is» The gate and broken the protecting bar." So Neptune spake, encouraging the Greeks. While firmly stood the serried phalanxes Round either Ajax, nor could Mars himself, Nor Pallas, musterer of armed hosts, «ss Reprove their order. There the flower of Greece Waited the Trojans and their noble chief, Spear beside spear, and shield by shield, so close That buckler pressed on buckler, helm on helm, And man on man. The plumes of horse-hair touched Page 7 Book XIII. 7 Each other as they nodded on the crests «si Cf the bright helms, so close the warriors stood. The lances quivered in the fearless hands Of warriors eager to advance and strike The enemy. But the men of Troy began i«s The assault; the fiery Hector was the first To rush against the Greeks. As when a stone Rolls from a cliiT before a wintry flood That sweeps it down the steep, when mighty rains Have worn away the props that held it fast; ,7» It rolls and bounds on high; the woods around Crash, as it tears its unresisted way Along the slope until it reach the plain, And there, however urged, moves on no more ; — So Hector, menacing to cut his way m Through tents and galleys to the very sea, Slaying as he went forward, when he now Met the firm phalanxes and pressed them close, Stopped suddenly ; the sons of Greece withstood His onset and repulsed it, striking him *s With swords and two-edged spears, and made thechief Give way before the shock. He lifted up His voice and shouted to the Trojans thus : — "Trojans and Lycians and Dardanians skilled In fighting hand to hand, stand firm. Not long i«s Will the Greeks bide my onset, though drawn up Square as a tower in close array. My spear, I trust, will scatter them, if true it be That Juno's husband, Sovereign of the mods, Page 8 8 The Iliad. And Lord of thunders, prompts my arm to-day." »r, He spake, and kindled in the breasts of all Fresh courage. In the band Deiphobus Marched proudly, Priam's son, with his round shield Before him, walking with a quick, light step Behmd its shelter. Then Meriones ,« Aimed at the chief his glittering spear; the point Missed not; it struck the orb of bullock's hide, Yet did not pierce it, for the weapon broke Just at the neck. Deiphobus held forth His shield far from him, dreading to receive ■» A spear-thrust from the brave Meriones. Vexed thus to lose the victory, and the spear Snapped by the blow, Meriones fell back Into the column of his friends, and passed Hastily toward the camp and ships, to bring «* A powerful spear that stood within his tent, While others fought, and fearful was the din. Then Teucer first, the son of Telamon, Smote gallant Imbrius, son of Mentor, lord Of many steeds. He, ere the Greeks had come ™ To Troy, dwelt at Pedaeum and espoused Medesicasta, Priam's spurious child. But when the well-oared galleys of the Greeks Mustered at Troy, he also came, and there Was eminent among her chiefs, and dwelt «s With Priam, and was honored as his son. The son of Telamon beneath the ear Pierced him with his long javelin, and drew forth Page 9 Book XIII. 9 The weapon. Headlong to the earth he fell. As on a mountain height, descried from far, m Hewn by a brazen axe, an ash is felled And lays its tender sprays upon the ground, Thus Imbrius fell, and round him in his fall Clashed his bright armor. Teucer sprang in haste To spoil the dead, but Hector hurled at him His shining spear; the wary Teucer stepped Aside, and just escaped the brazen blade. It struck Amphiniachus, Cteatus' son, And Actor's grandson ; as he came to join The battle, he was smitten in the breast, »*, And fell, his armor clashing round his limbs. Then Hector flew in haste to tear away From the large-souled Amphimachus the helm That cased his temples. Ajax saw, and hurled His glittering spear at Hector as he came.: ns It made no wound ; for Hector stood equipped All o'er in formidable brass. The spear Struck on the bossy shield with such a shock As forced him to recoil, and leave unspoiled The bodies, which the Achaians dragged away. ,*, For Stichius and Menestheus, chief among The Athenians, bore the dead Amphimachus To the Greek camp, while the two men of might, The chieftains Ajax, lifted Imbrius up; And as two lions, bearing off among ms The close-grown shrubs a goat, which they have snatched Page 10 10 The Iliad. From sharp-toothed dogs, uplift it in their jaws Above the ground, so the two warriors raised The corpse of Imbrius, and stripped off the mail, While, angered that Amphilochus was slain, »j, Oileus' son struck from the tender neck The head, and sent it far among the crowd, Whirled like a ball, to fall at Hector's feet. Meantime was Neptune moved with grief to see His grandson perish in that desperate fray, »ss And passed among the Achaian tents and ships Encouraging the men, and planning woes For Ilium. There he met Idomeneus, Expert to wield the spear, as he returned From caring for a comrade who had left *», The battle, wounded in the knee, and whom His friends had carried in. Idomeneus Had called the surgeons to his aid, and now Was hastening to the field, intent to bear His part in battle. Him the monarch god »s Of ocean thus addressed, but first he took The voice of Thoas, King Andraemon's son, Whose father ruled the ^Etolians through the bounds Of Pleuron, and in lofty Calydon, And like a god was honored in the land. v» "O counsellor of Crete, Idomeneus! Where are the threats which late the sons of Greece Uttered against the Trojans?" Promptly came The Cretan leader's answer : " No man here, O Thoas, seems blameworthy, for we all »7s Page 11 Book XIII. II Are skilled in war, nor does unmanly fear Hold any back ; nor from the difficult strife Does sloth detain one warrior. So it is Doubtless that it seems good to Saturn's son, The All-disposer, that the Greeks, afar" tso From Argos, should ingloriously fall And perish. Thoas, thou wert ever brave, And didst exhort the laggards. Cease not now To combat, cease not to exhort the rest." And Neptune, he who shakes the earth, re- joined : — «ss "Idomeneus, whoever keeps aloof From battle, willingly, to-day, may he Never return from Troy, but be the prey Of dogs. Take thou thy arms and come with me, For we must quit ourselves like men, and strive *r, To aid our cause, although we be but two. Great is the strength of feeble arms combined, And we can combat even with the brave." So speaking, Neptune turned to share the toils Of war. Idomeneus, who now had reached «;s His princely tent, put on his glorious mail, And seized two spears, and flew upon his way, Like lightning grasped by Saturn's son and flung Quivering above Olympus' gleaming peak, A sign to mortals, dazzled by the blaze, 300 So glittered, as he ran, his brazen mail. His fellow-warrior, good Meriones, Met him beside the tent, for he had come Page 12 12 The Iliad. To fetch a brazen javelin thence, and thus The stout Idomeneus addressed his friend :— 30s "O son of Molus, swift Meriones, Dearest of all my comrades! Why hast thou Thus left the battle-field? Hast thou a wound, — A weapon's point that galls thee? Dost thou bring A message to me? Think not that I sit v Within my tent an idler: I must fight." Discreetly did Meriones reply :— "Idomeneus, whose sovereign counsels rule The well-armed Cretans, I am come to seek A spear if one be left within thy tents. s•s I broke the one I bore, in hurling it Against the shield of fierce Deiphobus." The Cretan chief, Idomeneus, rejoined :— "If spears thou seek, there stand within my tent Twenty and one against the shining walls. I took them from slain Trojans. T is my wont Never to fight at distance from the foe, And therefore have I spears, and bossy shields, And helms, and body-mail of polished brass." Then spake in turn discreet Meriones :— vs "Within my tent are also many spoils Won from the Trojans, and in my black ship; But they are far away. I do not think That I forget what valor is. I fight Among the foremost in the glorious strife i*, Where'er the battle calls me. Other men Among the well-armed Greeks may not have seen Page 13 Book XIII. 13 What I perform, but thou must know me well." Idomeneus, the Cretan leader, spake :— "I know thy courage well. What need hast thou 313 To speak as thou hast done? If all of us, The bravest of the Greeks, were set apart To form an ambush ;— for an ambush tries And shows men's valor; there the craven, there The brave, is known ; the coward's color comes s*, And goes; his spirit is not calm within « His bosom, so that he can rest awhile And tremble not; he shifts his place; he sits On both his feet;. his heart beats audibly Within his breast; his teeth at thought of death 31s Chatter; the brave man's color changes not, Nor when with other warriors he sits down In ambush is he troubled, but he longs To rise and mingle in the desperate fray ; — For thee, in such an ambush, none could blame 310 Thy courage or thy skill. If there the foe Should wound thee from afar, or smite thee near, The weapon would not strike thy neck behind, Or pierce thy back, but enter at thy breast Or stomach, as thou wert advancing fast 3ss Among the foremost. But enough of this. Come! stand we here no longer, idiot-like, Lest some one chide us sharply. Hasten thou, And bring a sturdy javelin from the tent." He spake. Mcriones, like Mars in port & And swiftness, hastened to the tent and brought Page 14 14 The Iliad. A brazen spear, and joined Idomeneus, Eager for battle. As the god of war, The man-destroyer, comes into the field, With Terror, his strong-limbed and dauntless son, *s Following and striking fear into the heart Of the most resolute warrior, when from Thrace They issue armed against the Ephyri, Or else against the Phlegyans large of soul, And hearken not to both the hosts, but give »» To one the victory; so Meriones Advanced to battle with Idomeneus, Leaders of heroes both, and both equipped In glittering helms. And first Meriones Spake and addressed his fellow-warrior thus :— 37s "Son of Deucalion, at which point wilt thou Enter the throng? Upon the army's right, Its centre, or its left? The long haired Greeks Seem most to need our aid upon the left." Then spoke Idomeneus, in turn, the prince $&, Of Cretans : " At the centre of the fleet Are others who will guard it. Posted there Are either Ajax and the most expert Of Grecian archers, Teucer, not less skilled In standing fight, and amply will they task #s The arm of Hector, Priam's son, though bent On desperate conflict, and though passing fierce. With all his fierceness, he will find it hard To quell their prowess, never yet o'ercome. And fire the ships, unless Saturnian Jove *» Page 15 Book XIII. Himself should cast on them the flaming torch. Nor yet will Telamonian Ajax yield To any man of mortal birth, or reared Upon the grains of Ceres, or whom brass Or ponderous stones can wound. He would not own The warlike son of Peleus mightier »s Than he in standing fight, although in speed He vies not with him. Lead us then to join The army's left, that we may learn at once Whether our fate in battle shall confer 40o Glory on other men, or theirs on us." So spake the chief. Meriones, the peer Of Mars in swiftness, hastened till he joined The army where his comrade bade. The foe Beheld Idomeneus, who like a flame ,0s Swept on with his companion all in arms Gloriously wrought ; they raised from rank to rank The battle-cry, and met him as he came, And hand to hand, before the galleys' sterns Was waged the combat. As when storms arise, 4«, Blown up by piping winds, when dust lies loose Along the roads, a spreading cloud of dust Fills the wide air, so came the battle on Between the bands that struggled eagerly To slay each other. All along the line 41s The murderous conflict bristled with long spears That tore the flesh; the brazen splendor, shot From gleaming helmets and from burnished mail And shining bucklers, all in narrow space. Page 16 16 The Iliad. Dazzled the eyes. Brave-hearted would he be, m The man who, gazing on it, could have seen The furious strife rejoicing or unmoved. Meantime the potent sons of Saturn each Favored a different side, and planned new toils For all the warriors, Jupiter had willed 42s That Hector and the Trojans should prevail, Yet had he not decreed the Achaian host To perish before Troy; he only sought To honor Thetis and her large-souled son. But Neptune, mingling with the Greeks, aroused iw, Their martial spirit. From the hoary deep He.came unmarked, for deeply was he grieved To see the Greeks give way before the host Of Troy, and he was wroth with Jupiter. Both gods were of one race, and owed their birth «s To the same parents; but the elder-born Was Jupiter, and wiser. For that cause Not openly did Neptune aid the Greeks, But, as by stealth, disguised in human form, Moved through their army and encouraged them «4» To combat. Thus it was the potent twain Each drew, with equal hand, the net of strife And fearful havoc, which no power could break Or loosen, stretched o'er both the warring hosts, And laying many a warrior low in death. 41s And now, although his brows were strewn with gray. Idomeneus, encouraging the Greeks, Rushed on the Trojans, and revived the fight. Page 17 Book XIII. 17 He slew Orthryoneus, who just before, Drawn by the rumor of the war, had left 4s» Cabesus, and now made a lover's suit For Priam's fairest daughter. Without dower He sought to wed Cassandra, promising A vast exploit,— to drive the Greeks from Troy, In spite of all their valor. The old king 4ss Consented that the maiden should be his; And now he fought, and trusted to fulfil His promise. But Idomeneus took aim, And cast his glittering javelin at the youth. It struck him marching proudly on, nor stopped «&, The weapon at the brazen mail, but pierced The stomach. With a clash the warrior fell, And thus the victor boasted over him :— "Orthryoneus, I deem thee worthy of praise Beyond all other men, if thou perform 4ss What thou hast undertaken, — to defend Dardanian Priam, who has promised thee His daughter. We would make a.compact too, And will perform it, — to bestow on thee A spouse, the fairest daughter of the house 470 Of Atreus' son, and we will send for her To Argos, if thou join us, and lay waste The well built Ilium. Now, then, follow me, And at the ships which brought us we will treat Of marriage, and will make no niggard terms." 47s So spake Idomeneus, and dragged the slain Through the sharp conflict by the foot. He met B Page 18 18 The Iliad. Asius, who walked before his car, and came To avenge his friend. The attending charioteer Behind him reined the steeds, that they should breathe 4&, Over the shoulders of their lord, who sought To smite Idomeneus. The Greek was first To strike; he plunged the spear into his throat Below the chin, and drave the weapon through. The Trojan fell to earth as falls an oak, 43s Poplar, or stately pine, which woodmen fell With their sharp axes on the mountain-side, To form a galley's beam. So there he lay Stretched out before his coursers and his car, And gnashed his teeth, and clenched the bloody dust. The charioteer, amazed, and losing power «, Of action, dared not turn the horses bark To bear him from the foe. Antilochus The warlike cast his spear, and in the midst Transfixed him. Little did the brazen mail ws Avail to stay the blade, which cleft its way Into the stomach. With a sudden gasp He toppled from the sumptuous chariot-seat, And large-souled Nestor's son, Antilochus, Drave with the chariot to the well-armed Greeks. *» Deiphobus, who sorrowed for the fate Of Asius, drawing near Idomeneus, Hurled at him his bright spear. The Greek beheld, As face to face they stood, and scaped the stroke, Covered by his round shield, two-handled, strong, s»s Page 19 Book XIII. 19 With bullocks' hides and glittering brass. With this He hid himself, close couched within, and turned The brazen point aside. The buckler rang Shrilly; the weapon glanced away, yet flew Not vainly from the Trojan's powerful hand: s» It struck Hypsenor, son of Hippasus, The shepherd of the people, on the side Where lies the liver, just below the breast. His knees gave way; he fell ; Deiphobus Thus shouted o'er the dead his empty boast :— us "Not unavenged lies Asius, and no doubt, In journeying to the massy gates and wall Of Hades, will rejoice that I have sent A soul to be companion of his way." He spake; and at his boast the Greeks were moved s*, With anger, — most of all Antilochus The warlike; yet he left not to the foe His slain companion, but made haste to hold His shield above him. His beloved friends, Mecisteus, son of Echius, and the prince m Alastor, lifted up, with many a groan, The corps?,.and bore it to the roomy ships. Meantime the valor of Idomeneus Remitted not; he vehemently longed To cover many a Trojan with the night no Of death, or fall himself with clashing arms, In warring to defend the ships of Greece. The brave Alcathoti •, the beloved son Page 20 20 The Iliad. Of /Esyetus, whom Anchises made His son-in-law, — for he had given to him ns Hippodameia, eldest-born of all His daughters, whom her parents, while she dwelt With them, loved dearly, fair and wise beyond All other maidens of her age, and skilled In household arts ; so that the noblest prince m0 Of the broad Trojan kingdom made her his ; — Him, by the weapon of Idomeneus, Did Neptune bring to death. The sparkling eyes Grew dim, and stiffened were the shapely limbs, For neither could he flee nor turn aside; m But as he stood before him, column-like, Or like a towering tree, Idomeneus Transfixed him in the bosom with his spear The brazen coat of mail gave way, which oft Had saved him, breaking with a sharp, shrill sound Before the severing blade. He fell to earth ss, With noise ; the spear stood planted in his heart, And as he panted quivered through its length, Yet soon its murderous force was spent and still. And then the victor boasted thus aloud :— sss "Deiphobus, does this appear to thee A fair return, when three are slain for one, Or hast thou boasted idly? Yet do thou, Vain as thou art, stand forth and face me here, And I will teach thee of what race I am, — st» An offshoot of the stock of Jove, whose son Was Minos, guardian of our Crete, and he Page 21 Book XIII. Was father of the good Deucalion. Deucalion's son am I, and I am king O'er many men in the broad isle of Crete. My galleys brought me thence to be the dread Of thee, thy father, and the men of Troy." He spake. Deiphobus, irresolute, Stood doubting whether to retreat and bring Some other of the heroic sons of Troy To aid him, or to try the fight alone. As thus he mused, it seemed most wise to seek /Eneas. Him he found withdrawn among The rear of the army, for he was displeased With noble Priam, who had paid his worth With light esteem. Deiphobus approached, And thus with winged words accosted him :— "^Eneas, counsellor of Troy, if thou Hadst ever a regard to him who was Thy sister's husband, it becomes thee now To avenge him. Follow me, and help avenge Alcathous, guardian of thy tender years, Slain by the spear of famed Idomeneus.'' He spake; and at his words /Eneas felt His courage rise. Impatient for the fight, He went to meet Idomeneus ; yet fear Fell not upon the Greek as if he were A puny boy : he stood and kept his ground. As, when a mountain boar, unterrified, Waits in the wilderness the hunter-crew, That come with mighty din, his bristly back Page 22 22 The Iliad. Rises, his eyes shoot fire, he whets his tusks, And fiercely keeps both dogs and men at bay, — So did Idomeneus, expert to wield The spear, await /Eneas hastening on »s With fury. Not a backward step he made, But called upon his warrior-friends aloud, Looking at Aphareus, Ascalaphus, Deipyrus, Meriones, and last Antilochus, all skilled in arts of war, And thus exhorted them with winged words :— "Haste hither, O my friends,'and bring me aid. I stand alone, in dread of the approach Of swift JEneas, who comes fiercely on, Powerful to slay, and in his prime of youth, . *n The highest vigor of the human frame. Yet, were our years the same, that chief or I Would quickly triumph at the other's cost." He spake, and all with one accord draw near And stood by him, with shields obliquely held «10 Upon their shoulders. On the other side ^^neas cheered his comrades on. He fixed His look on Paris, and Deiphobus, And nobly born Agenor, who, like him, Were leaders of the Trojans. After these «,s The soldiers followed, as the thronging flock Follow the ram that leads them to the fount From pasture, and the shepherd's heart is pleased. So was /Eneas glad at heart to see The multitude of warriors following him. **> Page 23 Book XIII. 23 Then mingled they in battle hand to hand Around Alcathous, with their ponderous spears, And fearfully upon their bosoms rang The brass, as through the struggling crowd they aimed Their weapons at each other. Two brave men, &,s ^Eneas and Idomeneus, the peers Of Mars, conspicuous o'er their fellows, strove With cruel brass to rend each other's limbs. And first ^Eneas cast his spear to smite Idomeneus, who saw it as it came, And shunned it. Plunging in the earth beyond, It stood and quivered ; it had left in vain The Trojan's powerful hand. Idomeneus Next smote CEnomaiis: the spear brake through His hollow corselet at the waist ; it pierced 433 And drank the entrails : down amid the dust He fell, and grasped the earth with dying hand. Idomeneus plucked forth the massy spear, But, pressed by hostile weapons, ventured not To strip the sumptuous armor from the dead; «*, Since now no more the sinews of his feet Were firm to bear him rushing to retake His spear, or start aside from hostile spears. Wherefore in standing fight he warded off The evil hour, nor trusted to his feet «js To bear him fleetly from the field. He moved Slowly away, and now Deiphobus, Who long had hated him and bitterly, Page 24 24 The Iliad. Aimed at him his bright spear; it missed its mark, And struck Ascalaphus, the son of Mars. ss0 The weapon cleft the shoulder of the Greek, Who fell amid the dust, and clenched the earth. Not yet the clamorous Mars, of passionate mood, Had heard that in the fray his son was slain; But on the summit of the Olympian mount «ss He sat, o'ercanopied by golden clouds, Restrained from combat by the will of Jove, With other gods, forbidden, like himself, To aid the combatants. Meantime around Ascalaphus the combat hand to hand «0 Still raged. Deiphobus had torn away The slain man's shining helm, when suddenly Meriones sprang forward, spear in hand, And smote him on the arm; the wounded limb Let fall the helm, resounding as it fell, And with a vulture's leap Meriones Rushed toward him, plucking out from the torn flesh The spear, and falling back among the crowd. Polites, brother of the wounded, threw Both arms around his waist, and bore him off «70 From the loud din of conflict, till he reached His swift-paced steeds, that waited in the rear Of battle, with their chariot nobly wrought And charioteer. These took him back to Troy, Heavily groaning and in pain, the blood «7s Yet gushing from the newly wounded limb. Still fought the other warriors, and the noise Page 25 Book XIII. 25 Of a perpetual tumult filled the air. ./Eneas, rushing upon Aphareus, Caletor's son, who turned to face him, thrust «*, A sharp spear through his throat. With drooping head, And carrying shield and helmet to the ground, He fell, and rendered up his soul in death. Antilochus, as Thoon turned away, Attacked and smote him, cutting off the vein a* That passes through the body to the neck. This he divided sheer; the warrior fell Backward, and lay in dust, with hands outstretched To his beloved friends. Antilochus Flew to the slain, and from his shoulders stripped °» The armor, casting cautious glances round; While toward him pressed the Trojans on all sides, Striking the fair broad buckler with their darts, Yet could not even score with pointed brass The tender skin of Nestor's son ; for still «9s Neptune, the shaker of the sea-coast, kept Watch o'er him while the weapons round him show- ered. Yet he withdrew not from his foes, but moved Among the crowd, nor idle was his spear, But wielded right and left, and still he watched r» With'resolute mind the time to strike the foe At distance, or assault him near at hand. The son of Asius, Adamas, beheld The hero meditating thus, and struck, vol. 11. a Page 26 26 The Iliad. In close attack, the middle of his shield r0? With a sharp brazen spear. The dark-haired god Who rules the deep denied to Adamas The life he sought, and weakened the hard stroke. Part of the Trojan's weapon, like a stake Hardened by fire, stood fixed within the shield, 710 Part lay on earth, and he who cast it slunk Among his comrades to avoid his fate. Meriones, pursuing with his spear, Smote him between the navel and the groin, AVhere deadliest are the wounds in battle given 71s To man's unhappy race. He planted there The cruel blade, and Adamas, who fell, Writhed panting round it, as a bullock bound By cowherds on the mountain with strong cords Pants as they lead him off against his will. 7*, So wounded, Adamas drew heavy breath, And yet not long. The brave Meriones, Approaching, plucked the weapon forth, and night Came o'er the eyes of Adamas. At hand Stood Helenus, and struck Deipyrus m Upon the temple with his ponderous sword, Of Thracian make, and cut the three-coned helm Away, and dashed it to the ground ; it rolled Between a Grecian warrior's feet, who stooped And took it up, while o'er its owner's eyes 730 The darkness gathered. Grieved at this, the son Of Atreus, Menelaus great in war, Rushed forward, threatening royal Helenus. Page 27 Book XIII. 27 He brandished his sharp spear; the Trojan drew His bow; advancing, one to hurl a lance, 73s And one to send an arrow. Priam's son Let fly a shaft at Menelaus' breast. The bitter missile from the hollow mail Glanced off. As when from the broad winnowing-fan' On some wide threshing-floor the swarthy beans, 7*, Or vetches, bound before the whistling wind And winnower's force, so, bounding from the mail Of gallant Menelaus, flew afar The bitter shaft. Then Menelaus, great In battle, smote the hand of Helenus 7« That held the polished bow ; the brazen spear Passed through the hand, and reached the bow, and there Stood fixed, while Helenus, avoiding death, Drew back among his comrades, with his hand Held low, and trailing still the ashen stem. 7s0 Magnanimous Agenor from the wound Drew forth the blade, and wrapped the hand in wool, Carefully twisted, taken from a sling Carried by an attendant of the chief. To meet the glorious Menelaus sprang 7s5 Pisander, led by his unhappy fate To perish, Menelaus! by thy hand In that fierce conflict. When the two were near, Advancing toward each other, Atreus' son Took aim amiss; his spear flew far aside. 1— Pisander smote the buckler on the arm Page 28 28 The Iliad. Of mighty Menelaus, yet drave not The weapon through. The broad shield stopped its force, And broke it at the neck; yet hoped he still For victory, and exulted. Then the son 7*s Of Atreus drew his silver-studded sword And sprang upon his foe, who from beneath His buckler took a brazen battle-axe, With a long stem of polished olive-wood. Both struck at once. Pisander hewed away, v Below the crest, the plumed helmet-cone Of Atreus' son, who smote, above the nose, Pisander's forehead, crashing through the bones. Both bleeding eyes dropped to the ground amid The dust; he fell ; he writhed; the conqueror, 77s Advancing, set his heel upon his breast, And stripped the armor off, and, boasting, said :— "Thus shall ye leave unharmed the fleet that brought The knights of Greece, ye treaty-breaking sons Of Ilium, never satisfied with war! 7*, Yet lack ye not still other guilt and shame, — Wrong done to me, ye dogs! Ye have not feared The wrath of Hospitable Jove, who flings The thunder, and will yet destroy your town, With all its towers, — ye who, without a cause, 7ss Bore off my youthful bride, and heaps of wealth, When she had given you welcome as our guests. And now ye seek to burn with fire the fleet Page 29 Book XIII. 29 With which we cross the ocean, and to slay The Grecian heroes. Ye shall yet be forced, rr, Eager for battle as ye are, to pause. O Father Jupiter, who hast the praise Of highest wisdom among gods and men! All this is of thy ordering. How hast thou Favored this arrogant crew of Troy, in love ns With violence, who never have enough Of war and all its many miseries! All other things soon satisfy desire, — Sleep, love, and song, and graceful dance, which most Delight in more than warlike toils, — yet they *» Of Troy are never satisfied with war." So spake the illustrious man, and, having stripped The bloody armor from the dead, he gave The spoil to his companions, and rejoined The warriors in the van. Harpalion then, A son of King Pytemenes, with whom He left his home to join the war at Troy, Assaulted him. He never saw again His native land. Close to Atrides' shield, He struck it in the centre with his lance, »1 0 Yet could not drive the weapon through the brass, And backward shrank, in fear of death, among His comrades, looking round him lest some foe Should wound him with the spear. Meriones Let fly a brazen arrow after him, at3 Which, entering his right flank below the bone, Page 30 30 The Iliad. Passed through and cleft the bladder. Down he sank Where the shaft struck him, breathing out his life In the arms of his companions. Like a worm He lay extended on the earth; his blood Gushed forth, a purple stream, and steeped the soil. The large-souled Paphlagonians came around, And placed him in a chariot, sorrowing, And bore him to the gates of sacred Troy. The father followed weeping, but no hand &,s Was raised to avenge the slaughter of his son. Yet deeply moved was Paris at his death, For he had been Harpalion's guest among The Paphlagonians. Grieving for the slain, He sent a brazen arrow from his bow. «9» Now there was one Euchenor, rich and brave, The son of Polyidus, hoary seer; His dwelling was in Corinth, and he came, Forewarned and conscious of his fate, to Troy; For often Polyidus, good old man, «3S Warned him that he within his palace halls Should perish by a grievous malady, Or else be slain by Trojan hands beside The Grecian fleet. So, to escape at once The censure of the Achaians and disease, uo He came, lest he in after times might rue His choice. And now between the jaw and ear Did Paris smite him ; from the warrior's limbs Life fled, and darkness gathered o'er his eyes. And then they fought; like a devouring fire us Page 31 Book XIIL That battle was; but Hector, dear to Jove, Had not yet learned that on the left the Greeks Made havoc of his men ; for in that hour The Greeks had almost made the victory theirs, So greatly had the god who shakes the shores Kindled their courage, and with his own arm Brought timely aid. Still Hector, pressing on Where first he leaped within the gates and wall, Broke the close phalanxes of shielded Greeks. There, ranged beside the hoary deep, the ships Of Ajax and Protesilaus lay. The wall that guarded them was low, and there Warriors and steeds in fiercest conflict met; There the Boeotians, there in their long robes The Iaonians, there the Locrians, there The men of Fhthia, and the Epeians famed For valor, held back Hector, struggling on To reach the ships, yet found they had no power To drive the noble warrior from the ground, For he was like a flame. The chosen men Of Athens formed the van. Menestheus, son Of Peteus, was their leader, after whom Phidas and Stichius followed, and with them The gallant Bias. Meges, Phyleus' son, With Dracius and Amphion, marshalled there The Epeians; while the Phthian band were led By Medon and Podarces, warlike chief. And Medon was the great Oileus' son, And brother of the lesser Ajax, born Page 32 32 The Iliad. Without the tie of wedlock, and he dwelt s7s Far from his native land, in Phylacfe; For by his violent hand the brother died Of Eryopis, whom Oileus made His lawful spouse. Podarces was the son Of Iphiclus, and dwelt in Phylace. «*, These, at the head of Phthia's valiant youth, And cased in massive armor, fought beside Boeotia's warriors for the Grecian fleet. But Ajax swift of foot, Oileus' son, From him of Telamon departed not as Even for an instant. As when two black steers Of equal vigor o'er a fallow draw The strongly jointed plough, till near their horns Streams the warm sweat; the polished yoke alone Holds them asunder, as they move along «90 The furrow, and the share divides the soil That lies between them ; — so the heroic twain Kept near each other. Many men and brave Followed to Troy the son of Telamon As his companions, and, when weariness «« Came o'er his sweaty limbs, relieved their chief Of his broad buckler. But the Locrian host Attended not Oileus' great-souled son, Nor could they ever venture to engage In combat hand to hand. No brazen helms *» Were theirs, with horse-hair plumes, noorbbd shields, Nor ashen spears. They came with him to Troy, Trusting in their good bows, and in their slings Page 33 Book XIII. 33 Of twisted wool, from which they showered afar Stones that dispersed the phalanxes of Troy. 90s The chieftains Ajax, warring in the van, Clad in their shining armor, fought to check The Trojans and their leader, brazen-mailed, While in the rear the Locrians lurked unseen, And sent their shafts, so that the men of Troy, »«, All order lost, were fain to cease from fight. Then had the Trojans from the ships and tents Turned back, and fled, with fearful loss of life, To lofty Ilium, if Polydamas Had not accosted valiant Hector thus : — "Hector, thou hearkenest not to warning words. Deem'st thou, because a god has given thee strength Beyond all other men for feats of war, That therefore thou art wiser than they all In council? Think not for thyself to claim All gifts at once. On one the god bestows Prowess in war, upon another grace In dance, upon another skill to touch The harp and sing. In yet another, Jove The Thunderer implants the prudent mind, m By which the many profit, and by which Communities are saved; and well doth he Who hath it know its worth. Now let me speak What seems to me the wisest. Round thee flames The encircling war; the valiant sons of Troy, v» Since they have crossed the ramparts, staml aloof, Armed as they are, or fight against large odds Page 34 34 The Iliad. Scattered among the galleys. Yield thou now The ground, and, summoning the chiefs, decide What plan to follow, — whether we shall storm m The well-oared galleys, should the God vouchsafe The victory to us, — or else depart In safety from the fleet. I greatly fear The Achaians may repay to us the debt Of yesterday. There yet is at the fleet w One who, I think, no longer will refrain Wholly from battle." Thus Polydamas Spake, and the sage advice pleased Hector well, Who, leaping from his chariot to the ground, With all his weapons, said these winged words: — "Remain with all the bravest warriors here, «« Polydamas, while I depart to give The due commands, and instantly return." He spake, and with a shout he rushed away, Seen from afar, like a snow-mountain's peak, w» And flew among the Trojans and allies, Who crowded round the brave Polydamas, The son of Panthous, at Hector's call. Among the foremost combatants he sought Deiphobus, and mighty Helenus, sss The king; he looked for Adamas, the son Of Asius, and for Asius of the house Of Hyrtacus. Some not unharmed he found, Yet not o'ercome; while others lay in death Beneath the galley sterns, where Grecian hands »*, Had slain them; others on the wall, struck down Page 35 Book XIII. 35 By missiles, or in combat hand to hand. There on the left of that disastrous fray He met the noble Alexander, spouse Of fair-haired Helen, as he cheered his men, *ss And rallied them to battle. Hector thus Addressed his brother with reproachful words :— "Accursed Paris! noble but in form, Effeminate seducer! where are now Deiphobus, and mighty Helenus? 970 And Adamas, the son of Asius, where? And Asius, son of Hyrtacus? and where Orthryoneus? Now towering Ilium sinks From her high summit, and thy fate is sure." And then the godlike Paris answered thus :— m "Since it hath pleased thee, Hector, thus to cast Reproach on me, though innocent, I may Another day neglect the toils of war, Although in truth my mother brought me forth Not quite unapt for combat. Since the hour s*0 When thou didst lead the battle to the ships With thy companions, we have held our ground, Here on this spot, contending with the Greeks. Three chiefs for whom thou askest have been slain. Deiphobus and mighty Helenus, « Both wounded in the hand by massive spears, Have left the field; the son of Saturn saved Their lives. Now lead us wheresoe'er thou wilt, And we will follow thee with resolute hearts, Nor deem that thou wilt find in us a lack «o Page 36 3S The Iliad. Of valor while our strength of arm remains. The boldest cannot tight beyond his strength." With such persuasive words the warrior calmed His brother's anger, and they went where raged The hottest conflict round Cebriones, « Phalces, Ortbasus, and the excellent Polydamas, with Palmys at his side, And Polyphoetes, godlike in his form, And where Ascanius and Morys fought, Sons of Hippotion. They the day before «»* Came marching from Ascania's fertile fields, Moved by the will of Jove to share the war. All these swept on, as when a hurricane, A thunder-gust, from Father Jupiter Buffets the plain, and mingles with the deep, ,•"s In mighty uproar, and the billows rise All over the resounding brine, and swell, Whitening with foam, and chase each other on. So moved the Trojans on, man after man, In close array, all armed in glittering brass, «»o Following their generals. Hector, Priam's son, And peer of Mars in battle, led the van, His round shield held before him, tough with hides And overlaid with brass. Upon his brow The gleaming helmet nodded as he moved. «»s On every side he tried the phalanxes, If haply they might yield to his assault, Made from beneath that buckler; but the Greeks In spirit or in order wavered not. Page 37 Book XIII. 37 And Ajax, striding forth, defied him thus :— mm "Draw nearer, friend! Think'st thou to frighten thus The Greeks? We are not quite so inexpert In war, although so cruelly chastised By Jupiter. Thou thinkest in thy heart That thou shalt make our ships thy spoil; but we «»s Have also our strong arms to drive thee back, And far more soon the populous town of Troy, Captured and sacked, shall fall by Grecian hands. And now I warn thee that the hour is near When, fleeing, thou shalt pray to Father Jove i0*, And all the immortals, that thy long-maned steeds, Bearing thee townward mid a cloud of dust Along the plain, may be more swift than hawks." As thus he spake, an eagle, to the right, High in the middle heaven, flew over him, ,»« And, gladdened by the omen, all the Greeks Shouted ; but then illustrious Hector spake : — "Babbl er and boaster, what wild words are these? 0 Ajax! would that I were but as sure To be the child of aegis-bearing Jove, »,*, Brought forth by Juno the august, and held In honor everywhere like that which crowns Apollo and Minerva, as I know That to the Greeks this very day will bring Destruction, and that thou shalt also lie *»,, Slain with the others, if thou dare abide The stroke of my long spear, which yet shall tear Page 38 33 The Iliad. Thy dainty flesh, and thou, with thy full limbs, Shalt be the feast of Trojan dogs and birds, Unburied by the galleys of the Greeks." So Hector spake, and led his warriors on. They followed with a mighty shout; the rear Sent up as loud a cry. On the other side Shouted the Greeks, nor intermitted now Their wonted valor, but stood firm to breast The onset of the chosen men of Troy. The mingled clamor of both hosts went up To heaven, and to the shining seat of Jove.

XIV

.

THE mighty uproar was not unperceived By Nestor's ear, who, sitting at the wine, Addressed the son of /Esculapius thus : — "Noble Machaon, what will happen now? Bethink thee: for the clamor grows more loud From our young warriors at the ships. Stay here And drink the purple wine, while for thy limbs The fair-haired Hecamede warms the bath And washes the dark blood away, and I Will climb the watch-tower, and will know the worst. He spake, and took a buckler, fairly wrought, Glittering with brass, and left within the tent By Thrasymedes, his own knightly son,
Who to the war had borne his father's shield; He grasped a ponderous spear, with brazen blade, 1s And stood without the tent, and saw a sight Of shame, — the routed Greeks, and close behind The haughty Trojans putting them to flight, And the Greek wall o'erthrown. As when the face Of the great deep grows dark with weltering waves, That silently forbode the swift descent »• Of the shrill blast, the yet uncertain seas Roll not to either side, till from the seat Of Jupiter comes down the violent wind,— So paused the aged chief, uncertain yet »s Of purpose, — whether he should join the throng Of Greeks, with their swift coursers, or repair To sovereign Agamemnon, Atreus' son. This to his thought seemed wiser, and he went To seek Atrides. Meantime both the hosts v, Urged on the work of slaughter ; still they fought, And still the solid brass upon their limbs Rang, smitten with the swords and two-edged spears. Then, coming from the fleet, the wounded kings, Nurslings of Jove, met Nestor; toward him came is Tydides, and Ulysses, and the son Of Atreus, Agamemnon. On the beach Of the gray deep their ships were ranged afar From that fierce conflict. There the Greeks had drawn, *» To the plain's edge, the first that touched the land, And built a rampart at their sterns. Though long
The shore-line, it sufficed not to contain The galleys, and the host had scanty room; Wherefore they drew the galleys up in rows, Row behind row, and filled the shore's wide mou Between the promontories. There the kings Walked, leaning on their lances, to behold The tumult and the fight, and inly grieved. The sight of aged Nestor startled them, And thus the royal Agamemnon spake :— "Neleian Nestor, glory of the Greeks, Why hast thou left the murderous fray, and why Come hither? Much I fear the fiery chief, Hector, will make the menace good which once He uttered, speaking to the men of Troy,— Not to return to Ilium from the fleet Till he had burned our ships with fire, and slain Us also; thus he spake, and now fulfils His menace. O ye gods ! the other Greeks, And not Achilles only, cherish hate Against me in their hearts, and now refuse To combat even where our galleys lie." And Nestor, the Gerenian knight, replied :— "Thus is the threat accomplished, nor can Jove The Thunderer reverse the event. The wall In which we trusted as impregnable, Our fleet's defence and ours, is overthrown; But obstinately still the Greeks maintain The combat at the ships, nor couldst thou now Distinguish with thy sharpest sight where most
The ranks are routed, so confusedly They fall, and the wild uproar reaches heaven. Meantime consult we what may yet be done, If counsel aught avail; yet can I not Advise to mingle in the strife again. 75 It is not meet that wounded men should fight." And then the royal Agamemnon said :— "Since at our ships, beneath their very sterns, The combat rages; since the wall we built Avails not, nor the trench, at which the Greeks *, Labored and suffered, hoping it might be A sure defence for us and for our fleet, Certain it is that to Almighty Jove It hath seemed good that here the Greeks, afar From Argos, should be shamefully cut off; «s For well was I aware when he designed To aid the Greeks, and well can I perceive That he is honoring now the men of Troy Like to the blessed gods, and fettering Our valor and our hands. Hear my advice, w, And follow it. Let us draw down the ships Nearest the sea, and launch them on the deep, And moor them, anchored, till the lonely night Shall come, when, if the Trojans pause from war, Haply we may draw down the other barks; «s For he who flees from danger, even by night, Deserves no blame; and better is his fate Who flees from harm than his whom harm o'ertakes." Then wise Ulysses, with stern look, replied:—
"What words, Atrides, have escaped thy lips? ,90 Unhappy man, thou shouldst have held command O'er some effeminate army, and not ours,— Ours to whom Jupiter, from youth to age, Hith granted to accomplish difficult wars, Until we pass away. And wouldst thou then ,« Depart from Troy, the city of broad streets, For which we have endured so much and Ion"? Nay, be thou silent, lest the other Greeks Hear words that never should be said by one Who knows to speak with wisdom, and who bears no The sceptre, and who rules so many Greeks As thou dost. I contemn with my whole soul The counsel thou hast given, commanding us, While yet the battle rages, to draw down Our good ships to the sea, that so the foe «s May see his wish more easily fulfilled, Even in the hour of triumph, and our fate Be certain ruin; for the Greeks no more Will combat when they draw their galleys down, But, looking backward to the shore, will leave ,*, The battle there ; and thus, O king of men! Will mischief flow from what thou counsellest." And Agamemnon, king of men, rejoined :— "Thou touchest me, Ulysses, to the heart With thy harsh censure; yet I did not give "s Command to drag our good ships to the sea, Against the will of the Greeks. And would there were
Some other, young or old, to counsel them More prudently, for that would please me well." Then spake the great in battle, Diomed : — 130 "The man is here, nor have ye far to look If ye will be persuaded, and refrain To blame me angrily, because my years Are fewest midst you all. I too can boast Of noble birth; my father, Tydeus, lies ,« Buried beneath a mound of earth at Thebes. To Portheus three illustrious sons were born, Who dwelt in Pleuron, and in Calydon The lofty, — Agrius, Melas, and the knight, My father's father, (Eneus, eminent no Among the rest for valor; he remained At home, but, wandering thence, my father went To Argos, for the will of Jove was such, — Jove and the other gods. He wedded there A daughter of Adrastus, and he dwelt «s Within a mansion filled with wealth ; broad fields Fertile in corn were his, and many rows Of trees and vines around him ; large his flocks, And great his fame as one expert to wield, Beyond all other Greeks, the spear in war. ,s» This should ye know, for this is true; nor yet Contemn my counsel given with careful thought And for your good, nor deem it comes from one Unwarlike and low-born. Now let us join The battle, wounded as we are, for much 1ss It needs our presence, keeping carefully
Beyond the reach of weapons, to avoid Wound upon wound, and, cheering on the rest, Send back into the combat those who stand Apart, indulgent to their weariness." «so He spake: they hearkened, and with hasty steps Went on, King Agamemnon at their head. Nor was the glorious power that shakes the earth Unmindful of his charge. He went among The warriors in the semblance of a man 1«s Stricken in years, and, seizing the right hand Of Agamemnon, spake these winged words: — "O son of Atreus, the revengeful heart Of Peleus' son must leap within his breast For joy, to see the slaughter and the rout i7» Of the Achaians, since with him there dwells No touch of pity. May he perish too, Like us, and may some god o'erwhelm his name With infamy. With thee the blessed gods Are not so far incensed, and thou shalt see 17s The Trojan chiefs and princes of their host Raising the dust-clouds on the spacious plain In fleeing from our ships and tents to Troy." He spake, and, shouting, strode across the field. As loud a cry as from nine thousand men, ,» Or from ten thousand hurrying to engage In battle, such the cry that ocean's king Uttered from his deep lungs. It woke anew Invincible resolve in every heart Among the Greeks to combat to the end.
Now, Juno of the golden throne beheld As, standing on the Olympian height, she cast Downward her eyes to where her brother moved, Bearing his part with glory in the fray; And inly she rejoiced. She also saw 190 Jove on the peak of Ida, down whose side Glide many brooks, and greatly was displeased. Then the majestic goddess with large eyes Mused how to occupy the mind of him Who bears the aegis. This at length seemed best: To deck herself in fair array, and haste To Ida, that the God might haply yield To amorous desire, and in that hour Her hand might pour into his lids, and o'er His watchful mind, a soft and pleasant sleep. «o She went to her own chamber, which her son Vulcan had framed, with massive portals made Fast to the lintels by a secret bolt, Which none but she could draw. She entered in And closed the shining doors ; and first she took *,s Ambrosial water, washing every stain From her fair limbs, and smoothed them with rich oil. Ambrosial, soft, and fragrant, which, when touched Within Jove's brazen halls, perfumed the air Of earth and heaven. When thus her shapely form Had been anointed, and her hands had combed Her tresses, she arranged the lustrous curls, Ambrosial, beautiful, that clustering hung Round her immortal brow. And next she threw
Around her an ambrosial robe, the work «s Of Pallas, all its web embroidered o'er With forms of rare device. She fastened it Over the breast with clasps'of gold, and then She passed about her waist a zone which bore Fringes an hundred-fold, and in her ears « She hung her three-gemmed ear-rings, from whose gleam She won an added grace. Around her head The glorious goddess drew a flowing veil, Just from the loom, and shining like the sun; And, last, beneath her bright white feet she bound The shapely sandals. Gloriously arrayed »*, In all her ornaments, she left her bower, And calling Venus to herself, apart From all the other gods, addressed her thus : — "Wilt thou, dear child, comply with what I ask? Or, angered that I aid the Greeks, while thou n, Dost favor Troy, wilt thou deny my suit?" And thus Jove's daughter, Venus, made reply : — "O Juno, whom I reverence, speak thy thought, Daughter of mighty Saturn ! for my heart »ss Commands me to obey thy wish in all That I can do, and all that can be done." And thus imperial Juno, planning guile, Rejoined: "Give me the charm and the desire With which thou overcomest gods and men. »• I go to the far end of this green earth, . To visit Ocean, father of the gods,
And Mother Tethys, who, receiving me From Rhea, cherished me, and brought me up In their abodes, when Jove the Thunderer «4s Cast Saturn down to lie beneath the earth And barren sea. I go to visit them, And end their hateful quarrel. For too long Have they been strangers to the marriage-bed. But if my words persuade them, and bring back »s0 Their hearts to their old love, my name will be Honored by them, and dear throughout all time." And laughter-loving Venus answered thus: — "What thou desirest should not be denied, And shall not, for thou sleepest in the arms «ss Of Jupiter, the mightiest of the gods." She spake, and from her bosom drew the zone, Embroidered, many-colored, and mstinct With every winning charm — with love, desire, Dalliance, and gentle speech —that stealthily *° O'ercomes the purpose of the wisest mind, And, placing it in Juno's hands, she said : — "This many-colored zone, and all that dwells Within it, take, and in thy bosom hide, And thou, I deem, wilt not return and leave ««s Thy purpose unfulfilled." As thus she spake, The large-eyed stately Juno smiled and took, And, smiling, in her bosom placed the zone, While Venus, daughter of the Thunderer, Went to the palace. Juno took her way k, From high Olympus o'er Pieria's realm
And rich Emathia, o'er equestrian Thrace, With snowy peaks exceeding high; her feet Touched not the ground. From Athos suddenly She stooped upon the tossing deep, and came To Lemnos, seat of Thoas the divine. And there she met Death's brother, Sleep, and took His hand in hers, and thus accosted him :— "O Sleep, whose sway is over all the gods And all mankind, if ever thou didst heed My supplication, hearken to me now, And I shall be forever grateful. Close The glorious eyes of Jove beneath his lids Midst our embracings, and for thy reward Thou shalt possess a sumptuous throne of gold ,«s Imperishable. Vulcan, my lame son, Shall forge it for thee, and adorn its sides, And place below a footstool, upon which Thy shining feet shall rest in banqueting." Then gentle Sleep made answer, speaking thus :— "Great Saturn's daughter, Juno the august, «. On any other of the deathless gods Could I bring slumber, — even on the tides Of the swift Ocean, parent of them all; Yet may I not approach Saturnian Jove ,m If he command me not. Already once He made me quail with fright before his threats, When his magnanimous son, Alcides, sailed From Troy, which he had ravaged. Then I lulled The senses of the ^Egis-bearer, Jove,
Wrapping myself around him, while thy mind Was planning mischiefs for his son, and thou Didst wake the blasts of all the bitter winds To sweep the ocean, and to bear away The hero on its billows from his friends 30s To populous Cos. When Jupiter awoke His anger rose ; he seized and flung the gods Hither and thither; me he chiefly sought, And would have cast me to destruction, down From the great heavens into the deep, if Night, 310 Whose power o'ercomes the might of gods and mcn, Had not preserved me, fleeing to her shade. So Jove refrained, indignant as he was, For much he feared to offend the swift-paced Night. And now thou bid'st me tempt my fate again." 31s Imperial, large-eyed Juno thus rejoined : — "Why rise such thoughts, O Sleep, within thy heart? Deem'st thou that Jove the Thunderer favors Troy As much as he was angered for the sake Of Hercules, his son? Do what I ask, *,» And thou shalt have from me a wedded spouse. One of the younger Graces shall be thine, — Pasithea, whom thou hast desired so long" She spake, and Sleep, delighted, answered thus : — "Swear now to me, O goddess, by the Styx, » The inviolable river. Lay one hand Upon the food-producing earth, and place Thc other on the glimmering; sea, that all The gods below, round Saturn, may attest
Thy promise, — that thou wilt bestow on me 3j» One of the younger Graces for my bride, — Pasithea, whom I have desired so long." He spake, and white-armed Juno willingly Complied ; she took the oath, and called on all The gods who dwell in Tartarus below, bs And bear the name of Titans. When the oath Was taken, and the accustomed rites performed, From Lemnos and from Imbrus forth they went, Shrouded in mist; and swiftly moving on Toward Ida, seamed with rivulets and nurse y» Of savage beasts, they came to Lectos first, And there they left the sea. Their way was now Over the land, and underneath their feet The forest summits shook. Sleep halted there Ere yet the eye of Jupiter descried us His coming, and upon a lofty fir, The tallest growing on the Idaean mount, High in the air among the clouds of heaven, Springing from earth, he took his perch within The screen of branches, like the shrill-voiced bird, Called Chalcis by the immortals, and by men 3s, Cymindis, haunting the high mountain-side. And Juno hastened on to Gargarus, The peak of lofty Ida. Jupiter, The Cloud-compeller, saw her, and at once Love took possession of his mighty heart, As when they first were wedded, and withdrew From their dear parents' sight. The God drew near
And stood before her, and addressed her thus :— "Why art thou hastening from Olympus thus, And whither; yet without thy steeds and car?" And Juno answered with dissembled guile : — "To the far ends of the green earth I go, To visit Ocean, father of the gods, And Mother Tethys, in whose palace halls They nourished me, and brought me up. I go To end their hateful quarrels, for too long Have they been strangers to the marriage-bed, Incensed against each other. Now my steeds, Waiting to bear me over land and sea, Stand at the foot of Ida seamed with rills, And now I come to thee, lest thou perchance Be wroth if I unknown to thee repair To where old Ocean dwells amid his deeps." The Cloud-compeller, Jupiter, rejoined :— "Hereafter, Juno, there will be a time For such a journey ; meantime let us give This hour to rest and dalliance. Never yet Did love of goddess or of mortal maid Possess and overcome my he.art as now; Not even when I loved Ixion's dame, Who bore Pirithous, prudent as a god Among the counsellors ; nor when I loved Acrisius' daughter with the dainty feet, Danae, who brought forth Perseus, eminent Above the other warrior-chiefs; nor when I carried off from Phoenix the renowned
His daughter, who bore Minos afterward, And Rhadamanthus. Never so I loved Semele, nor Alcmena who in Thebes Brought forth to me the great-souled Hercules, My valiant son, while Bacchus, the delight Of men, was born of Semele; nor yet So loved I Ceres, fair-haired queen, nor yet Latona, gloriously beautiful, Nor even thee, as now I love, and yield My spirit to the sweetness of desire." Imperial Juno artfully replied :— "Importunate Saturnius, what is this That thou hast said? If on this summit height Of Ida we recline, where all around Is open to the sight, how will it be Should any of the ever-living gods Behold us sleeping, and to all the rest Declare it? I could never, rising thence, Enter again thy palace, save with shame. Yet if thou truly speakest thy desire, Thou hast a marriage-chamber of thine own, Which Vulcan, thy beloved son, for thee Framed, fitting to its posts the solid doors; And thither let us go to take our rest Within it, since thou hast declared thy will." Then spake again the Cloud-compeller Jove: "O Juno! fear thou not that any god Or man will look upon us. I shall throw A golden cloud around us, which the Sun
Himself cannot look through, although his eye Is piercing, far beyond all other eyes." The son of Saturn spake, and took his wife Into his arms, while underneath the pair »™ The sacred Earth threw up her freshest herbs, — The dewy lotus, and the crocus-flower, And thick and soft the hyacinth. All these Upbore them from the ground. Upon this couch They lay, while o'er them a bright golden cloud «s Gathered, and shed its drops of glistening dew. So slumbered on the heights of Gargarus The All-Father, overcome by sleep and love, And held his consort in his arms. Meanwhile The gentle Sleep made haste to seek the fleet 4*, Of Greece. He bore a message to the god Neptune, who shakes the shores, and, drawing near, He thus accosted him with winged words :— "Now, Neptune, give the Greeks thy earnest aid, And though it be but for a little space, 43s While Jupiter yet slumbers, let them win The glory of the day; for I have wrapt His senses in a gentle lethargy, To which he is betrayed by Juno's wiles." He spake, and took his way, departing thence 4*, Among the tribes of men. These words inflamed The god's desire to aid the Greeks; he sprang Far on among the foremost, and exclaimed : — "O Greeks! do ye again submit to yield The victory to Hector, Priam's son.
That he may seize our fleet and bear away The glory of the day? This is his hope, And this his boast, since now Achilles lies Inactive at his ships, in sullen wrath. Yet little should we need him, if the rest «0 Stood bravely by each other. Hear me now, And do what I advise. Let all of us, The best and bravest, bearing shields, and capped With glittering helms, and wielding in our hands The longest spears, advance, and I will lead «s The charge ; nor do I think that Hector, son Of Priam, daring as he seems, will yet Abide our onset. Whoso has the heart To make a stand with me, and yet who bears A narrow shield, let it be given to one Less warlike, and a broader shield be found." He spake; they hearkened and obeyed. The kings Tydides, and Ulysses, and the son Of Atreus, Agamemnon, though their wounds 4M Still galled them, marshalled and reviewed the ranks, And changed their arms ; they made the braver wear The better armor, and the worse they gave To the less warlike. Now, when o'er their breasts The burnished mail was girded, they began *> Their march ; the great earth-shaker, Neptune, led The onset, grasping in his sinewy hand A sword of fearful length and flashing blade, Like lightning. No man dared encounter it In combat; every arm was stayed by fear.
Right opposite, illustrious Hector ranged 47s His Trojans. Dark-haired Neptune and the son Of Priam no.v engaged in desperate strife, One on the side of Troy, and one for Greece. The sea swelled upward toward the Grecian tents And fleet, while both the armies flung themselves 4* Against each other with a loud uproar. Not with such noise the ocean-billows lash The mainland, when the violent north wind Tumbles them shoreward ; not with such a noise Roar the fierce flames within the mountain glen, 4«s When leaping upward to consume the trees; And not so loudly howls the hurricane Among the lofty branches of the oaks When in its greatest fury, as now rose The din of battle from the hosts that rushed «0 Against each other with terrific cries. At Ajax glorious Hector cast his spear, As face to face they stood. It missed him not. But struck him where two belts upon his breast O'erlapped each other, — that which held the shield And that which bore the silver-studded sword. «* These saved the tender muscles. Hector, vexed That thus his weapon should have flown in vain, Retreated toward his comrades, shunning death. As he drew back, the Telamonian hurled s0» A stone, — for stones in multitude, that propped The galleys, lay around, and rolled among The feet of those who struggled. One of these
He lifted, smiting Hector on the breast, Above the buckler's orb and near the neck. s0i He sent it spinning like a top ; it fell And whirled along the ground. As when beneath The stroke of Father Jupiter an oak Falls broken at the root, and from it fumes A stifling smell of sulphur, and the heart s" Of him who stands and sees it sinks with dread, — For fearful is the bolt of mighty Jove, — So dropped the valiant Hector to the earth Amid the dust; his hand let fall the spear; His shield and helm fell with him, and his mail vs Of shining brass clashed round him. Then the Greeks Rushed toward him, yelling fiercely, for they hoped To drag him thence; and many a lance they cast; But none by javelin or by thrust could wound The shepherd of the people, for there came s*, Around him all the bravest of his host, — Polydamas, ^Fineas, and the great Agenor, and Sarpedon, he who led The Lycian bands, and Glaucus the renowned; These flung themselves into the strife, while none » Of all the rest refrained, but firmly held Their broad round shields before him. Then his friends Lifted him in their arms, and bore him off, Out of the conflict, to his fiery steeds That waited for him in the battle's rear,
With charioteer and sumptuous car; and these Bore him to Ilium, sorely suffering. But when they now had reached the crossing-place Of Xanthus, full of eddies, pleasant stream, The progeny of ever-living Jove, s35 They lifted out the hero from the car, And laid him on the ground, and on him poured Water, at which his breath and sight returned. He sat upon his knees, and from his throat Gave forth the purple blood, and then he fell Back to the ground, and darkness veiled his eyes, For still his senses felt the stunning blow. The Greeks saw Hector leave the field, and pressed The foe more hotly, and bethought themselves Of their old valor. Then the swift of foot, $4s Oilean Ajax, darted to the van, And with his fir-tree spear smote Satnius, son Of Enops, whom a Naiad eminent For beauty among all the nymphs brought forth To Enops, when on Satnio's banks he kept ss, His flocks. Oileus' son, expert to wield The spear, drew near, and pierced him in the flank. Prostrate he fell, and suddenly the Greeks And Trojans gathered round in desperate fray. Polydamas, the mighty spearman, son ss5 Of Panthoiis, coming to avenge him, smote On the right shoulder Prothoenor, son Of Areilochus. The pitiless spear
Passed through, and falling in the dust he grasped The earth with dying hands. Polydamas s*, Shouted aloud, exulting over him :— "Not vainly, as I think, hath flown the spear From the strong hand of the magnanimous son Of Panthoiis. Some Achaian hath received The weapon in his side, to lean upon s«s In going down to Pluto's dim abode." He spake ; the Achaians chafed to hear his boast, And most the warlike son of Telamon; For the slain Greek fell near him. Instantly, Just as the Trojan moved away, he hurled s7» His shining lance. Polydamas, to escape The death-stroke, sprang aside. Archilochus, Antenor's son, received the blow: the gods Had doomed him to be slain. It pierced the spine Where the head joins the neck, and severed there s7s The tendons on each side. His head and mouth And nostrils struck the ground before his knees. And thus to excellent Polydamas Did Ajax shout in turn : " Bethink thee now, And tell me truly, was not this a man se0 Worthy to die for Prothoenor's sake? No man of mean repute or meanly born He seems, but either brother to the knight Antenor, or his son ; for certainly His looks declare him of Antenor's race." sss He spake ; but well he knew the slain. Meanwhile The Trojans heard and grieved. Then Acamas,
Stalking around his fallen brother, slew Promachus, the Boeotian, with his spear, While dragging off the dead man by the feet. s» Then o'er the fallen warrior, Acamas Boasted aloud : "O measureless in threats! Bowmen of Argos! not to us alone Shall woe and mourning come ; ye also yet Will perish. See your Promachus o'erthrown, sx And by my spear, that so my brother's death May not be unrequited. Every man Should wish a brother left to avenge his fall." He ended, and the Greeks were vexed to hear His boast; the brave Peneleus most of all Was angered, and he rushed on Acamas, Who waited not the onset of the king, And in his stead was Ilioneus slain, The son of Phorbas, who was rich in flocks, Whom Mercury, of all the sons of Troy, a* Loved most, and gave him ample wealth ; his wife Brought Ilioneus forth, and only him; And him Peneleus smote beneath the brow In the eye's socket, forcing out the ball; ^ The spear passed through, and reappeared behind. Down sat the wounded man with arms outstretched, While, drawing his sharp sword, Peneleus smote The middle of his neck, and lopped away The helmed head, which fell upon the ground, The spear still in the eye. He lifted it 6•s As one would lift a poppy up, and thus
He shouted, boasting, to the Trojan host :— "Go now, ye Trojans, and mform from me The father and the mother of the slain That they may mourn within their palace walls s» Illustrious Ilioneus. After this Shall the sad wife of Promachus, the son Of Alegenor, never hasten forth To meet her husband with glad looks, when we The Greeks return from Ilium with our fleet." He spake; the Trojans all grew pale with fear, And gazed around for an escape from death. Say, Muses, ye who on the Olympian height Inhabit, who was first among the Greeks To gather bloody spoil, when now the power «*, That shakes the shores had turned the tide of war. First, Ajax, son of Telamon, struck down Hyrtius, the leader of the Mysian band, And son of Gyrtias, while Antilochus Spoiled Mermerus and Phalces. Morys next, «is Slain by the weapon of Meriones, Fell with Hippotion. Teucer overthrew Prothoiis and Periphoetes. Atreus' son Smote Hyperenor, prince among his tribe, Upon the flank ; the trenchant weapon drank The entrails, and the soul, driven forth, escaped Through the deep wound, and darkness veiled his eyes. But Ajax swift of foot, Oi'.cu;' son, O'erthrew the most, for none could equ-1 him In swift pursuit when Jove ordained a flijht.

XV

.

NOW when the Trojans in theirflight had crossed Rampart and trench, and many had been slain By the pursuing Greeks, they made a halt Beside their chariots, in despair and pale With terror. Meanwhile Jupiter awoke, s On Ida's height, from slumber by the side Of Juno, goddess of the golden throne. At once he rose and saw the Trojan host Routed, and, following close upon their flight, The Argive warriors putting them to rout, ,0 Aided by Neptune, sovereign of the sea, And Hector lying on the field among His fellow-warriors, breathing painfully, Vomiting blood, and senseless, for the arm That smote was not the feeblest of the Greeks. The Father of immortals and of men Beheld and pitied him, and terribly Frowned upon Juno, and bespake her thus : — "O evil minded Juno, full of guile! Thy arts have made the noble Hector leave » The combat, and have forced his troops to flee. I know not whether't were not well that thou Shouldst taste the fruit of thy pernicious wiles, Chastised by me with stripes. Dost thou forget When thou didst swing suspended, and I tied »s Two anvils to thy feet, and bound a chain
Of gold that none could break around thy wrists? Then didst thou hang in air amid the clouds, And all the gods of high Olympus saw With pity. They stood near, but none of them 30 Were able to release thee. Whoso came Within my reach I seized, and hurled him o'er Heaven's threshold, and he fell upon the earth Scarce breathing. Yet the passion of my wrath, Caused by the wrongs of godlike Hercules, 3s Was not to be so calmed; for craftily Hadst thou called up the violent northern blast, To chase him far across the barren deep, And drive him from his course to populous Cos. I rescued him at length, and brought him back *, To Argos famed for steeds, though after long And many hardships. I remind thee now Of this, that thou mayst see of what avail Hereafter thy dissembled love and all Thy cunning strategies will be to thee." « He spake, and Juno, large-eyed and august, Shuddered, and answered Jove with winged words: — "Be witness, Earth, and the great Heavens above, And waters of the Styx that glide beneath,— That dreadful oath which most the blessed gods s» Revere, — be witness, too, that sacred head Of thine, and our own nuptial couch, by which I would not rashly swear at any time, That not by my persuasion Neptune went—
The shaker of the shores — to harass Troy s5 And Hector, and to aid the cause of Greece. He went self-counselled; he had seen the Greeks Pressed grievously beside their fleet, and took Compassion on them. Yet would I advise That he obey thy word, and take his place «0 Where thou, the Cloud compeller, bid'st him go." She ended, and the Father of the gods And mortals smiled, and said, in winged words : — "Large-eyed, imperial Juno, wouldst thou sit In council with the immortals, and assist '3 My purposes, then Neptune, though at heart He were averse, would yet conform his will To mine and thine. If thou dost truly speak, And from thy heart, go now to where the gods Assemble, summon Iris, and with her 70 The archer-god Apollo. Give in charge To Iris that she hasten to the host Of the mailed Greeks, and bid king Neptune leave, The battle for his palace. Let the god Phoebus, preparing Hector for the fight, « Breathe strength into his frame, that so he lose The sense of pain which bows his spirit now, And he shall force the Greeks again to flee In craven fear. Then shall their flying host Fall back upon the galleys of the son *0 Of Peleus, who shall send into the fight His friend Patroclus. Him the mighty spear Of Hector shall o'erthrow before the walls
Of Ilium, after many a Trojan youth Shall by his hand have fallen, and with them «3 My noble son, Sarpedon. Roused to rage, Then shall the great Achilles take the 'life Of Hector. Be it from this time my care That all the assaults of Trojans in the fleet Be beaten back, till by Minerva's aid *, The Greeks possess the lofty town of Troy. Still am I angry, nor will I allow One of the ever-living gods to aid The Greeks, until the prayer of Peleus' son Shall fully be accomplished, as my word 9s And nod were given, when Thetis clasped my knees, Entreating me to honor, signally, Her son, Achilles, spoiler of walled towns." He spake; the white-armed goddess willingly - Obeyed him, and from Ida's summit flew 100 To high Olympus. As the thought of man Flies rapidly, when, having travelled far, He thinks, " Here would I be, I would be there," And flits from place to place, so swiftly flew Imperial Juno to the Olympian mount, 10s And there she found the ever-living gods Assembled in the halls of Jupiter. These, as they saw her, starting from their seats, Reached forth their cups to greet her. All the rest She overlooked, and took the beaker held no By blooming Themis, who in haste had run To meet her, and in winged accents said:—
"Why comest thou, O Juno! with the look Of one o'ercome with fear. Hath Saturn's son, Thy lord, disquieted thy soul with threats?" ns The white-armed goddess Juno answered her : — "Ask me not, heavenly Themis, — thou dost know The cruel, arrogant temper that is his, — But sit presiding at the common feast, In this fair palace of the gods, and thou ,*, And all in heaven shall hear what evils Jove Has threatened. All, I think, will not rejoice To hear the tidings, be they gods or men, Though some contentedly are feasting now." Thus having said, imperial Juno took us Her place, and all the gods within the halls Of Jupiter were grieved. The goddess smiled, But only with the lips ; her forehead wore Above the jetty brows no sign of joy, While thus she spake in anger to the rest : — 130 "Vainly, and in our madness, do we strive With Father Jove. We come and seek by craft Or force to move his stubborn will ; he sits Apart, unyielding, unregarding, proud Of the vast strength and power in which he stands Above all other of the deathless gods. •# Bear therefore patiently whatever ill He sends to each. Already, as I learn, Hath Mars his share of sorrow. In the war Ascalaphus hath perished, whom he loved i*, Dearly, beyond all other men, and whom
The fiery god acknowledged as his son." As thus she spake, Mars smote his sinewy thighs With his dropped hands, and sorrowfully said :— "Be not offended with me, ye who make us Your dwelling on Olympus, if I go Down to the Achaian fleet, and there avenge The slaughter of my son, though I be doomed To fall before the thunderbolt of Jove, And lie in blood and dust among the dead." »s» He spake, and summoned Fear and Flight to yoke His steeds, and put his glorious armor on. Then greater and more terrible had been The avenging wrath of Jupiter inflamed Against the gods, if Pallas in her fear iss For all the heavenly dwellers had not left Her throne, and, rushing through the portals, snatched The helmet from his head, and from his arm The shield, and from his brawny hand the spear, And laid the brazen weapon by, and thus ,,», Rebuked the fiery temper of the god :— "Thou madman, thou art frantic, thou art los\.! Hast thou not ears to hear, nor any shame Nor reason left? Hast thou not heard the Ivor 's Of white-armed Juno, who so lately left "s Olympian Jupiter? Wouldst thou return In pain and sorrow to the Olympian heights, Driven back ingloriously, and made the cause Of many miseries to all the gods ?—
For Jove would leave the Trojans and their foes, 17» The gallant Greeks, and turn on us, and bring Ruin upon Olympus. He would seize Guilty and guiltless in his rage alike. Wherefore I counsel thee to lay aside Resentment for the slaughter of thy son, 17s Since braver men and stronger have been slain, And will be slain hereafter. Vain it were To seek from death to save the race of man." She said, and, leading back the fiery Mars, Seated him on his throne, while Juno called no Apollo forth, with Iris, messenger Of heaven, and thus in winged accents spake :— "Jove calls you both to Ida. When ye reach Its heights, and look upon his countenance, Receive his sovereign mandate and obey." 1«s So spake imperial Juno, and withdrew And took her seat again, while they in haste Flew toward the mount of Ida, seamed with rills And nurse of savage beasts. Upon the top Of Gargarus they found the Thunderer, ,*, The son of Saturn, sitting. In a cloud Of fragrant haze he sat concealed ; the twain Entered and stood before the God of Storms, Who saw them not displeased, so speedily Had they obeyed his consort. First he turned us To Iris, and in winge:l accents said : — "Haste thee, swift Iris, and report my words To royal Neptune, and report them right.
Bid him, withdrawing from the battle-field, Repair to the assembly of the gods, *» Or the great ocean. If he disobey, Contemning my command, then bid him think Maturely, whether, mighty though he be, He can withstand when I put forth my power Against him. Greater is my strength than his, a0s And elder-born am I. Yet in his pride Of heart he dares to call himself my peer, Though all the others look on me with awe." Thus spake the god, and Iris, whose swift feet Are like the wind, obeyed, and downward plunged From Ida's height to sacred T roy. As when Snow-flakes or icy hail are dropped to earth From clouds before the north wind when it sweeps The sky, so darted Iris to the ground, And stood by mighty Neptune's side, and said :— "O dark-haired shaker of the shores, I bring «s A message from the /Egis-bearer, Jove, That thou, withdrawing from the battle-field, Repair to the assembly of the gods, Or the great ocean. If thou disobey, Contemning his command, then hear his threat: He will come hither and put forth his power Against thee, and he warns thee not to tempt The strife ; for greater is his power than thine, And he is elder-born, though in thy pride itj Of heart thou dost declare thyself the peer Of him whom all the rest regard with awe."
Illustrious Neptune answered with disdain :— "In truth an arrogant speech; he seeks by forte To bar me from my purpose, who can claim n» Rights equal to his own, though great his power. We are three brothers, — Rhea brought us forth, — The sons of Saturn,—Jupiter, and I, And Pluto, regent of the realm below. Three parts were made of all existing things, »» And each of us received his heritage. The lots were shaken; and to me it fell To dwell forever in the hoary deep, And Pluto took the gloomy realm of night, And, lastly, Jupiter the ample heaven «0 And air and clouds. Yet doth the earth remain, With high Olympus, common to us all. Therefore I yield me not to do his will, Great as he is ; and let him be content With his third part. He cannot frighten me «s With gestures of his arm. Let him insult With menaces the daughters and the sons Of his own loves, and give them law, since they Perforce must hear, and patiently submit." Then the fleet-footed Iris spake again : — »?, "O dark-haired Neptune, shall I bear from thee This harsh, defiant answer back to Jove, Or shall it yet be changed? The prudent mind Yields to the occasion, and thou knowest well The Furies wait upon the elder-born." Then spake in turn the god who shakes the shores: —
"0 goddess Ins, thou hast wisely said. An excellent thing it is when messengers Know how to counsel well. But in my heart And soul a wrathful sense of injury Arises when he chides with insolent words Me, who was equal with him in my lot, And born to equal destinies. Yet now, Although offended, I give way; but this I tell thee, and't is from my heart, — if he, In spite of me and Pallas, spoiler-queen, And Juno, Mercury, and Vulcan, spare The towers of Troy, — if he refuse to bring Ruin on her, and glory on the Greeks, Then let him know that hatred without end Or intermission is between us two." As thus he spake, the shaker of the shores Quitted the Grecian army, took his way Seaward, and plunged into the deep. The host Perceived their loss. Then Cloud-compelling J( Turned to Apollo and addressed him thus : — "Now go at once to Hector, mailed in brass, Beloved Phoebus, for the god who shakes The earth, departing to the ocean-deeps, Avoids our wrath; else had the other gods, Even they who far beneath the earth surround Oltl Saturn, heard our quarrel. Well it is For both of us that he, although enraged, Braved not my arm, for otherwise the strife Had not been ended without sweat. Now take
The fringed aegis in thy hands, and shake Its orb before the warrior Greeks, to fill Their hearts with fear. I give, O archer-god, Illustrious Hector to thy charge. Revive The might that dwelt within him, till the Greeks « Reach, in their flight, the fleet and Hellespont; Then shall it be my care, by word and deed, To give them rest and respite from their toils." He spake: Apollo hearkened and obeyed His father, darting down from Ida's height *,$ Like the fleet falcon, chaser of the dove, And swiftest of the race of birds. He found Hector, the warlike Priam's noble 6on, No longer on his bed. He sat upright; The life was coming back; he knew again 390 His friends ; the heavy breathing ceased ; the sweat Was stanched ; the will of aegis-bearing Jove Revived the warrior's strength. The archer-god, Phoebus, approached, and, standing by him, said :— "Why, Hector, son of Priam, dost thou sit w Languishing thus, apart from all the host? Has aught of evil overtaken thee?" And then the crested Hector feebly said: "Who mayst thou be, O kindest of the gods, That thus dost question me? Hast thou not heard That the great warrior Ajax, with a stone, 3" Smote me upon the breast, and made me leave The battle-field, where I o'ertook and slew His comrades by the galleys of the Greeks?
I thought to be this day among the dead s•s In Pluto's mansion ; even now it seemed That I was breathing my dear life away." Then spake again Apollo, archer-god :— "Take courage, for the son of Saturn sends From Ida's summit one who will attend j*, And aid thee, — Phoebus of the golden sword, Long practised to defend thy Troy and thee. Rise now, encouraging thy numerous host Of charioteers to press with their swift steeds Straight toward the roomy galleys of the Greeks, I go before to smooth for them the way, And turn the Achaian bands, and make them flee." He spake, and into the great ruler's breast Breathed strength and courage. As a stabled horse, Fed at his crib with barley, breaks the thong 330 That fastened him, and, issuing, scours the plain Where he was wont in some smooth-flowing stream To bathe his sides, —he holds his head aloft Proudly, and o'er his shoulders streams the mane, — Consciously beautiful, he darts away 33; On nimble knees, that bear him to the fields He knows so well, and pastures of the mares ; — So after he had hearkened to the god Moved the swift feet of Hector, and he flew To cheer his horsemen on. As peasant men 3*, Rush with their dogs in chase of horned stag Or mountain goat, whose refuge is among Thickets and lofty rocks, nor can they take
Their prey, for at their clamor there appears A maned lion in the way, and turns 3« The chasers back, although in hot pursuit, — Thus did the Greeks embattled close pursue The men of Ilium, striking with their swords And two-edged spears ; but when at length they saw Hector among the ranks of armed men, 3s» Their hearts were troubled, and their courage sank. Thoas, Andrannon's son, the bravest far Among the /Etolians, skilled to cast the spear And combat hand to hand, addressed the Greeks. In council few excelled him, when the youths j;s Assembled for debate. With prudent speech Thoas bespake his fellow-warriors thus :— "Gods! what a marvel do mine eyes behold; Hector has risen from death! We fully thought, Each one of us, that, smitten by the hand w Of Telamonian Ajax, he had died. Some god hath rescued and restored to strength This Hector who hath slain, and yet will slay, I fear, so many Greeks. He comes not thus Leading the charge without the aid of Jove, y,s The God of Thunders. Now let all of us Follow this counsel: bid the multitude Retreat upon the ships, and let the rest, Who boast ourselves the bravest of the host, Stand firm and breast his onset, and so break .370 Its fury with our lifted spears. I think, With all his rage, he will be slow to fling
Himself into a band of armed Greeks." He spake ; they hearkened and at once complied j The Ajaxes, the Prince Idomeneus, vs Teucer, Meriones, and Meges, peer Of Mars, assembled all the chiefs, and ranked Their files to encounter Hector and his band Of Trojans, while the multitude fell back To the Greek galleys. Then, in close array, *0 The Trojan host moved forward. Hector led The van in rapid march. Before him walked Phoebus, the terrible aegis in his hands Dazzlingly bright within its shaggy fringe, By Vulcan forged, the great artificer, s And given to Jupiter, with which to rout Armies of men. With this in hand he led The assailants on. The Achaians kept their ground In serried ranks, and a sharp yell arose i*• From Greeks and Trojans. Arrows from the string Flew through the air, and spears from valiant hands. Some pierced the breasts of warrior-youths, but more Fell half-way ere they reached their aim, and plunged Into the ground, still hungering for their prey. As long as Phoebus held the aegis still, 3« The weapons reached and wounded equally Both armies, and in both the people fell; But ever when the god looked face to face On the Greek knights, and shook the orb, and gave A mighty shout, he made their hearts to sink *» Within their bosoms, and their courage fled.
As when two beasts of prey at dead of night Suddenly, while their keeper is away, Scatter a herd of beeves or flock of sheep, So the disheartened Greeks were put to rout, *,s For Phoebus sent among them fear, and gave Victory to Hector and the men of Troy. Then, as the lines were broken, man slew man. First Stichius fell by Hector's hand, and next Arcesilaus ; one was chief among i10 The mailed Boeotians, one the trusty friend Of brave Menestheus. Medon fell before /Eneas, and with him Iasus died. Medon was great Otleus' base-born son, And Ajax was his brother, and he dwelt 4's In Phylace, an exile, for his hand Had slain the brother of his father's wife, The step-dame Eriopis, late espoused. Iasus was appointed to command The warriors sent from Athens, and he claimed 4*, His birth from Sphelus, son of Bucolus. Mecistes fell before Polydamas. Polites struck down Echius in the van, And Clonius died by great Agenor's hand; And Paris, when Deiochus had turned. 43s To flee, among the foremost combatants, Smote him upon the shoulder from behind, And drave the brazen weapon through his heart . Then, while the Trojans stripped the dead, the Greeks
Fled every way, and, falling as they ran m Into the trench and on the stakes, were driven Back o'er the rampart. Hector lifted up His mighty voice, and bade the Trojans leave The bloody spoil and hasten to the ships. "And whomsoever I shall find apart «s In any place, at distance from the ships, There will I slay him. None of all his kin, Women or men, shall build his funeral pile, But dogs shall tear his limbs in sight of Troy." He spake; and on the shoulders of his steeds «*, He laid the lash, and urged them toward the foe, And cheered the Trojans on. They joined their shouts To his, and charged with all their steeds and cars; And fearful was the din. Apollo marched Before them, treading down with mighty feet *c The banks of the deep ditch, and casting them Back to the middle, till a causey rose, Broad, and of length like that to which a spear Reaches when thrown by one who tries his strength. O'er this the Trojans poured into the camp «s0 By squadrons, with Apollo still in front, Holding the marvellous segis. He with ease O'erthrew the rampart. As a boy at play Among the sea-shore sands in childish sport Scatters with feet and hands the little mounds 4ss He reared, thus didst thou cause the mighty work, O archer Phoebus, which the Greeks had reared
With so much toil, to crumble. Thou didst fill Their hearts with eager thoughts of flight, till, hemmed 4s5 Between the assailants and their ships, they stopped And bade each other stand, and raised their hands To all the gods, and offered vows aloud. Gerenian Nestor, guardian of the Greeks, With arms extended toward the starry skies, Prayed earnestly: "O Father Jove, if e'er 4os In fruitful Argos there were burned to thee The thighs of fattened oxen or of sheep, By one who asked a safe return to Greece, And thou didst promise it, remember him, God of Olympus, and avert from us 470 The day of evil. Suffer not the Greeks To perish, slaughtered by the sons of Troy." So spake he supplicating. Jupiter The All-disposer thundered as he heard The old man's prayer. The Trojans by that voice Of aegis-bearing Jove were moved to press 47« The Greeks more resolutely, and were filled With fiercer valor. As a mighty wave On the great ocean, driven before a gale Such as rolls up the hugest billow, sweeps 4s» O'er the ship's side, so swept the Trojan host With dreadful tumult o'er the wall. They drave Their steeds into the camp, and there they fought Beside the galley-sterns, and hand to hand, With two-edged spears, — they from their cars, the Greeks
From their black ships on high with long-stemm poles Which lay upon the decks, prepared for fight At sea, and strongly joined to blades of brass. Patroclus, while the Greeks and Trojans fought Around the wall, at distance from the fleet 490 Sat with the brave Eurypylus in his tent, Amusing him with pleasant talk, and dressed His wound with balms that calmed the bitter pain. But when he saw the Trojans bursting in Over the wall, and heard the din, and saw m The Achaians put to rout, he gave a cry Of sudden grief, and with his open hands Smote both his thighs, and sorrowfully said : — "Eurypylus, I cannot stay with thee, Much as thou needest me, for desperate grows s0» The struggle. Now let thine attendant take The charge of thee. I hasten to persuade Achilles to the field. Who knows but I, With Jove's good help, may change his purpose yet? For potent are the counsels of a friend." its The hero spake, and instantly his feet Bore him away. Meanwhile the Achaian host Firmly withstood the onset of their foes. And yet, though greater was their multitude, They could not drive the Trojans from the fleet, s10 Nor could the Trojans break, with all their power, The serried lines, and reach the tents and ships. As when a plumb-line, in the skilful hands
Of shipwright well instructed in his art By Pallas, squares the beam that builds a bark, s»s So even was the fortune of the fray. While some beside one galley waged the war, And others round another, Hector came To encounter Ajax the renowned, and both Fought for one ship. The Trojan could not drive The Greek away, and burn his ship with fire, pi Nor the Greek drive the Trojan, for a god Had brought him thither. Then did Ajax smite Caletor, son of Clytius, with his spear Upon the breast, as he was bringing fire y,s To burn the ship; he dropped the torch, and fell, With clashing armor. Hector, as he saw His kinsman lying slain amid the dust By the black galley, raised his voice, and thus Called to the Lycians and the men of Troy : — sr, "Hear, men of Troy and Lycia, and ye sons Of Dardanus, who combat hand to hand, Stand firm, and never yield this narrow ground. Rescue the son of Clytius, who has fallen Before the ships, nor let the Achaians make sn His arms their spoil." The hero spake, and aimed His shining spear at Ajax, whom it missed, But smote Lycophron, Master's son, who served Ajax, and dwelt with him, for he had left His native land, Cythera, having slain s40 One of the gallant Cytherean race. Him Hector smote upon the head beneath
The ear with his keen weapon, as he stood Near Ajax ; from the galley's stern he fell Headlong upon the ground, with lifeless limbs. s4s Then to his brother Teucer Ajax spake :— "Dear Teucer, see, our faithful friend is gone, The son of Mastor, from Cythera's isle, Whom we had learned to honor equally With our own parents in our palaces. ss0 He falls before the great-souled Hector's hand. Where, then, are now thy shafts that carry death, And where the bow that Phoebus gave to thee?" He spake, and Teucer, hearkening, came in haste, With his bent bow, and quiver full of shafts, sss And, standing near him, sent his arrows forth Among the Trojan warriors. There he smote Clitus, Pisenor's eminent son, the friend Of the renowned Polydamas, who claimed His birth from Panthoiis. Clitus held the reins, 9s0 Guiding the coursers of Polydamas Where most the crowded Grecian phalanxes Wavered and broke, that so he might support Hector and his companions. Soon he met, Brave as he was, disaster which no hand 93s Had powrer to avert: the bitter arrow struck His neck behind, and from the chariot-seat He fell to earth ; the startled steeds sprang back; The empty chariot rattled. This the king Polydamas perceived, and came to meet b» His steeds, and gave them to Astinoiis,
The son of Protiaon, charging him To keep them ever near, and in his sight, While he, returning, mingled with the throng That struggled in the van. Then Teucer aimed m Another shaft at Hector mailed in brass, Which, had it reached him fighting gallantly, Had made him leave the battle, for his life Had ended there. The act was not unseen By All-disposing Jupiter, whose power s*, Protected Hector, and denied the Greek The glory hoped for; for he snapped in twain The firmly twisted cord as Teucer drew That perfect bow; the brazen arrow flew Aside; the warrior's hands let fall the bow, s«s And, shuddering, he bespake his brother thus : — "Now woe is me! some deity, no doubt, Brings all our plans to nought. T is he whose touch Strikes from my hand the bow, and snaps in twain The cord just twisted, which I bound myself » This morning to the bow, that it might bear The frequent arrow bounding toward the foe." He spake, and thus replied the man of might, The Telamonian Ajax: "Lay aside Thy bow, my brother, and thy store of shafts, ms Since, in displeasure with the Greeks, a god Has made them useless. Haste to arm thy hand With a long spear, and on thy shoulders lay A buckler, and with these attack the foe, And bid thy fellows stand. Let Trojans see
That, even though the day thus far be theirs, They cannot lay their hands on our good ships Without a mighty struggle. Let us all Be mindful of our fame for gallant deeds." He spake, and Teucer went to place the bow «0s Within the tents, and on his shoulders hung A fourfold shield, and placed on his grand brows A stately helmet with a horse-hair crest That nodded fearfully. He took in hand A ponderous spear with brazen blade, and sprang^o Forward with hasty steps, and stood beside His brother Ajax. Hector, when he saw That Teucer's shafts had failed him, called aloud Upon the men of Lycia and of Troy :— "Ye men of Troy and Lycia, and ye sons Of Dardanus who combat hand to hand, Acquit yourselves like men, my friends, and prove Your fiery valor by these roomy ships; For I have seen with mine own eyes the shafts Of their chief warrior rendered impotent «™ By Jupiter. His hand is plainly seen Among the sons of men ; to some he gives Glory above the rest ; from some he takes The glory, and withdraws from their defence. He withers now the courage of the Greeks, ,$ And succors us. Press closely round the fleet, And combat. Whosoe'er among you all, Wounded or beaten down, shall meet his death, So let him die; 't is no inglorious fate
To perish fighting in his country's cause; «v, And he shall leave his wife and children safe, His home and household store inviolate, If now the Greeks depart to their own land." With words like these he filled their hearts anew With strength and courage. On the other side «3s Ajax exhorted thus his warrior friends : — * Shame on you, Greeks! We perish here, unless We rescue with strong arms our host and fleet. Think ye that, should the crested Hector seize Our galleys, ye may reach your homes on foot? ,*, Hear ye not Hector's voice, who, fiercely bent To burn our ships with fire, is cheering on His warriors? To no dance he summons them, But to the battle. Nought is left for us, And other counsel there is none, save this: «« Close with the foe; let every hand put forth Its strength; far better't were to die at once, Or make at once our safety sure, than thus To waste away, in lingering fight, beside Our ships, destroyed by weaker arms than ours." ss0 So spake the chief, and all who heard received Courage and strength. Then Hector put to death Schedius, the son of Perimedes, prince Of the Phocaians. Ajax also slew Laodamas, Antenor's honored son, «ss A chief of infantry. Polydamas Struck down Cyllenian Otus, who had come, The comrade of Phylides, at the head
Of the high-souled Epeians. Meges saw, And rushed upon Polydamas, who sprang aso Aside unharmed, for Phoebus suffered not The son of Panthoiis thus to be o'erthrown, Fighting among the foremost. But the spear Of Meges wounded Croesmus in the breast; He fell with clanging arms. The slayer stripped «s The corpse; but Dolops, son of Lampus, skilled To wield the spear, leaped on him in the act. Lampus, the father, best of men, was son Of king Laomedon, and eminent For warlike prowess. Dolops struck the shield «7» Of Meges in the midst; the corselet stayed The blade with its close jointed plates, and saved The warrior's life. That corselet Phyleus brought From Ephyre, beside the Selleis, Given by his host, Euphetes, king of men, «n For his defence in battle, and it now Preserved his son from death. Then Meges smote With his sharp spear the helm that Dolops wore, And from its summit struck the horse-hair crest, New-tinged with purple, and the cone entire «, Fell midst the dust. While Meges, standing firm, Fought thus, and hoped the victory, to his aid Came warlike Menelaus, unobserved, And, standing near, smote Dolops from behind, Beneath the shoulder, and drave through the spear Till it appeared beyond. The Trojan fell «* Upon his face, and both the Greeks rushed on
To wrench the brazen armor from his limbs, When Hector saw his fall and called aloud Upon the kindred of the slain. He first «*, Rebuked the valiant Melanippus, son Of Hicetaon, who but lately fed His slow-paced beeves at Percote, while yet The enemy was far from Troy ; but when The Achaians landed from their well-oared barks, ,*s He came to Troy, and took an eminent place Among the Trojans. Near to Priam's halls He had his dwelling, honored equally With Priam's sons. Him Hector thus rebuked :— "Why, Melanippus, are we loitering thus? 7,» Grievest thou not to see thy kinsman slain? And see'st thou not how eagerly the Greeks Are spoiling Dolops of his arms? Come on With me. No time is this for distant fight, But either we must rout the Greeks, or they 70s Will level to the ground the lofty towers Of Ilium, and will slay its citizens." He spake, and led the way ; his godlike friend Followed him, while the son of Telamon, Ajax, exhorted thus the sons of Greece :— 710 "Be men, my friends, and let a noble dread Of shame possess your hearts, and jealously Look to each other's honor in the heat Of battle; for to men who flee there comes No glory, and that way no safety lies." 715 He spake, and all were eager to drive back
The assaulting foe; they heeded well his words, And drew around their barks a fence of mail, While Jove urged on the Trojans. Then it was That Menelaus, brave in battle, spake 7» To rouse the courage of Antilochus :— "Antilochus, there is no other Greek Younger than thou, or fleeter; none so strong For combat. Would that, springing on the foe, Thou mightest strike some Trojan warrior down." 7n So speaking, he drew back; but he had roused The courage of his friend, who, springing forth From midst the foremost combatants, took aim, First looking keenly round, with his bright spear, From which the Trojans shrank as they beheld 73» The hero cast it. Not in vain he threw The weapon, for it struck upon the breast Brave Melanippus, Hicetaon's son; Beneath the pap it smote him as he came. He fell with ringing arms; Antilochus 71s Sprang toward him like a hound that springs to seize A wounded fawn, which, leaping from its lair, Is stretched disabled by the hunter's dart. So sprang the stout Antilochus on thee, O Melanippus ! —sprang to spoil thy limbs im Of armor; but the noble Hector saw, And, hastening through the thick of battle, came Against him. Mighty as he was in war, Yet ventured not Antilochus to wait His coming; but as flees a savage beast,
Conscious of guilty deed, when, having slain Herdsman or hound, that kept the pastured kine, He steals away before a crowd of men, So fled the son of Nestor. On his rear The Trojans under Hector poured a storm 7s0 Of weapons, and the din was terrible. Yet when he reached the serried ranks of Greece He turned and stood. Meanwhile the Trojan host, Like ravening lions, fiercely rushed against The. galleys, that the will of Jupiter 7ss Might be fulfilled ; for now he nerved their limbs With vigor ever new, while he denied Stout hearts and victory to the Greeks, and rheered Their foes with hope. His purpose was to give The victory to Hector, Priam's son, tsm Till he should cast upon the beaked ships The fierce, devouring fire, and bring to pass The end for which the cruel Thetis prayed. Therefore did Jove the All-disposer wait Till from a burning galley he should see 7«s The flames arise. Then must the Trojan host, — Such was his will,— retreating from the fleet, Yield to the Greeks the glory of the day. For this he moved the already eager heart Of Hector, son of Priam, to attack tv, The roomy ships. The hero was aroused To fury fierce as Mars when brandishing His spear, or as a desolating flame That rages on a mountain-side among
The thickets of a close-grown wood. His lips 77s Were white with foam; his eyes from underneath His frowning brows streamed fire ; and as he fought, Upon the hero's temples fearfully The helmet nodded. Jupiter himself Sent aid from his high seat, and heaped on him 7*, Honor and fame beyond the other chiefs, — And they were many, —for his term of life Was to be short. Minerva even now Was planning to bring on its closing day, Made fatal by the might of Peleus' son. 7«s And now he strove to break the Grecian ranks, Assaulting where he saw the thickest crowd And the best weapons ; yet in vain he strove With all his valor. Through the serried lines He could not break ; the Greeks in solid squares 790 Resisted, like a rock that huge and high By the gray deep abides the buffetings Of the shrill winds and swollen waves that beat Against it. Firmly thus the Greeks withstood The Trojan host, and fled not. In a blaze 79s Of armor, Hector, rushing toward their ranks, Fell on them like a mighty billow raised By the strong cloud-born winds, that flings itself On a swift ship, and whelms it in its spray, While fearfully among the cordage howls s*, The blast; the sailors trcmble and are faint With fear, as men who deem their death-hour nigh. So the Greek warriors were dismayed at heart.
As when a hungry lion suddenly Springs on a herd of kine that crop the grass *,s By hundreds in the broad moist meadow-grounds, Beneath the eye of one who never learned To guard his horned charge from beasts of prey, But ever walks before them or behind, While the grim spoiler bounds into the midst e-0 And makes a prey of one, and all the rest Are scattered in affright, so all the Greeks Were scattered by the will of heaven before Hector and Father Jove. Yet only one, Young Periphoetes of Mycenae, fell, s.« The son of Copreus. Once his father went An envoy from Eurystheus to the court Of mighty Hercules. The son excelled The father in all gifts of form and mind, In speed, in war, in council eminent Among the noblest of his land. His death Brought Hector new renown ; for as he turned, Stepping by chance upon his buckler's rim, That reached the ground, — the buckler which had been His fence against the enemy's darts, — he fell m Backward, his helmet clashing fearfully Around his temples. Hector saw, and came In haste, and pierced his bosom with his spear, Among his fellow-warriors, who with grief Beheld, yet dared not aid him, such their awe «30 Of noble Hector. Now the Greeks retired
Among that row of galleys which were first Drawn up the beach; the foe poured after them, In hot pursuit; again the Greeks fell back, Constrained, and left that foremost row behind, *a And stood beside their tents in close array, And not dispersed throughout the camp, for shame And fear restrained them, and unceasingly With shouts they bade each other bravely stand. Chiefly Gerenian Nestor, wise to guide s« The counsels of the Greeks, adjured them all, And in their parents' name, to keep their ground. "O friends, be men ; so act that none may feel Ashamed to meet the eyes of other men. Think each one of his children and his wife, «« His home, his parents, living yet or dead. For them, the absent ones, I supplicate, And bid you rally here, and scorn to fly." He spake, and his brave words to every heart Carried new strength and courage. Pallas then «s» Lifted the heaven-sent cloud that veiled the fight, And all things in the clear full light were seen On either side, both where the galleys lay And where the warriors struggled. They beheld Hector the great in war, and all his host, ess Both those who formed the rear and wielded not Their arms, and those who combated in front Beside the ships. And now it pleased no more The soul of valiant Ajax to remain In the thick squadrons with the other Greeks,
But, striding on the galley-decks, he bore A sea-pike two and twenty cubits long, Huge, and beset with iron nails. As when One who is skilled to vault on running steeds Chooses four horses from a numerous herd, a* And on the highway to a populous town Drives them, while men and women in a crowd Behold his feats with wonder, as he leaps Boldly, without a fall, from steed to steed, And back again, and all the while they run, e7o So on the lofty decks of those good ships From ship to ship flew Ajax, lifting up His mighty voice, — a shout that reached to heaven, — And bade the Greeks defend their fleet and tents. Nor loitered Hector in those armed throngs «w Of Troy, but as a tawny eagle swoops Upon a flock of birds that seek their food Along a river's border, — geese or cranes, Or long-necked swans, — so Hector in hot haste Sprang toward a galley with an azure prow, aso While mightily the power of Jove impelled The hero onward, and inflamed his train With courage. Fiercely then around the ships The struggle was renewed. Thou wouldst have said No toils of war could tire those resolute arms, s»s So stubbornly they fought. In every mind The thought was this: the Greeks were in despair Of rescue, and believed their hour had come
To perish; every Trojan hoped to give The fleet to flames, and slay the sons of Greece. *» With thoughts like these the hostile warriors closed. Then Hector laid his hand upon the stern Of a stanch galley, beautiful and swift, In which l'rotesilaiis came to Troy,— It never bore him back. Around its keel sss The Trojans and the Greeks fought hand to hand, And slew each other. For no more they sent The arrow or the javelin from afar, Waiting to see the wound it gave, but each With equal fury pressed upon his foe *» With halberd and with trenchant battle-axe, Huge sword and two-edged spear. Upon the ground Had fallen many a fair black-hilted sword With solid handles, some from slain men's hands, Some from lopped arms of warriors; the dark earth Ran red with blood. But Hector, having laid 90« His hand upon the galley's stern, held fast To the carved point, and called upon his men :— "Bring fire, and press in throngs upon the foe; For now doth Jove vouchsafe to us a day »10 Worth" all the past, — a day on which we make The ships our prey. Against the will of Heaven They landed on our coast, and brought on us Disas'ers many, through the coward fears Of our own elders, who denied my wish 91s To combat at the galleys, and held back The people. But if then the Thunderer
Darkened our minds, his spirit moves us now In what we do, and we obey his will.-' He spake ; and they with fiercer valor fell sn0 Upon the Greeks. Even Ajax could no more Withstand the charge, but, fearing to be slain, Amid a storm of darts withdrew a space, To where the seven-foot bench of rowers lay, And left the galley's stern. There, as he stood, He watched the assailants keenly, and beat back With thrusts of his long spear whoever brought The firebrand. With terrific shouts he called Upon the Greeks to combat manfully:— "O friends, Achaian heroes, ministers 0» Of Mars, be men, be mindful of your fame For valor. Do ye dream that in your rear Are succors waiting us, or firmer walls That may protect us yet? Nay, no fenced town im Have we for refuge, flanked with towers from which Fresh troops may take our place. Between the sea And country of the well-armed Trojans lie Our tents ; our native land is far away; And now our only hope of safety left Is in our weapons: there is no retreat." wo He spake, and mightily with his sharp spear Thrust at whoever of the men of Troy At Hector's bidding came with fire to burn The galleys. On the blade of that long spear The hero took them as they came, and slew ws In close encounter twelve before the fleet.

XVI

.

SUCH was the struggle for that gallant bark. Meanwhile Patroclus stood beside his friend The shepherd of the people, Peleus' son, And shed hot tears, as when a fountain sheds Dark waters streaming down a precipice. s The great Achilles, swift of foot, beheld And pitied him, and spake these winged words : — "Why weepest thou, Patroclus, like a girl, — A little girl that by her mother's side Runs, importuning to be taken up, ,o And plucks her by the robe, and stops her way, And looks at her, and cries, until at last She rests within her arms? Thou art like her, Patroclus, with thy tears. Dost thou then bring Sad tidings to the Myrmidons or me? 's Or hast thou news from Phthia? It is said That still Menoetius, son of Actor, lives, And Peleus also, son of /Eacus, Among the Myrmidons. Full bitterly Should we lament to hear that either died. »0 Or mournest thou because the Achaians fall Through their own folly by the roomy ships? Speak, and hide nothing, for I too would know." And thou, O knight Patroclus, with a sigh Deep drawn, didst answer thus : " Be not displeased, Page 95 Book XVI. 95 Achilles, son of Peleus, bravest far *. Of all the Achaian army! for the Greeks Endure a bitter lot. The chiefs who lale Were deemed their mightiest are within the ships, Wounded or stricken down. There Diomed, », The gallant son of Tydeus, lies, and there Ulysses, the great spearman, wounded both; And Agamemnon ; and Eurypylus, Driven from the field, an arrow in his thigh. Round them the healers, skilled in remedies, ss Attend and dress their painful wounds, while thou, Achilles, sittest here implacable. O, never be such fierce resentments mine As thou dost cherish, who art only brave For mischief! Whom wilt thou hereafter aid, « If now thou rescue not the perishing Greeks? O merciless! it cannot surely be That Peleus was thy father, or the queen Thetis thy mother; the green sea instead And rugged precipices brought thee forth, « For savage is thy heart. But if thou heed The warning of some god, if thou hast heard Aught which thy goddess-mother has received From Jove, send me at least into the war, And let me lead thy Myrmidons, that thus s» The Greeks may have some gleam of hope. And give The armor from thy shoulders. I will wear Thy mail, and then the Trojans, at the sight, May think I am Achilles, and may pause Page 96 96 The Iliad. From fighting, and the warlike sons of Greece, a Tired as they are, may breathe once more, and gain A respite from the conflict. Our fresh troops May easily drive back upon their town The weary Trojans from our tents and fleet." So spake he, sighing ; rash and blind, he asked « Death for himself and evil destiny. Achilles the swift-footed also drew A heavy sigh, and thus in turn he spake :— "What, O divine Patroclus, hast thou said? I fear no omen yet revealed to me; «s Nor has my goddess-mother told me aught From Jove; but ever in my heart and soul Rankles the painful sense of injury done By one who, having greater power, deprives An equal of his right, and takes away 70 The prize he won. This is my wrong, and this The cause of all my bitterness of heart. Her whom the sons of Greece bestowed on me As my reward, a trophy of my spear, After the sack of a fenced city, — her 7s Did Agamemnon, son of Atreus, take Out of my hands, as if I were a wretch, A worthless outcast. But let that affront Be with the things that were. It is not well To bear a grudge forever. I have said My anger should not cease to burn until The clamor of the battle and the assault Should reach the fleet. But go thou and put on Page 97 Book XVI. 97 My well-known armor; lead into the field My Myrmidons, men that rejoice in war, «s Since like a lowering cloud the men of Troy Surround the fleet, and the Achaians stand In narrow space close pressed beside the sea, And all the city of Ilium flings itself Against them, confident of victory, 90 Now that the glitter of my helm no mose Flashes upon their eyes. Yet very soon Their flying host would fill the trenches here With corpses, had but Agamemnon dealt Gently with me; and now their squadrons close ss Around our army. Now no more the spear Is wielded by Tydides Diomed In rescue of the Greeks; no more the shout Of Agamemnon's hated throat is heard; But the man-queller Hector, lifting up «» His voice, exhorts the Trojans, who, in throngs, Raising the war-cry, fill the plain, and drive The Greeks before them. Gallantly lead on The charge, Patroclus; rescue our good ships; Let not the enemy give them to the flames, And cut us off from our desired return. Follow my counsel ; bear my words in mind; So shalt thou win for me among the Greeks Great honor and renown, and they shall bring The beautiful maiden back with princely gifts. "0 When thou hast driven the assailants from the fleet, Return thou hither. If the Thunderer, vol. 11. 5 G Page 98 98 The Iliad. Husband of Juno, suffer thee to gain That victory, seek no further to prolong The combat with the warlike sons of Troy, «s Apart from me, lest I be brought to shame, Nor, glorying in the battle and pursuit, Slaying the Trojans as thou goest, lead Thy men to Troy, lest from the Olympian mount One of the ever-living gods descend i»i Against thee : Phoebus loves the Trojans well. But come as soon as thou shalt see the ships In safety; leave the foes upon the plain Contending with each other. Would to Jove The All-Father, and to Pallas, and the god «s Who bears the bow, Apollo, that of all The Trojans, many as they are, and all The Greeks, not one might be reprieved from death, While thou and I alone were left alive To overthrow the sacred walls of Troy." ,*, So talked they with each other. Ajax, whelmed Beneath a storm of darts, meantime but ill Endured the struggle, for the will of Jove And the fierce foe prevailed. His shining helm Rang fearfully, as on his temples fell, Stroke following after stroke, the weapons hurled Against its polished studs. The buckler borne Firmly on his left arm, and shifted oft From side to side, had wearied it, and yet The Trojans, pressing round him, could not drive, With all their darts, the hero from his place. mi Page 99 Book XVI. 99 Heavily heaved his panting chest; his limbs Streamed with warm sweat; there was no breathing- time; On danger danger followed, toil on toil. Now, Muses, dwellers of Olympus, tell us How first the galleys of the Greeks were fired. Hector drew near, and smote with his huge sword The ashen spear of Ajax just below The socket of the blade, and cut the stem In two. The son of Telamon in vain 1s» Brandished the severed weapon, while afar The brazen blade flew off, and ringing fell To earth. Then Ajax in his mighty mind Acknowledged that the gods were in the war, And shuddered, knowing that the Thunderer iss Was thwarting all his warlike purposes, And willed the victory to Troy. The chief Withdrew beyond the reach of spears, while fast The eager enemy hurled the blazing brands At the swift ship, and wrapped the stern in flames Unquenchable. Achilles saw, and smote -«, His thigh, and spake: "Patroclus, noble friend And knight, make haste: already I behold The flames that rage with fury at the fleet. Now, lest the enemy seize our ships and we Be barred of our return, put quickly on Thy armor; be my task to call the troops." He spake: Patroclus then in glittering brass Arrayed himself; and first around his thighs Page 100 IOO The Iliad. He put the beautiful greaves, and fastened them w Wilh silver clasps; around his chest he bound The breastplate of the swift /Eacides, With star-like points, and richly chased ; he hung The sword with silver studs and blade of brass Upon his shoulders, and with it the shield ,:s Solid and vast; upon his gallant head He placed the glorious helm with horse-hair plume, That grandly waved on high. Two massive spears He took, that fitted well his grasp, but left The spear which great Achilles only bore, ,so Heavy and huge and strong, and which no arm Among the Greeks save his could poise ; his strength Alone sufficed to wield it. 'T was an ash Which Chiron felled in Pelion's top, and gave To Peleus, that it yet might be the death ,*s Of heroes. Then he called, to yoke with speed The steeds, Automedon, whom he esteemed Next to Achilles, that great scatterer Of armies; for he found him ever firm In battle, breasting faithfully its shock. 190 Automedon led forth to take the yoke Xanthus and Balius, coursers that in speed Were like the wind. Podarge brought them forth To Zephyrus, while she, the Harpy, grazed By ocean's streams. Upon the outer side 19s He joined to them the noble Pedasus, Brought by Achilles from the captured town Where ruled Eetion. Though of mortal stock, Page 101 Book XVI. 101 Well might he match with those immortal steeds. Meanwhile Achilles armed the Myrmidons, »», Passing from tent to tent. Like ravening wolves, Terribly strong, that, having slain among The hills an antlered stag of mighty size, Tear and devour it, while their jaws are stained With its red blood, then gather in a herd *,s About some darkly flowing stream, and lap The sullen water with their slender tongues, And drop the clots of blood from their grim mouths, And, although gorged, are fierce and fearless still, — So came the leaders of the Myrmidons, »,» In rushing crowds, about the valiant friend Of swift /Eacides. Among them stood Achilles, great in war, encouraging The charioteers and warriors armed with shields. Achilles, dear to Jupiter, had led »is Fifty swift barks to Ilium, and in each Were fifty men, companions at the oar. O'er these he gave command to five; himself, Supreme in power, was ruler over all. One band the nobly armed Menestheus led, 0*, Son of Spercheius. To that river-god, Beautiful Polydora brought him forth, Daughter of Peleus; she, a mortal maid, Met an immortal's love. Yet Borus, son Of Perieres, owned the boy and took »s The mother for his bride, with princely dower Eudorus led the second band, a youth Page 102 102 The Iliad. Of warlike mould, whom Polymela bore, Daughter of Phylas, graceful in the dance. In secrecy she brought him forth, for once The mighty Argus-queller saw the maid Among the choir of those who danced and sang At Dian's festival, the huntress-queen, Who bears the golden shafts; he saw and loved And, climbing to her chamber, met by stealth 23s The damsel, and she bore a gallant son, Eudorus, swift of foot and brave in war. When Ilithyia, midwife goddess, gave The boy to see the pleasant light of day, The stout Echecleus, son of Actor, brought »*, The mother to his house, with liberal dower. The aged Phylas reared the child she left Tenderly as a son, and loved him well. Pisander, warlike son of Msemalus, Commanded the third squadron ; none like him 34s Among the Myrmidons could wield the spear Except Pelides. Phoenix, aged knight, Led the fourth squadron. With the fifth and last There came Alcimedon, Laerceus' son, As leader. When their ranks were duly formed, »s» Achilles spake to them in earnest words :— "Now, Myrmidons, forget no single word Of all the threats ye uttered against Troy Since first my wrath began. Ye blame me much, And say: 'Hard-hearted son of Peleus, sure «s Thy mother must have suckled thee on gall; Page 103 Book XVI. 103 For sternly thou dost keep us in the ships, Unwilling as we are. We might, at least, Crossing the sea, return in our good ships, If thus thine anger is to last.' These words •*, Ye utter oft when our assemblies meet, And now the great occasion is at hand Which ye have longed for ; now let him whose heart Is fearless meet the Trojans valiantly." He spake, and roused their courage and their might, *s And as they heard their king they brought their rank-, To closer order. As an architect Builds up, with closely fitting stones, the wall Of some tall mansion, proof against the blast, So close were now the helms and bossy shields, »70 Shield leaned on shield, and helm on helm, and man On man, and on the glittering helmet-cones The horse-hair plumes with every motion touched Each other, so compact the squadrons stood. Two heroes, nobly armed, were at their head, to Patroclus and Automedon, and both Had but one thought, — to combat in the van. Entering his tent, Achilles raised the lid Of a fair coffer, beautifully wrought, Which silver-footed Thetis placed on board *>0 His bark, and filled with tunics, cloaks well lined, And fleecy carpets. There he also kept A goblet richly chased, from which no lip Of man, save h'S, m•ght drink the dark red wine, Page 104 104 The Iliad. Nor wine be poured to any god save Jove, »es The mighty Father. This he took, in hand And purified with sulphur first, and then Rinsed with clear water. Next, with washen hands, He drew the dark red wine, and stood without, In the open space, and, pouring out the wine, w Prayed with his eyes turned heavenward, not un- heard By Jupiter, who wields the thunderbolt. "Dodonian Jove, Pelasgian, sovereign King, Whose dwelling is afar, and who dost rule Dodona winter-bound, where dwell thy priests, The Selli, with unwashen feet, who sleep Upon the ground! Thou once hast heard my prayer, And thou hast honored me, and terribly Avenged me on the Greeks. Accomplish yet This one request of mine. I shall remain *» Among the rows of ships, but in my stead I send my comrade, who will lead to war My vast array of Myrmidons. With him, O God of Thunders, send the victory. Make his heart bold; let even Hector learn w Whether my follower, though alone, can wage Successful war, or conquer only then When I go forth with him into the field Of slaughter. When he shall have beaten back The assailants from the fleet, let him return 310 Unharmed to my good galleys and to me. With all his arms and all his valiant men." Page 105 Book XVI. 105 So spake he, offering prayer, and Jupiter, The Great Disposer, hearkened. Half the prayer The All-Father granted him, and half denied: 3's To drive the storm of battle from the fleet He granted, but denied his friend's return In safety. When the warrior thus had prayed, And poured the wine to Father Jove, he went Into his tent again, and there replaced s*, The goblet in the coffer. Coming forth, He stood before the entrance to behold The terrible encounter of the hosts. The newly armed, led by their gallant chief, Patroclus, marched in warlike order forth, 3as And in high hope, to fall upon the foe. As wasps, that by the wayside build their cells, Angered from time to time by thoughtless boys,— Whence mischief comes to many, — if by chance Some passing traveller should unwittingly 3* Disturb them, all at once are on the wing, And all attack him, to defend their young So fearless and so fierce the Myrmidons Poured from their fleet, and mighty was the din. Patroclus with loud voice exhorted them : — «s "O Myrmidons, companions of the son Of Peleus, bear in mind, my friends, your fame For valor, and be men, that we who serve Achilles, we who combat hand to hand, May honor him by our exploits, and teach 340 Wide-ruling Agamemnon how he erred 5* Page 106 1o6 The Iliad. Slighting the bravest warrior of the Greeks." These words awoke the courage and the might Of all who heard them, and in close array They fell upon the Trojans. Fearfully »s The fleet around them echoed to the sound Of Argives shouting. When the Trojans saw, In glittering arms, Menoetius' gallant son And his attendant, every heart grew faint With fear ; the close ranks wavered ; for they thought That the swift son of Peleus at the fleet Had laid aside his wrath, and was again The friend of Agamemnon. Eagerly They looked around for an escape from death. Then first Patroclus cast his shining spear w Into the crowd before him, where they fought Most fiercely round the stern of the good ship Of brave Protesilaus. There it smote Pyrcechmes, who had led from Amydon, On the broad Axius, his Paeonian knights. i* Through his right shoulder went the blade ; he fell, Heavily groaning, to the earth. His band Of warriors from Paeonia, panic-struck, Fled from Patroclus as they saw their chief Cut off, their bravest in the battle-field. 3«s So from the ship he drave the foe, and quenched The blazing fire. There lay the half-burnt bark, While with a mighty uproar fled the host Of Troy, and from between the beaked ships Poured after them with tumult infinite s« Page 107 Book XVI. 107 The Greeks. As when from some high mountain-top The God of Lightnings, Jupiter, sweeps off The overshadowing cloud, at once appear The watch-lowers and the headland heights and lawns All in full light, and all the unmeasured depth 37s Of ether opens, so the Greeks, when thus Their fleet was rescued from the hostile flame, Breathed for a space ; and yet they might not cease From battle, for not everywhere alike Were chased the Trojans from the dark-hulled ships Before the Greeks, but struggled still to keep 3»1 The mastery, and yielded but to force. Then in that scattered conflict of the chiefs Each Argive slew a warrior. With his spear The brave son of Menoetius made a thrust *i At Areilochus, and pierced his thigh, Just as he turned away, and through the part Forced the keen weapon, splintering as it went The bone, and brought the Trojan to the ground; And warlike Menelaus pierced the breast w, Of Thoas where the buckler left it bare, And took his life. The son of Phyleus saw Amphiclus rushing on, and with his spear Met him and pierced his leg below the knee, Where brawniest is the limb. The blade cut through The sinews, and his eyes were closed in night. ws There fought the sons of Nestor. One of these, Antilochus, transfixed with his good spear Page 108 1o8 The Iliad. Atymnius through the flank, and brought him down At his own feet. With sorrow Maris saw 4,» His brother fall, and toward Antilochus Flew to defend the corpse; but ere he strook, The godlike Thrasymedes, with a blow That missed not, smote his shoulder, tearing off With the spear's blade upon the upper arm 4..s The muscles from the bone. With ringing arms He fell, and darkness gathered o'er his eyes. Thus were two brothers by two brothers slain, And sent to Erebus; two valiant friends Were they of King Sarpedon, and the sons »,« Of Amisodarus, who reared and fed Chimera, the destroyer of mankind. O.lean Ajax, springing forward, seized On Cleobulus, for the struggling crowd Hindered his flight. He took the Trojan's life, 41s Smiting the neck with his huge-handled sword; The blade grew warm with blood, and cruel fate Brought darkness o'er the dying warrior's eyes. Peneleus fought with Lycon ; each had cast His spear and missed his aim, and now with swords The twain encountered. Lycon dealt a stroke Upon the crested helmet of his foe, And the blade failed him, breaking at the hilt. Meantime Peneleus smote beneath the ear The neck of Lycon : deep the weapon went; 47s The severed head, held only by the skin, Dropped to one side, and life forsook the limbs. Page 109 Book XVI. Meriones, o'ertaking Acamas, In rapid flight, discharged a mighty blow On his left shoulder as he climbed his car; 4*, He fell, and darkness gathered o'er his eyes. Then plunged Idomeneus the cruel spear Into the mouth of Erymas. The blade Passed on beneath the brain, and pierced the neck, And there divided the white bones. It dashed 4r. The teeth out ; both the eyes were filled with blood, Which gushed from mouth and nostrils as he breathed; And the black cloud of death came over him. Thus every Grecian leader slew his man. As ravening wolves that spring on lambs and kids, And seize them, wandering wide among the hills «, Beyond the keeper's care, and bear them off, And rend with cruel fangs their helpless prey, So fiercely did the Achaians fling themselves Upon the men of Troy, who only thought «s Of flight from that tumultuous strife, and quite Forgot their wonted valor. All the while The greater Ajax sought to hurl his spear At Hector, clad in brazen mail, who yet, Expert in battle, kept his ample chest 4^ Hid by his bull's-hide shield, and, though he heard The hiss of darts and clash of spears, and saw The fortune of the field deserting him, Lingered to rescue his beloved friends. As from the summit of Olympus spreads 43s Page 110 I IO The Iliad. A cloud into the sky that late was clear, When Jove brings on the tempest, with such speed In clamorous flight the Trojans left the fleet, Yet passed they not the trench in seemly plight. The rapid steeds of Hector bore him safe *s0 Across with all his arms, while, left between The high banks of the trench, the Trojan host Struggled despairingly. The fiery steeds, Harnessed to many a chariot, left it there With broken pole. Patroclus followed close, With mighty voice encouraging the Greeks, And meditating vengeance on the foe, That noisily ran on, and right and left Were scattered, filling all the ways. The dust Rose thick and high, and spread, and reached the clouds, 47" As with swift feet the Trojan coursers held Their way to Ilium from the tents and ships. Patroclus where he saw the wildest rout Drave thither, shouting threats. Full many a chief Fell under his own axle from his car, «s And chariots with a crash were overthrown. The swift, immortal horses which the gods Bestowed on Peleus leaped the trench at once, Eager to reach the plain. As eagerly Patroclus longed to overtake and smite t«o Hector, whose steeds were hurrying him away. As when, in autumn time, the dark-brown earth Is whelmed with water from the stormy clouds, Page 111 Book XVI. 111 When Jupiter pours down his heaviest rains, Offended at men's crimes who override 4*s The laws by violence, and drive justice forth From the tribunals, heedless of the gods And their displeasure, — all the running streams Are swelled to floods, — the furious torrents tear The mountain slopes, and, plunging from the heights With mighty roar, lay waste the works of mtn, «, And fling themselves into the dark-blue sea, — Thus with loud tumult fled the Trojan horse. Patroclus, having cut the nearest bands Of Troy in pieces, made his warriors turn «s Back to the fleet, and, eager as they were, Stopped the pursuit that led them toward the town. Then, in the area bounded by the sea, River, and lofty wall, he chased and smote And took full vengeance. With his glittering spear He wounded Pronoiis where the buckler left soi The breast exposed ; the Trojan with a clash Fell to the earth, and life forsook his limbs. Advancing in his might, Patroclus smote Thestor, the son of Enops, as he sat v% Cowering upon his sumptuous seat, o'ercome With fear, and dropped the reins. Through his right cheek Among the teeth Patroclus thrust his spear, And o'er the chariot's border drew him forth With the spear's stem. As when an angler sits v, Upon a jutting rock, and from the sea Page 112 112 The Iliad. Draws a huge fish with line and gleaming hook, So did Patroclus, with his shining spear, Draw forth the panting Trojan from his car, And shook him clear: he fell to earth and died. s•1 As Eryalus then came swiftly on, Patroclus flung a stone, and on the brow Smote him; the Trojan's head, beneath the blow, Parted in two within the helm ; he fell Headlong to earth, a prey to ghastly death. s» Then slew he Erym.is, Amphoterus, Epaltes, Pyris, Ipheus, Echius, Tlepolemus, Damastor's son, and next Euippus; nor was Polymelus spared, The son of Argias, —smitten all, and thrown, s»s Slain upon slain, along their mother earth. And now Sarpedon, as he saw his friends, The unbelted Lycians, falling by the hand Of Menoetiades, exhorted thus The gallant Lycians: "Shame upon you all, s30 My Lycians! whither do you flee? Be bold! For I myself will meet this man, and learn Who walks the field in triumph thus, and makes Such havoc in our squadrons; for his hand H.is laid full miny a gallant warrior low." 3v. He spake, and from his car with all his arms Sprang to the ground, while on the other side Patroclus, as he saw him come, leaped down And left his chariot. As on some tall rock Two vultures, with curved talons and hooked beaks, Page 113 Book XVI. "3 Fight screaming, so these two with furious cries s«i Advanced against each other. When the son Of crafty Saturn saw them meet, his heart Was touched with pity, and he thus bespake His spouse and sister Juno: "Woe is me 1 s4s Sarpedon, most beloved of men, is doomed To die, o'ercome by Menoetiades. And now I halt between two purposes, — Whether to bear him from this fatal fight, Alive and safe, to Lycia's fertile fields, ss0 Or let him perish by his enemy's hand." Imperial, large-eyed Juno answered thus :— "What words, dread son of Saturn, hast thou said! Wouldst thou deliver from the common lot Of death a mortal doomed long since by fate? sss Do as thou wilt, but be thou sure of this, — The other gods will not approve. And bear In mind these words of mine. If thou shouldst send Sarpedon home to Lycia safe, reflect Some other god may claim the right, like thee, s* To rescue his beloved son from death In battle ; for we know that in the war Round Priam's noble city are many sons Of gods, who will with vehement anger see Thy interposing hand. Yet if he be s«3 So dear to thee, and thou dost pity him, Let him in mortal combat be o'ercome By Menoetiades, and when the breath Of life has left his frame, give thou command Page 114 1t4 The Iliad. To Death and gentle Sleep to bear him hence st» To the broad realm of Lycia. There his friends And brethren shall perform the funeral rites; There shall they build him up a tomb, and rear A column, — honors that become the dead." She ceased, nor did the All-Father disregard sn Her words. He caused a bloody dew to fall Upon the earth in sorrow for the son Whom well he loved, and whom Patroclus soon Should slay upon the fertile plain of Troy, Far from the pleasant land that saw his birth. , The warriors now drew near. Patroclus slew The noble Thrasymelus, who had been Sarpedon's valiant comrade in the war. Below the belt he smote him, and he fell Lifeless. Sarpedon threw his shining lance; ss« It missed, but struck the courser Pedasus In the right shoulder. With a groan he fell In dust, and, moaning, breathed his life away. Then the two living horses sprang apart, And the yoke creaked, and the entangled reins s90 Were useless, fastened to the fallen horse. Automedon, the mighty spearman, saw The remedy, and from his brawny thigh He drew his sword, and cut the outside horse Loose from his fellows. They again were brought Together, and obeyed the reins once more; And the two chiefs renewed the mortal fight. And now, again, Sarpedon's shining spear Page 115 Book XVI. "5 Was vainly flung; the point, in passing o'er Patroclus's left shoulder, gave no wound. In turn, Patroclus, hurling not in vain His weapon, smote him where the midriff's web Holds the tough heart. He fell as falls an oak Or poplar or tall pine, which workmen hew Among the mountains with their sharpened steel ,s To frame a ship. So he before his steeds And chariot fell upon the bloody dust, And grasped it with his hands, and gnashed his teeth. As when a lion coming on a herd Seizes, amid the crowd of stamping beeves, A tawny and high-mettled bull, that dies Bellowing in fury in the lion's jaws,— Like him, indignant to be overcome, The leader of the bucklered Lycian host, Laid prostrate by Patroclus, called by name *s His dear companion, and addressed him thus :— "Beloved Glaucus, mighty among men! Now prove thyself a hero, now be bold. Now, if thou have a warrior's spirit, think Of nought but battle. Go from rank to rank, «» Exhorting all the Lycian chiefs to fight Around Sarpedon. Combat thou for me With thy good spear, for I shall be to thee A shame and a reproach through all thy days, If here the Greeks, beside whose ships I fall, ,s Bear off my armor. Stand thou firm, and stir Thy people up to combat valiantly." Page 116 116 The Iliad. While he was speaking, death crept o'er his sight And stopped his breath. Patroclus set his heel Against his bosom, and plucked out the spear; i The midriff followed it, and thus he drew The life and weapon forth at once. Meantime The Myrmidons held fast the snorting steeds, That, loosened from the Lycian's car, were bent On flight. The grief of Glaucus as he heard «33 His comrade's voice was bitter, and his heart Ached at the thought that he could bring no aid. He seized his arm and pressed it in his grasp, For there the wound which Teucer's arrow left, When Glaucus stormed the wall and Teucer's shafts Defended it, still pained him grievously, And thus he prayed to Phoebus, archer-god : — "Give ear, O king! wherever thou abide, In the opulent realm of Lycia, or in Troy; For everywhere thou nearest those who cry ms To thee in sorrow, and great sorrow now Is on me. Grievous is the wound I bear; Sharp are the pains that pierce my hand ; the blood Cannot be stanched ; my very arm becomes A burden; I can wield the spear no more «*, With a firm grasp, nor combat with the foe. A mighty chief— Sarpedon, son of Jove — Has perished, and the father came not nigh To aid his son. Yet come thou to my aid, O monarch-god! and heal this painful wound, «ss And give me strength to rally to the fight Page 117 Book XVI. 117 The Lycian warriors, and myself contend Valiantly for the rescue of the dead." «s« So prayed he: Phoebus hearkened, and at once Assuaged the pain, and stanched the purple blood In the deep w ound, and filled his frame with strength. The warrior felt the change, rejoiced to know That with such friendly speed the mighty god Granted his prayer. And first he went among The Lycian chiefs, exhorting them to wage «s Fierce battle for Sarpedon. Then he sought, Walking with rapid strides, the Trojan chiefs, Agenor, nobly born, Polydamas, The son of Panthoiis, tineas next, And Hector mailed in brass. By him he stood, «n0 And thus accosted him with winged words : — "O Hector, thou art careless of the fate Of thine allies, who for thy sake, afar From those they love, and from their native land, Pour out their lives; thou bringest them no aid. Sarpedon lies in death, the chief who led The bucklered Lycians, who with justice swayed The realm of Lycia, and defended it With valor. Him hath brazen Mars beneath The weapon of Patroclus smitten down. «o Come then, my friends, repulse we gallantly These Myrmidons; else will they bear away His armor and insult his corpse, to avenge The havoc we have made among the Greeks Who perished by our weapons at the fleet." «s Page 118 I 1S The Iliad. He spake, and grief immitigable seized The Trojans; for the slain, though stranger-bom, Had been a pillar of the realm of Troy, And many were the troops that followed him, And he was bravest of them all in war. ««0 Then rushed the Trojans fiercely on the Greeks, With Hector, sorrowing for Sarpedon's fall, Leading them on, while the bold-hearted chief, Patroclus Menoetiades, aroused The courage of the Greeks. He thus addressed «9s The warriors Ajax, eager like himself For combat: "Be it now your welcome task, O warriors Ajax, to drive back the foe; He who first sprang across the Grecian wall, Sarpedon, lies a corpse, and we must now 700 Dishonor the dead chief, and strip from him His armor, and strike down with our good spears Whoever of his comrades shall resist." He spake, and all were resolute to beat The enemy back; and when, on either side, w Trojans and Lycians, Myrmidons and Greeks, Had put their phalanxes in firm array, They closed, with dreadful shouts and horrid clash Of arms, in fight around the dead, while Jove Drew o'er that deadly fray an awful veil t0 Of darkness, that the struggle for the corpse Of his dear son might rage more furiously. The Trojans first drave back the dark-eyed Greeks, For one was in the onset smitten down, Page 119 Book XVI. i Not the least valiant of the Myrmidons, — The son of brave Agacles, nobly born Epeigeus, who aforetime, when he ruled The populous Budeium, having slain A noble kinsman, fled a suppliant To Peleus and the silver-footed queen, Thetis, his consort, and by them was sent, With terrible Achilles, to the coast Of courser-breeding Ilium and the siege Of Troy. As now he stooped to seize the dead, Illustrious Hector smote him with a stone Upon the forehead, cleaving it in two In the strong helmet; headlong on the corse He fell, and cruel death crept over him. With grief Patroclus saw his comrade slain, And broke his way among the foremost ranks. As a swift hawk that chases through the air Starlings and daws, so didst thou dart among Trojans and Lycians, for thy wrath was roused, O knight Patroclus! by thy comrade's death. And now his hand struck Sthenelaus down, The dear son of Ithaemenes; he flung A stone that crushed the sinews of the neck Back drew illustrious Hector, and with him The warriors who were fighting in the van. As far as one can send a javelin, When men contend in martial games, or meet Their deadly enemies in war, so far Withdrew the Trojans, and the Greeks pursued. Page 120 120 The Iliad. The leader of the bucklered Lycian host, Glaucus, was first to turn against his foes. 74s He slew the brave Bathycles, the dear son Of Chalcon, who in Hellas had his home, And was the richest of the Myrmidons. The Lycian, turning on him suddenly As he drew near pursuing, sent his spear 730 Right through his breast, and with a clash he fell. Great was the sorrow of the Greeks to see That valiant warrior fall; the men of Troy Exulted, and pressed round him in a crowd. Nor lacking was the valor of the Greeks, Who met them manfully. Meriones Struck down a Trojan chief, Laogonus, Onetor's valiant son. His father stood Priest at the altar of Idaean Jove, And like a god was honored by the realm. Below the jaw and ear Meriones Smote him, and instantly the life forsook His limbs, and fearful darkness shrouded him. Straight at Meriones ^Eneas aimed His brazen spear to smite him, as he came, Beneath his buckler; but the Greek beheld The weapon in the air, and, stooping low, Escaped it ; over him it passed, and stood Fixed in the earth behind him, where its stem Trembled, for now the rapid steel had spent Its force. As thus it quivered in the ground, yEneas, who perceived that it had left Page 121 Book XVI. 121 His powerful hand in vain, was vexed, and said: "Had I but struck thee, dancer as thou art, Meriones, my spear had suddenly 7-s Ended thy dancing." Then Meriones, The skilful spearman, answered : "Thou art brave, But thou wilt find it hard to overcome The might of all who gather to repulse Thy onset. Thou art mortal, and if I, 7*, Aiming at thee with my good spear, should pierce Thy bosom, valiant as thou art and proud Of thy strong arm, thy death would bring me praise, And send thy soul where gloomy Pluto dwells." He spake ; the brave Patroclus heard, and thus Rebuked him : "Why wilt thou, Meriones, With all thy valor, stand to make a speech? The foe, my friend, will not be forced to leave The corpse by insults ; some of them must die. In deeds the issue of a battle lies; 790 Words are for counsel. Now is not the time To utter swelling phrases, but to fight." He ended, and went on ; the godlike man Followed his steps. As when from mountain dells Rises, and far is heard, a crashing sound 79s Where woodmen fell the trees, such was the noise From those who fought on that wide plain, — the din Of brass, of leather, and of tough bull's-hide Smitten with swords and two-edged spears. No eye, Although of keenest sight, would then have known Noble Sarpedon, covered as he lay, *» vol. 11. 6 Page 122 122 The Iliad. From head to foot, with weapons, blood, and dust; And still the warriors thronged around the dead. As when in spring-time at the cattle-stalls Flies gather, humming, when the milk is drawn, * Round the full pails, so swarmed around the corpse The combatants ; nor once did Jove withdraw His bright eyes from the stubborn fray, but still Gazed, planning how Patroclus should be slain. Uncertain whether, in the desperate strife a,» Over the great Sarpedon, to permit Illustrious Hector with his spear to lay The hero dead, and make his arms a spoil, Or spare him yet a while, to make the war More bloody. As he pondered, this seemed best: That the brave comrade of Achilles first s.« Should put to flight the Trojans and their chief, Hector the brazen-mailed, pursuing them Toward Troy with slaughter. To this end he sent Into the heart of Hector panic fear, **» Who climbed his car and fled, and bade the rest Flee also, for he saw how Jove had weighed The fortunes of the day. Now none remained, Not even the gallant Lycians, when they saw Their monarch lying wounded to the heart ,s Among a heap of slain ; for Saturn's son In that day's strife had caused a multitude To fall in death. Now when the Greeks had stripped Sarpedon of the glittering brazen mail, The brave son of Menoetius bade his friends Page 123 Book XVI. 123 Convey it to the hollow ships. Meanwhile The Cloud-compeller spake to Phoebus thus : — "Go now, beloved Phoebus, and withdraw Sarpedon from the weapons of the foe; Cleanse him from the dark blood, and bear him thence, 933 And lave him in the river-stream, and shed Ambrosia o'er him. Clothe him then in robes Of heaven, consigning him to Sleep and Death, Twin brothers, and swift bearers of the dead, And they shall lay him down in Lycia's fields, a40 That broad and opulent realm. There shall his friends And kinsmen give him burial, and shall rear His tomb and column, — honors due the dead." He spake : Apollo instantly obeyed His father, leaving Ida's mountain height, «4s And sought the field of battle, and bore otf Noble Sarpedon from the enemy's spears, And laved him in the river-stream, and shed Ambrosia o'er him. Then in robes of heaven He clothed him, giving him to Sleep and Death, ?s0 Twin brothers, and swift bearers of the dead, And they, with speed conveying it, laid down The corpse in Lycia's broad and opulent realm. Meantime Patroclus, urging on his steeds And charioteer, pursued, to his own hurt, »ss Trojans and Lycians. Madman! had he then Obeyed the counsel which Pelides gave, Page 124 124 The Iliad. The bitter doom of death had not been his. But stronger than the purposes of men Are those of Jove, who puts to flight the brave, ^ And takes from them the victory, though he Impelled them to the battle; and he now Urged on Patroclus to prolong the fight. Who first, when thus the gods decreed thy death, Fell by thy hand, Patroclus, and who last? w Adrastus first, Autonoiis next, and then Echeclus; then died Perimus, the son Of Meges; then with Melanippus fell Epistor; next was Elasus o'ercome, And Mulius, and Pylartes. These he slew, While all the rest betook themselves to flight. Then had the Greeks possessed themselves of Troy, With all its lofty portals, by the hand And valor of Patroclus, for his rage Was terrible beyond the rage of all s7s Who bore the spear, had not Apollo stood On a strong tower to menace him with ill, And aid the Trojans. Thrice Patroclus climbed A shoulder of the lofty wall, and thrice Apollo, striking his immortal hands '*, Against the glittering buckler, thrust him down; And when, for the fourth time, the godlike man Essayed to mount the wall, the archer-god, Phoebus, encountered him with fearful threats: "Noble Patroclus, hold thy hand, nor deem «ss The city of the warlike Trojans doomed Page 125 Book XVI. 1-5 To fall beneath thy spear, nor by the arm Of Peleus' son, though mightier far than thou." He spake; Patroclus, fearful of the wrath Of the archer-god, withdrew, and stood afar, a* While Hector, at the Sccean gates, restrained His coursers, doubtful whether to renew The fight by mingling with the crowd again, Or gather all his host within the walls By a loud summons. As he pondered thus, «w Apollo stood beside him in the form Of Asius, a young warrior and a brave, Uncle of Hector, the great horse-tamer, And brother of Queen Hecuba, and son Of Dymas, who in Phrygia dwelt beside 9» The streams of the Sangarius. Putting on His shape and aspect, thus Apollo said :— "Why, Hector, dost thou pause from battle thus? Nay, it becomes thee not. Were I in might Greater than thou, as I am less, full soon ,r*i Wouldst thou repent this shrinking from the war. Come boldly on, and urge thy firm-paced steeds Against Patroclus; slay him on the field, And Phoebus will requite thee with renown." He spake, and mingled in the hard-fought fray, 910 While noble Hector bade his charioteer, The brave Cebriones, ply well the lash, And join the battle. Phoebus went before, Entering the crowd, and spread dismay among The Greeks, and gave the glory of the hour 91s Page 126 126 The Iliad. To Hector and the Trojans. Little heed Paid Hector to the rest, nor raised his arm To slay them, but urged on his firm-paced steeds To meet Patroclus, who, beholding him, Leaped from his car. In his left hand he held 9» A spear, and with the other lifting up A white, rough stone, the largest he could grasp, Flung it with all its force. It flew not wide, Nor flew in vain, but smote Cebriones, The warlike chief who guided Hector's steeds, A spurious son of Priam the renowned. The sharp stone smote his forehead as he held The reins, and crushed both eyebrows in ; the bone Resisted not the blow; the warrior's eyes Fell in the dust before his very feet. 930 Down from the sumptuous seat he plunged, as dives A swimmer, and the life forsook his limbs. And this, Patroclus, was thy cruel jest:— "Truly a nimble man is this who dives With such expertness. Were this, now, the sea, 93s Where fish are bred, and he were searching it For oysters, he might get an ample store For many men, in leaping from a ship, Though in a storm, so skilfully he dives Even from the chariot to the plain. No doubt «« There must be divers in the town of Troy." He spake, and sprang upon Cebriones. With all a lion's fury, which attacks The stables and is wounded in the breast, Page 127 Book X17. 127 And perishes through his own daring; thus, mi Patroclus, didst thou fall upon the slain, While Hector, hastening also, left his steeds, And both contended for Cebriones. As lions for the carcass of a deer Fight on a mountain summit, hungry both, w, And both unyielding, thus two mighty men Of war, Patroclus Menuetiades And glorious Hector, eager each to smite His adversary with the cruel spear, Fought for Cebriones. The slain man's head 9ss Was seized by Hector's powerful hand, whose grasp Relaxed not, while Patroclus held the foot; And, thronging to the spot, the other Greeks And Trojans mingled in the desperate strife. As when the east wind and the south contend »*, In the open mountain grounds, and furiously Assail the deep old woods of beech and ash And barky cornel, flinging their long boughs Against each other with a mighty roar, And crash of those that break, so did the Greeks 9«s And Trojans meet with mutual blows, and slay Each other; nor had either host a thought Of shameful flight. Full many a trenchant spear Went to its mark beside Cebriones, And many a winged arrow that had left 970 The bowstring; many a massive stone was hurled Against the ringing bucklers, as they fought Around the dead, while he, the mighty, lay Page 128 128 The Iliad. Stretched on the ground amid the eddying dust, Forgetful of his art of horsemanship. 975 While yet the sun was climbing to his place In middle heaven, the men of either host Were smitten by the weapons, and in both The people fell; but when he stooped to the west The Greeks prevailed, and from that storm of darts And tumult of the Trojans they drew forth «ai Cebriones, and stripped him of his arms. Still rushed Patroclus onward, bent to wreak His fury on the Trojans. Fierce as Mars, He charged their squadrons thrice with fearful shouts, And thrice he laid nine warriors in the dust. 9m But as with godlike energy he made The fourth assault, then clearly was it seen, Patroclus, that thy life was near its end, For Phoebus terribly in that fierce strife 990 Encountered thee. Patroclus saw him not Advancing in the tumult, for he moved Unseen in darkness. Coming close behind, He smote, with open palm, the hero's back Between the ample shoulders, and his eyes ns Reeled with the blow, while Phoebus from his head Struck the tall helm, that, clanking, rolled away Under the horses' feet; its crest was soiled With blood and dust, though never till that hour Had dust defiled its horse-hair plume; for once 100. That helmet guarded an illustrious head, The glorious brows of Peleus' son, and now Page 129 Book XVI. 129 Jove destined it for Hector, to be worn In battle; and his death was also near. The spear Patroclus wielded, edged with brass, io»s Long, tough, and huge, was broken in his hands , And his broad buckler, dropping with its band, Lay on the ground, while Phoebus, son of Jove, Undid the fastenings of his mail. With mind Bewildered, and with powerless limbs, he stood »k, As thunderstruck. Then a Dardanian named Euphorbus, son of Panthous, who excelled His comrades in the wielding of the spear, The race, and horsemanship, approaching, smote Patroclus in the back with his keen spear, 10's Between the shoulder-blades. Already he Had dashed down twenty warriors from their cars, Guiding his own, a learner in the art Of war. The first was he who threw a lance At thee, Patroclus, yet o'ercnme thee not; ,0*, For, plucking from thy back its ashen stem, He fled, and mingled with the crowd, nor dared Await thy coming, though thou wert unarmed, While, weakened by that wound and by the blow Given by the god, Patroclus turned and sought Shelter from danger in the Grecian ranks; But Hector, when he saw the gallant Greek Thus wounded and retreating, left his place Among the squadrons, and, advancing, pierced Patroclus with his spear, below the belt, »» Driving the weapon deep. The hero fell 6» 1 Page 130 13° The Iliad. With clashing mail, and all the Greeks beheld His fall with grief. As when a lion bears A stubborn boar to earth, what time the twain Fight on the mountains for a slender spring, 103s Both thirsty and both fierce, the lion's strength Lays prone his panting foe, so Priam's son Slew, fighting hand to hand, the valiant Greek, Son of Menoetius, who himself had slain So many. Hector gloried over him »o*» With winged words : "Patroclus, thou didst think To lay our city waste, and carry off Our women captive in thy ships to Greece. Madman! in their defence the fiery steeds Of Hector sweep the battle-field, and I, i«j Mightiest of all the Trojans, with the spear Will guard them from the doom of slavery.* Now vultures shall devour thee, wretched youth! Achilles, mighty though he be, has brought No help to thee, though doubtless when he sent 10s0 Thee forth to battle, and remained within, He charged thee thus : ' Patroclus, flower of knights, Return not to the fleet until thy hand Hath torn the bloody armor from the corpse Of the man-queller Hector.' So he spake, 10ss And filled with idle hopes thy foolish heart." Then thou, Patroclus, with a faltering voice, Didst answer thus: " Now, Hector, while thou mayst, Utter thy boast in swelling words, since Jove And Phoebus gave the victory to thee. Page 131 Book XVI. 131 Easily have they vanquished me j 't was they Who stripped the armor from my limbs, for else, If twenty such as thou had met me, all Had perished by my spear. A cruel fate O'ertakes me, aided by Latona's son, 10«s The god, and by Euphorbus among men. Thou who shalt take my spoil art but the third; Yet hear my words, and keep them in thy thought. Not long shalt thou remain alive; thy death By violence is at hand, and thou must fall, '«70 Slain by the hand of great /Eacides." While he was speaking, death stole over him And veiled his senses, while the soul forsook His limbs and flew to Hades, sorrowing For its sad lot, to part from life in youth ,^s And prime of strength. Illustrious Hector thus Answered the dying man : " Why threaten me, Patroclus, with an early death? Who knows That he, thy friend, whom fair-haired Thetis bore, Achilles, may not sooner lose his life, «*, Slain by my spear?" He spake, and set his heel Upon the slain, and from the wound drew forth His brazen spear and pushed the corpse aside, And with the weapon hurried on to smite Godlike Automedon, the charioteer ««s Of swift ^Eacides; but him the steeds Fleet-footed and immortal, which the gods Bestowed on Peleus, swiftly bore away.

XIX

.

IN saffron-colored mantle from the tides Of Ocean rose the Morning to bring light To gods and men, when Thetis reached the fleet, Bringing the gift of Vulcan. There she found Her son, who, bending o'er Patroclus, wept J Aloud, and all around a troop of friends Lamented bitterly. Beside him stood The glorious goddess, took his hand, and said :— "Leave we the dead, my son, since it hath pleased The gods that he should fall; and now receive 10 This sumptuous armor, forged by Vulcan's hand, Beautiful, such as no man ever wore." The goddess spake, and laid the armor down Before Achilles; as they touched the earth, The well-wrought pieces clanked, and terror seized The Myrmidons. No one among them all Dared fix his gaze upon them; all shrank back. Achilles only, as he saw them, felt His spirit roused within him. In his eyes A terrible brightness flashed, as if of fire. 0• He lifted up the god's magnificent gift Rejoicing, and, when long his eyes had dwelt Delighted on the marvellous workmanship, Thus to his mother said, in winged words : — "A god indeed, my mother, must have given « Page 192 I g2 The Iliad. These arms, the work of heavenly hands: no man Could forge them. Now I arm myself for war. But for the valiant Menoetiades 1 greatly fear that flies will gather round The wounds inflicted by the spear, and worms Be bred within them, to pollute the corpse Now that the life is gone, and taint the whole." And silver-footed Thetis answered thus: "Son, have no care for that. The task be mine To drive away the importunate swarm that feed On heroes slain in battle. Though it lie The whole year long, the body shall remain Even more than uncorrupted. Call thou now To council all the Achaian chiefs; renounce Thy feud with Agamemnon, king of men, And arm for war, and put on all thy might." She spake, and called a fiery courage up Within the hero's breast. The goddess then Infused ambrosia and the ruddy juice Of nectar through the nostrils of the dead Into the frame, to keep it from decay. Along the beach the great Achilles went, Calling with mighty shouts the Grecian chiefs. Then even they who till that day remained Beside the fleet, — the pilots and the men Who held the helm, the stewards of the ships, And the purveyors, — all made haste to swell The assembly, for they knew that he who long Had borne no part in the disastrous war Page 193 Book XIX. 193 Had now come forth. Two ministers of Mars, ss The brave Tydides and the nobly born Ulysses, both supported by their spears, Came halting, for their wounds were painful yet; They came and sat among the foremost chiefs. And last came Agamemnon, king of men, «0 Wounded, for he had felt in thick of fight The edge of the sharp spear which Coon bore, Antenor's son. Now when the Greeks were all Assembled, swift Achilles rose and said : — "Atrides, of a truth it would have been «s Better for both of us had we done this At first, though sorely angered, when we strove For a girl's sake so fiercely. Would that she Had perished in my ships, by Dian's shaft, The day on which I laid Lyrnessus waste! 70 So many Greeks would then have not been forced, Slain by the enemy's hand, to bite the dust Of the great earth, while I was brooding o'er My wrath. All that was for the good of Troy And Hector; but the Greeks, I think, will long 7s Remember our contention. Let us leave These things among the things that were, and, though They make us grieve, let us subdue our minds To what the time requires. Here then my wrath Shall end; it is not meet that it should burn »0 Forever.' Hasten thou and rouse to war The long-haired Greeks, that I may yet again vol. 11. 9 M Page 194 194 The Iliad. Go forth among the men of Troy, and learn If they design to encamp another night Before the fleet. There is among them all No man, I ween, who will not joyfully Sit down when he escapes my deadly spear." He ended, and the Achaians all rejoiced To hear the brave Pelides thus renounce His anger. Agamemnon, king of men, Then rose. He came not forth into the midst, But stood beside his seat, and thus he spake :— "O friends, Achaian heroes, ministers Of Mars! Whoever rises up to speak 'T is well to hear him through, and not break in Upon his speech, else is the most expert Confounded. Who amid a clamorous throng Can listen or can speak? The orator Of clearest voice must utter it in vain. Now I address Pelides; for the rest, Hearken ye all, and ponder what I say. The Greeks speak often of this feud, and cast The blame on me. Yet was I not the cause, But Jupiter and Fate, and she who walks In darkness, dread Erynnis. It was they Who filled my mind with fury in the hour When from Achilles I bore off his prize. What could I do? A deity prevails In all things. Ate, mighty to destroy, Daughter of Jove, and held in awe by all. Delicate are her feet; she never comes Page 195 Book XIX. Near to the ground, but glides above the heads Of men, to do them harm, and in her net Entangles one at least of two who strive. Jove, deemed the mightiest among men and gods, "s Once felt her power of mischief. Him his spouse, Juno, entrapped by cunning, when within The massive walls of Thebes Alcmena lay In childbed, and the mighty Hercules Was near his birth. For Jupiter had said ,~ Boastfully to the immortals: 'Hear, ye gods And goddesses, what I am moved to speak: This day shall Ilithyia, who presides At births, bring into light a prince whose rule The neighboring tribes shall own; he shall be one Who bears the blood of my illustrious race.' i* "Imperial Juno thus, with words of guile, Made answer: 'What thou sayest will prove false, Nor wilt thou keep thy word. Now swear to me, Olympius, with the irrevocable oath, ,», That whosoever of thy race shall fall This day between a woman's feet shall bear The rule o'er all the neighboring tribes.' She spake, And Jove, perceiving not her craft, complied, And took the mighty oath, but afterward ,a Found himself wronged. For Juno, darting forth, Shot from the Olympian summit, and at once Alighted at Achaian Argos. There She found the noble wife of Sthenelus, The son of Perseus, pregnant with a son, ,4• Page 196 196 The Iliad. In the seventh month. She caused him to be born, The number of his months yet incomplete, And kept Alcmena's hour of childbirth back, And stayed her pangs. The goddess then made haste To bear the tidings to Saturnian Jove. us O Father Jupiter, by whom are hurled The ruddy lightnings, I have news for thee. A man-child of a generous stock is born, — Eurystheus, whom the Argives shall obey,— Born at this hour to Sthenelus, the son ,*, Of Perseus, who is thine. And well it is That such a prince should rule the Argive race. "She ended: Jupiter was deeply grieved, And, seizing Ate by her shining locks, In his great wrath, he swore a mighty oath, — iss That Aie, whose delight it is to bring Mischief to all, should never tread again Olympus and the starry floor of heaven. Thus having sworn, he swung her, with raised arm, On high, and hurled her from the starry heaven ,*, Downward, where soon she reached the haunts of men; Yet oft in after time because of her He sighed, beholding his beloved son Doomed by Eurystheus to unworthy tasks. So I, while crested Hector in his might i«s Made havoc at our fleet among the Greeks Even by their prows, remembered well my fault. Page 197 Book XIX. And now since I have borne the penalty, And Jupiter it was who took away My reason, I would gladly make amends »70 With liberal gifts. But rise and join the war; Inflame the courage of the rest; the gifts Will I supply, —all that were promised thee When nobly born Ulysses yesterday Went to thy tents. Or, if it please thee, wait, m Though armed for battle, and my train shall bring The treasures from my ship, that thou mayst see My presents are peace-offerings indeed." The swift of foot, Achilles, answered thus: "Most glorious son of Atreus, king of men! Whether, O Agamemnon, thou wilt give Gifts, as is meet, or keep them, rests with thee. Now let us think of war; it is not well To waste the hour in talking, and put off The mighty work that we have yet to do. i«s Let every Greek among you, as he sees Achilles fighting in the foremost ranks, And slaughtering the Trojan phalanxes, Take heart and boldly combat with his man." And then Ulysses, wise in council, spake, ,*, Answering Achilles: "Nay, thou shouldst not thus, Brave as thou art, lead on the sons of Greece, Yet fasting, to the conflict with the men Of Troy beside their city. No brief space The struggle will endure when once the foes m Rush on each other, and a god inspires Page 198 198 The Iliad. Both hosts with fury. Bid the Achaians take In their swift galleys food and wine; in these Are force and vigor. No man can endure To combat all the day till set of suri, »» Save with the aid of food, however great The promptings of his valor; for his limbs Grow heavy, thirst and hunger weaken him, And his knees fail him as he walks. Not so The warrior well supplied with food and wine: *», He fights the foe all day; a resolute heart Is in his bosom; nor does weariness O'ertake him till all others leave the field. Now let the people be dismissed awhile, And a repast be ordered. Let the king, »io Atrides, bring huo the assembly here His gifts, that all the Greeks may look on them, And thou rejoice to see them. Let him rise Among the Greeks, and take a solemn oath That he has ne'er approached the maiden's bed »s To claim a husband's right. Thus let thy heart Be satisfied. Yet let the monarch spread A sumptuous banquet in his tent for thee, That thy redress may be complete. And thou, Atrides, wilt hereafter be more just «» To others. It dishonors not a king To make amends to one whom he has wronged." And then King Agamemnon spake in turn: "Son of Laertes, gladly have I heard What thou hast said, and well hast thou discoursed Page 199 Book XIX. 199 Of all things in their order. I will take . ** The oath of which thou speakest, — so my heart Commands me. In the presence of a god I take it, and commit no perjury. Now let Achilles, though he longs for war, n» Delay awhile; and all assembled here, Remain ye on the ground till from my ship The gifts are brought. This charge and this com- mand I give to thee, Ulysses. Take with thee A band of youths, the noblest of the host, *yi And bring the presents promised yesterday To Peleus' son, and hither let them lead The women. Meantime let Talthybius haste To bring from our broad camp a boar, which I Will offer up to Jove and to the Sun." »-» The swift of foot, Achilles, thus replied: "Most glorious son of Atreus, king of men, These things are for the time when there shall come A pause from battle, and this warlike heat Within my breast shall cool. They whom the spear Of Hector, son of Priam, has o'ercome «4« Lie mangled on the earth, since Jupiter Awarded him the glory of the day : — And ye propose a banquet. I would call The sons of Greece to rush into the war «s» Unfed and fasting, and when this disgrace Shall be avenged, I would, at sunset, spread A liberal feast. Be sure that I, till then, Page 200 200 The Iliad. Taste neither food nor drink, while my slain friend Lies gashed with weapons in my tent, amidst »ss His sorrowing comrades. Little I regard The things of which thou speakest, for my thoughts Are all of bloodshed and of dying groans." Ulysses, the sagacious, thus rejoined: "Achilles, son of Peleus, bravest far *» Of all the Achaians, mightier with the spear By no small odds than I, yet do I stand In prudence much above thee; I have lived More years, and more have learned. Let then thy mind Accept what I shall say. Men soon become *s Weary of warfare, even when the sword Lays its most ample harvest on the earth. But fewer sheaves are reaped when Jupiter, The arbiter of battles, turns the scale. It is not well that we of Greece should mourn The dead with fasting, since from day to day Our warriors fall in numbers. Where were then Respite from daily fasts? Lay we our slain In earth and moutn a day. We who outlive The cruel combat should refresh ourselves *n With food and wine, that we may steadily Maintain in arms the conflict with the foe. And then let no man idly wait to hear A further call to war, — for it will come Freighted with evil to the man who skulks »*, Among the ships, — but let us all go forth Page 201 Book XIX. 201 To wage fierce battle with the knights of Troy." He spake, and summoned to his side the sons Of glorious Nestor, and Meriones, And Meges, son of Phyleus, and with them •*-, Thoas, and Lycomedes, Creon's son, And Melanippus. Straight they took their way To Agamemnon's tent, and there their task Was done as quickly as the word was given. *» They brought seven tripods forth, the promised gifts, And twenty burnished caldrons, and twelve steeds, And led away seven graceful women trained In household arts, — the maid with rosy cheeks, Briseis, was the eighth. Ulysses came, Leading the way, and bearing, duly weighed, «w Ten talents, all of gold. The Achaian youths Followed, and placed the presents in the midst Of that assembly. Agamemnon r,ose; And then Talthybius, who was like a god In power of voice, came near and took his place *» Beside the monarch, holding in his hands A boar. The son of Atreus drew a knife, Which hung by the great scabbard of his sword, And, cutting off the forelock of the boar, Prayed with uplifted hands to Jupiter: m Meantime the Greeks in silence kept their seats, And, as became them, listened to the king, Who looked into the sky above, and said : — "Now first bear witness, Jove, of all the gods Greatest and best, and also Earth and Sun, v 9* Page 202 202 The Iliad. And Furies dwelling under Earth, who take Vengeance on men forsworn, that never I Have laid, for purpose of unchaste desire, Or other cause, my hand upon the maid Briseis. She hath dwelt inviolate sis Within my tents. If yet in aught I say Lurk perjury, then may the blessed gods Heap on my head the many miseries With which they punish those who falsely swear!" He spake, and drew the unrelenting blade 3*, Across the animal's throat. Talthybius took And swung the carcass round, and cast it forth Into the gray sea's depths, to be the food Of fishes. Then again Achilles rose Among the warlike sons of Greece, and said :— m "Great sorrows thou dost send, O Father Jove! Upon mankind; for never would the son Of Atreus have provoked the wrath that burned Within my bosom, never would have thought To bear away the maiden from my tent 330 In spite of me, had it not been the will Of Jupiter that many a Greek should die. But banquet now, and then prepare for war." So spake Achilles, and at once dissolved The assembly, each repairing to his ship m Save the large-hearted Myrmidons, who still Were busy with the gifts, and carried them Toward their great general's galley. These they laid Carefully in the tents, and seated there Page 203 Book XIX. . 203 The women, while the attentive followers drave w, The coursers to the stables. When the maid Briseis, beautiful as Venus, saw Patroclus lying gashed with wounds, she sprang And threw herself upon the dead, and tore Her bosom, her fair cheeks and delicate neck; 34s And thus the graceful maiden, weeping, said :— "Patroclus, dear to my unhappy heart! I left thee in full life, when from this tent They led me; I return and find thee dead, 0 chieftain of the people! Thus it is b0 That sorrow upon sorrow is my lot. Him to whose arms my father, in my youth, And gracious mother gave me as a bride, 1 saw before our city pierced and slain, And the three brothers whom my mother bore sss Slain also, — brothers whom I dearly loved. Yet thou, when swift Achilles struck to earth My hapless husband, and laid waste the town Of godlike Mynes, wouldst not suffer me To weep despairingly; for thou didst give *» Thy word to make me yet the wedded wife Of great Achilles, bear me in the fleet To Phthia, and prepare the wedding feast Among the Myrmidons. O ever kind! I mourn thy death, and cannot be consoled." #s Weeping she spake; the women wept with her Seemingly for the dead, but each, in truth, For her own griefs. Meanwhile the elders came Page 204 204 The Iliad. Around Achilles, praying him to join The banquet, but the chief, with sighs, refused. 370 "Dear comrades, if ye love me, do not thus Press me to sit and feast. A mighty woe Weighs down my spirit; it is my resolve To wait and bear until the setting sun." So saying, he dismissed the other kings. vs The sons of Atreus, and the high-born chief Ulysses, Nestor, and Idomeneus, And Phoenix, aged knight, alone remained, And anxiously they sought to comfort him In his great grief; but comfort would he none 3«0 Ere entering the red jaws of war. He drew Deep sighs, and, thinking on Patroclus, spake: "The time has been when thon too, hapless or.e, Dearest of all my comrades, wouldst have spread With diligent speed before me in my tent 13s A genial banquet, while the Greeks prepared For desperate battle with the knights of Troy. Thou liest now a mangled corse, and I, Through grief for thee, refrain from food and drink, Though they are near. No worse calamity 3x, Could light on me, not even should I hear News of my father's death, who haply now Tenderly mourns with tears his absent son In Phthia, while upon a foreign coast I wage for hated Helen's sake the war yn Against the Trojans; or were I to hear Tidings that my beloved son had died, Page 205 Book XIX. 205 The noble Neoptolemus, who now, If living, is in Scyros, growing up To manhood. Once the hope was in my heart *», That I alone should perish here at Troy, Far from the Argive pastures full of steeds, And thou return to Phthia and bring home My son from Scyros in thy ship, and show The youth my wealth, my servants, and my halls, «s High-roofed and spacious. For my mind misgives That Peleus either lives not, or endures A painful age, and hardly lives, yet waits To hear the sorrowful news that I am slain." So spake he weeping, and the elders sighed 4•» To see his tears, as each recalled to mind Those whom he left at home, while Saturn's son Beheld their grief with pity, and bespake His daughter Pallas thus with winge;! words :— "My child, wilt thou desert that valiant man? 41s And shall Achilles be no mote thy care? Lo, by his ships, before their lofty prows, He sits, lamenting his beloved friend. The rest are at the banquet; he remains Apart from them, and fasting. Hasten thou; 4» With nectar and ambrosial sweets refresh His frame, that hunger overtake him not." As thus he spake he sent the goddess forth Eager to do her errand. Plunging down, In form a shrill-voiced harpy with broad wings, 4»s She cleft the air. The Greeks throughout the camp Page 206 2o6 The Iliad. Were putting on their armor. She infused Into the hero's frame ambrosial sweets And nectar, that his limbs might not grow faint With hunger. Then the goddess sought again «, The stable mansion of Almighty Jove, While all the Greeks came pouring from the fleet. As when the flakes of snow fall thick from heaven, Driven by the north wind sweeping on the clouds Before it, so from out the galleys came m Helms crowding upon helms that glittered fair, Strong hauberks, bossy shields, and ashen spears. The gleam of armor brightened heaven and earth, And mighty was the sound of trampling feet. Amidst them all the great Achilles stood, «o Putting his armor on; he gnashed his teeth; His eyes shot fire; a grief too sharp to bear Was in his heart, as, filled with rage against The men of Troy, he cased his limbs in mail, The gift of Vulcan, from whose diligent hand «s It came. And first about his legs he clasped The beautiful greaves, with silver fastenings, Fitted the corselet to his bosom next, And from his shoulders hung the brazen sword With silver studs, and then he took the shield, 430 Massive and broad, whose brightness streamed as far . As the moon's rays. And as at sea the light Of beacon, blazing in some lonely spot By night, upon a mountain summit, shines Page 207 Book XIX. 207 To mariners whom the tempest's force has driven 4ss Far from their friends across the fishy deep, So from that glorious buckler of the son Of Peleus, nobly wrought, a radiance streamed Into the sky. And then he raised and placed Upon his head the impenetrable helm 4*. With horse-hair plume. It glittered like a star, And all the shining tufts of golden thread, With which the maker's hand had thickly set Its cone, were shaken. Next the high-born chief Tried his new arms, to know if they were well *s Adjusted to his shape, and left his limbs Free play. They seemed like wings, and lifted up The shepherd of the people. Then he drew From its ancestral sheath his father's spear, Heavy and huge and tough. No man of all «0 The Grecian host could wield that weapon save Achilles only. T was a Pelian ash, Which Chiron for his father had cut down On Pelion's highest peak, to be the death Of heroes. Meantime, busy with the steeds, 47s Automedon and Alcimus put on Their trappings and their yoke, and round their necks Bound the fair collars, thrust into their mouths The bit, and backward drew the reins to meet The well-wrought chariot. Then Automedon Took in his hand the showy lash, and leaped Into the seat. Behind him, all equipped Page 208 208 The Iliad. For war, Achilles mounted, in a blaze Of arms that dazzled like the sun, and thus Called to his father's steeds with terrible voice : — "Xanthusand Balius, whom l'odarge bore,— 4» A noble stock, — I charge you to bring back Into the Grecian camp, the battle done, Him whom ye now are bearing to the field, Nor leave him, as ye left Patroclus, dead." «0 Swift-footed Xanthus from beneath the yoke Answered him with bowed head and drooping mane That, flowing through the yoke-ring swept the ground, — For Juno gave him then the power of speech :— "For this one day, at least, we bear thee safe, «s O fiery chief, Achilles! but the hour Of death draws nigh to thee, nor will the blame Be ours; a mighty god and cruel fate Ordain it. Not through our neglect or sloth Did they of Troy strip off thy glorious arms *» From slain Patroclus. That invincible god, The son of golden-haired Latona, smote The hero m the foremost ranks, and gave Glory to Hector. Even though our speed Were that of Zephyr, fleetest of the winds, s0s Yet certain is thy doom to be o ercome In battle by a god and by a man." Thus far he spake, and then the Furies checked His further speech. Achilles, swift of foot, Replied in anger: "Xanthus, why foretell s» Page 209 Book XX. 209 My death? It is not needed; well I know My fate, — that here I perish, far away From Peleus and my mother. I shall fight Till I have made the Trojans sick of war." He spake, and, shouting to his firm-paced steeds, Drave them, among the foremost, toward the war.

XX

.

THUS, O Pelides, did the sons of Greece, Impatient for the battle, arm themselves, By their beaked ships, around thee. Opposite, Upon a height that rose amidst the plain, The Trojans waited. Meantime Jupiter s Sent Themis from the Olympian summit, ploughed With dells, to summon all the immortal ones To council. Forth she went from place to place, Bidding them to the palace halls of Jove. Then none of all the Rivers failed to join •,• The assembly, save Oceanus, and none Of all the Nymphs were absent whose abode Is in the pleasant groves and river-founts And grassy meadows. When they reached the halls Of cloud-compelling Jove they sat them down .s On shining thrones, divided each from each By polished columns, wrought for Father Jove By Vulcan's skill. Thus all to Jove's abode N Page 210 2IO The Iliad. Were gathered. Neptune had not disobeyed The call. He left the sea, and took his seat « Among them, and inquired the will of Jove. "Why, wielder of the lightning, dost thou call The gods again to council? Do thy plans Concern the Greeks and Trojans? For the war Between their hosts will be rekindled soon." »s And thus the Cloud-compeller Jove replied: "Thou who dost shake the shores, thou knowest well The purpose of my mind, and for whose sake I call this council. Though so soon to die, They are my care. Yet will I keep my place, *, Seated upon the Olympian mount, and look Calmly upon the conflict. All of you Depart, and aid the Trojans or the Greeks, As it may list you. For should Peleus' son Alone do battle with the men of Troy, 33 Their squadrons could not stand before the assault Of the swift-footed warrior for an hour. Beforetime, at the sight of him they fled, O'ercome with fear, and now, when he is roused To rage by his companion's death, I fear » Lest, though it be against the will of fate, He level with the ground the walls of Troy." Saturnius spake, and moved the hosts to join In desperate conflict. All the gods went forth To mingle with the war on different sides. « Juno and Pallas hastened to the fleet Page 211 Book XX. 211 With Neptune, he who makes the earth to shake, And Hermes, god of useful arts, and shrewd In forecast. Vulcan also went with them, Strong and stern-eyed, yet lame, his feeble legs s» Moviug with labor. To the Trojan side Went crested Mars, Apollo with his locks Unshorn, Diana mighty with the bow, Latona, Xanthus, and the Queen of smiles, Venus; for while the gods remained apart 5s From men, the Achaian host was high in hope Because Achilles, who so long had left The war, now reappeared upon the field, And terror shook the limbs of every son Of Troy when he beheld the swift of foot, «° Pelides, terrible as Mars — that curse Of human-kind — in glittering arms again. But when the dwellers of Olympus joined The crowd of mortals, Discord, who makes mad The nations, rose and raged; Minerva raised «s Her war-cry from the trench without the wall, And then she shouted from the sounding shore; While, like a cloudy whirlwind, opposite, Moved Mars, and fiercely yelled, encouraging The men of Troy, as on the city heights 70 He stood, or paced with rapid steps the hill Beside the Simo s, called the Beautiful. Thus, kindling hate between the hosts, the gods Engaged, and hideous was the strife that rose Among them. From above, with terrible crash, n Page 212 The Iliad. Thundered the father of the blessed gods And mortal men, while Neptune from below Shook the great earth and lofty mountain peaks. Then watery Ida's heights and very roots, The city of Troy, and the Greek galleys, quaked. «- Then Pluto, ruler of the nether world, Leaped from his throne in terror, lest the god Who makes the earth to tremble, cleaving it Above him, should lay bare to gods and men His horrible abodes, the dismal haunts «s Which even the gods abhor. Such tumult filled The field of battle when the immortals joined The conflict. Then against King Neptune stood Phoebus Apollo, with his winged shafts, And Pallas, goddess of the azure eyes, 90 Confronted Mars. Encountering Juno came The sister of Apollo, archer-queen And huntress, Dian of the golden bow. The helpful Hermes, god of useful arts, Opposed Latona, and the mighty stream ss Called Xanthus by the immortals, but by men Scamander, with his eddies strong and deep, Stood face to face with Vulcan in the field. So warred the gods with gods. Meantime the son Of Peleus, ranging through the thick of fight, "0 Sought only Hector, Priam's son, whose blood He meant to pour to greedy Mars, the god Of carnage. But Apollo, who impels Warriors to battle, stirred /Eneas up Page 213 Book XX. 213 To meet Pelides. First he filled his heart 10s With resolute valor, and then took the voice Of Priam's son, Lycaon. In his shape Thus spake Apollo, son of Jupiter: — "/Eneas, prince of Troy, where now are all The boasts which thou hast made before the chiefs Of Troy at banquets, that thou yet wouldst meet Pelides in the combat hand to hand?" /Eneas made reply: "Priamides, Why dost thou bid me, when thou knowest me Unwilling, meet in combat Peleus' son, us The mighty among men? It will not be For the first time if I confront him now. He chased me once from Ida with his spear, — Me and my fellows, when he took our herds And laid Lyrnessus waste and Pedasus. ,*, But Jove, who gave me strength and nimble feet, Preserved me; I had else been slain by him And by Minerva, for the goddess went Before him, giving him the victory And moving him to slay the Leleges »s And Trojans with the brazen spear he bore. 'T is not for mortal man to fight the son Of Peleus, at whose side there ever stands One of the immortal gods, averting harm. And then his weapon flies right on, nor stops ,*, Until it bites the flesh. Yet were the god To weigh the victory in an equal scale, Achilles would not vanquish me with ease, Page 214 214 The Iliad. Though he might boast his frame were all of brass." Then spake the king Apollo, son of Jove: 13s "Pray, warrior, to the eternal gods. They say That Venus gave thee birth, who has her own From Jove. His mother is of lower rank Than thine. Thine is a child of Jove, but his A daughter of the Ancient of the Deep. ,» Strike at him with that conquering spear of thine, Nor let him scare thee with stern words and threats." He said, and breathed into the prince's breast Fresh valor, as, arrayed in glittering arms, He pressed to where the foremost warriors fought; Yet not unseen by Juno's eye went forth u« The son of old Anchises. She convened The gods in council, and addressed them thus : — "Neptune and Pallas, what shall now be done? Consider ye. ^Eneas, all arrayed is» In glittering arms, is pressing on to meet Pelides. Phoebus sends him. Let us join To turn him back, or let some one of us Stand near Achilles, fill his limbs with strength, Nor let his heart grow faint, but let him see >« That we, the mightiest of the immortals, look On him with favor, and that those who strive Amid the war and bloodshed to protect The sons of Troy are empty boasters all. For this we came from heaven to interpose i, In battle, that Achilles may endure No harm from Trojan hands, although, no doubt, Page 215 Book XX. 215 Hereafter he must suffer all that Fate Spun for him when his mother brought him forth. But if he hear not, from some heavenly voice, 1«s Of this assurance, fear may fall on him When, haply, in the battle he shall meet Some god; for when revealed to human sight The presence of the gods is terrible." And then did Neptune, he who shakes the earth, Make answer: "Juno, it becomes thee ill ,71 To be so greatly vexed. I cannot wish A contest with the other gods, though we In power excel them. Rather let us sit Apart, where we can look upon the war, 171 And leave it to mankind. And yet if Mars Or Phoebus should begin the fight, or seek To thwart Achilles or restrain his arm, There will be cause for us to join the strife In earnest, and I deem that they full soon, ,, The contest ended, will return to join The assembled gods upon the Olympian mount, Forced to withdraw by our all-potent hands." So spake the dark-haired god, and led the way To the high mound of godlike Hercules, i«s Raised from the earth by Trojans, with the aid Of Pallas, that the hero there might find A refuge when the monster of the deep Should chase him from the sea-beach to the plain. With other gods beside him Neptune there ,*, Sat down and drew a shadow, which no sight Page 216 2l6 The Iliad. Could pierce, around their shoulders. Other gods, Upon the hill called Beautiful, were grouped Round thee, Apollo, archer-god, and Mars, Spoiler of cities. On both sides they sat, us Devising plans, unwilling to begin The fierce encounter, though Almighty Jove From where he sat in heaven commanded it. The warriors thronged into the field, which shone With brazen armor and caparisons - »90 Of steeds; earth trembled with the sounding tramp Of marching squadrons. From the opposing ranks Two chieftains, each the bravest of his host, Impatient to engage, — Anchises' son, ^Eneas, and the great Achilles, — came. »,s And first ^Eneas, with defiant mien And nodding casque, stood forth. He held his shield Before him, which he wielded right and left, And shook his brazen spear. On the other side, Pelides hurried toward him, terrible »,» As is a lion, which the assembled hinds Of a whole village chase and seek to slay, While on he stalks, contemning their assault; But if the arrow of some strong-armed youth Have smitten him, he stands, and gathers all «s His strength to spring, with open jaws and leeth Half hid in foam, and uttering fearful growls From his deep chest; he lashes with his tail His sides and sinewy thighs to rouse himself To combat, and then, grimly frowning, leaps «0 Page 217 Book XX. 217 To slay, or by the foremost youths be slain, So sprang Achilles, moved by his bold heart To meet the brave /Eneas. As the twain Drew near each other, the swift-footed chief, The great Achilles, was the first to speak : — »s "Why, O /Eneas, hast thou come so far Through this vast crowd to seek me? Does thy heart Bid thee confront me in the hope to gain The place which Priam holds, and to bear rule Over the knights Oi Troy? Yet shouldst thou take My life, think not that Priam in thy hand asi Will place such large reward. He has his sons, Nor is he fickle, but of stable mind. Or will the Trojans, if thou slayest me, Bestow on thee broad acres, of a soil m Fruitful exceedingly, and suited well To vines or to the plough, which thou mayst till That also, as I hope, thou wilt obtain With difficulty; for, unless I err, I forced thee once to flee before my spear. «*, Dost thou remember, when thou wert alone Among thy beeves, I drave thee, running fast, Down Ida's steeps? Then didst thou never turn To face me, but didst seek a hiding-place Within Lyrnessus, which I also took «s And wasted, with the aid of Father Jove And Pallas. From the town I led away The women, never to be free again. vol. 11. 10 Page 218 218 The Iliad. Jove and the other gods protected thee That day. Yet will they not protect thee now, «s» As thou dost vainly hope. Withstand me not, I counsel thee, but hide thyself among The crowd before thou suffer harm, for he Who sees past evils only is a fool." And then /Eneas answered: "Do not think, »ss Pelides, with such words to frighten me, As if I were a beardless boy. I too Might use reproach and taunt; but well we know Each other's birth and lineage, through report Of men, although by sight I know not thine, Nor know'st thou mine. They say that thou art sprung From Peleus the renowned, and from the nymph Of ocean, fair-haired Thetis, while I boast My birth from brave Anchises, and can claim Venus as mother. Two of these to-day *s Must weep the death of a beloved son, For we are not to part, I think, nor end The combat after a few childish words; Yet let me speak, that thou mayst better know Our lineage, known already far and wide. »70 Jove was the father, cloud-compelling Jove, Of Dardanus, by whom Dardania first Was peopled, ere our sacred Troy was built On the great plain, — a populous town ; for men Dwelt still upon the roots of Ida fresh *n With many springs. To Dardanus was born Page 219 Book XX. 219 King Erichthonius, richest in his day Of mortal men, and in his meadows grazed Three thousand mares, exulting in their brood Of tender foals. Of some of this vast herd »*, Boreas became enamored as they fed. He came to them in likeness of a steed That wore an azure mane, and they brought forth Twelve foals, which all were females, of such speed That when they frolicked on the teeming earth *>s They flew along the topmost ears of wheat And broke them not, and when they sported o'er The mighty bosom of the deep they ran Along the hoary summits of its waves. To Erichthonius Tros was born, who ruled *» The Trojans, and from Tros there sprang three sons Of high renown, — llus, Assaracus, And godlike Ganymede, most beautiful Of men; the gods beheld and caught him up To heaven, so beautiful was he, to pour *>s The wine to Jove, and ever dwell with them. And llus had a son, Laomedon, Of mighty fame, to whom five sons were born, Tithonus, Priam, Lampus, Clytius, And Hicetaon, trained to war by Mars. y* Assaracus begat my ancestor, Capys, to whom Anchises owes his birth. Anchises is my father; Priam's son Is noble Hector. Such I claim to be My lineage and my blood; but Jove at will « Page 220 220 The Iliad. Gives in large measure, or diminishes, Men's warlike piowess; and the power of Jove Is over all. But let us talk no more Of things like these, as if we were but boys, While here in the mid-field we stand between The warring armies. Both of us might cast Reproaches at each other, many and foul, Such as no galley of a hundred oars Could bear and float. Men's tongues are voluble, And endless are the modes of speech, and far 313 Extends from side to side the field of words. Such as thou utterest it will be thy lot To hear from others. But what profits it For us to rail and wrangle, in high brawl, Like women angered to the quick, that rush s» Into the middle of the street and scold With furious words, some true and others false, As rage may prompt them? Me thou shalt not move With words from my firm purpose ere thou raise Thy arm against me. Let us hasten first *s To prove the temper of our brazen spears." He spake, and hurled his brazen spear to smite The dreadful shield, a terror in men's eyes; That mighty buckler rang with the strong blow. Achilles, as it came, held forth his shield 3* With nervous arm far from him, for he feared That the long javelin of his valiant foe Might pierce it. Idle fear; he had not thought That the bright armor given him by the gods Page 221 Book XX. 221 Not easily would yield to force of man. 33s Nor could the rapid spear that left the hand Of brave ^Eneas pierce the shield; the gold, The gift of Vulcan, stopped it. Through two folds It went, but three remained; for Vulcan's skill Fenced with five folds the disk, — the outer two w Of brass, the inner two of tin; between Was one of gold, and there the brazen spear Was stayed. And then in turn Achilles threw His ponderous spear, and struck the orbed shield Borne by ^Eneas near the upper edge, wa Where thinnest was the brass and thinnest lay The bullock's hide. The Pelian ash broke through; The buckler crashed; ^ineas, stooping low, Held it above him, terrified; the spear, Tearing both plate and hide of that huge shield, 3s0 Passed over him, and, eager to go on, Plunged in the earth and stood. He, when he saw The massive lance which he had just escaped Fixed in the earth so near him, stood awhile As struck with fear, and with despairing looks. 3ss Achilles drew his trenchant sword and rushed With fury on ^Eneas, uttering A fearful shout. ^Eneas lifted up A stone, a mighty weight, which no two men, As men are now, could raise, yet easily He wielded it. ./Eneas then, to save His threatened life, had smitten with the stone His adversary's buckler or his helm, Page 222 222 The Iliad. And with his sword Pelides had laid dead The Trojan, had not he who shakes the earth, jss Neptune, beheld him in that perilous hour, And instantly addressed the immortal gods : — "My hear', ye gods, is heavy for the sake Of the great-sauled ./Eneas, who will sink To Hades overcome by Peleus' son. a70 Rash man! he listened to the archer-god Apollo, who has now no power to save The chief from death. But, guiltless as he is, Why should he suffer evil for the wrong Of others? He has always sought to please m With welcome offerings the gods who dwell In the broad heaven. Let us withdraw him, then, From this great peril, lest, if he should fall Before Achilles, haply Saturn's son May be displeased. And't is the will of fate **, That he escape; that so the Dardan race, Beloved by Jove above all others sprung From him and mortal women, may not yet Perish from earth and leave no progeny. For Saturn's son already holds the house s«s Of Priam in disfavor, and will make ^Eneas ruler o'er the men of Troy, And his sons' sons shall rule them after him." Imperial Juno with large eyes replied: "Determine, Neptune, for thyself, and save »» ^Eneas, or, all blameless as he is, Abandon him to perish by the hand Page 223 Book XX. 223 Of Peleus' son, Achilles. We have sworn — Minerva and myself—that never we Would aid in aught the Trojans to escape m Their day of ruin, though the town of Troy Sink to the dust in the destroying flames,— Flames kindled by the warlike sons of Greece." And then did Neptune, shaker of the shores, Go forth into the battle and amidst *» The clash of spears, and come where stood the chiefs, ^Eneas and his mighty foe, the son Of Peleus. Instantly he caused to rise A darkness round the eyes of Peleus' son, And from the buckler of ^Eneas drew 40s The spear with ashen stem and brazen blade, And laid it at Achilles' feet, and next He lifted high /Eneas from the ground And bore him thence. O'er many a warrior's head, And many a harnessed steed, -Eneas flew, «io Hurled by the god, until he reached the rear Of that fierce battle, where the Caucons stood Arrayed for war. The shaker of the shores Drew near, and said to him in winged words :— "What god, ^Eneas, moved thee to defy « Madly the son of Peleus, who in might Excels thee, and is dearer to the gods? Whenever he encounters thee in arms Give way, lest thou, against the wiil of fate, Pass down to Hades. When he shall have met m Page 224 224 The Iliad. His fate and perished, thou mayst boldly dare To face the foremost of the enemy; No other of the Greeks shall take thy life. He spake, and having thus admonished him He left /Eneas there, and suddenly *,s Swept off the darkness that so thickly rose Around Achilles, who, with sight now clear, Looked forth, and, sighing, said to his great soul:— "How strange is this! My eyes have seen to-day A mighty marvel. Here the spear I flung 4*, Is lying on the earth, and him at whom I cast it, in the hope to take his life, • I see no longer. Well beloved, no doubt, Is this /Eneas by the immortal gods. Yet that, I thought, was but an empty boast «s Of his. Well, let him go; I cannot think That he who gladly fled from death will find The courage to encounter me again. And now will I exhort the Greeks to fight This battle bravely, while I go to prove «• The prowess of the other chiefs of Troy." He spake, and, cheering on the soldiery, He sprang into the ranks: "Ye noble Greeks, Avoid no more the Trojans; press right on. "Let each man single out his man, and fight «s With eager heart. T is hard for me to chase, With all my warlike might, so many men, And fight with all. Not even Mars, the god, Although immortal, nor Minerva's self, Page 225 Book XX. Could combat with so vast a multitude 4s» Unwearied; yet whatever I can do, With hands and feet and strength, I give my word Not to decline, or be remiss in aught. 1 go to range the Trojan files, where none, I think, will gladly stand to meet my spear." 4ss Such stirring words he uttered, while aloud Illustrious Hector called, encouraging The men of Troy, and promising to meet Achilles: "Valiant Trojans, do not quail Before Pelides. In the strife of words *s0 I too might bear my part against the gods; But harder were the combat with the spear, For greater is their might than ours. The son Of Peleus cannot make his threatenings good. A part will he perform and part will leave *ss Undone. I go to wait him; I would go Although his hands were like consuming flame, — His hands like flame, his strength the strength of steel." He spake: the Trojans at his stirring word Lifted their lances, and the adverse hosts 470 Joined battle with a fearful din. Then came Apollo and admonished Hector thus :— "Hector, encounter not Achilles here Before the armies, but amidst the throng And tumult of the battle, lest perchance 47s He strike thee with the javelin or the sword." He spake: the Trojan chief, dismayed to hear io• o Page 226 226 The Iliad. The wirning of the god, withdrew among The crowded ranks. Meantime Achilles sprang Upon the Trojans with a terrible cry, And slew a leader of the host, the brave Iphition, whom a Naiad, at the foot Of snowy Tmolus, in the opulent vale Of Hyda, bore to the great conqueror Of towns, Otrynteus. As he came in haste, os The noble son of Pcleus with his spear Smote him upon the forehead in the midst, And cleft the head in two. He fell; his arms Clashed, and Achilles boasted o'er him thus :—- "Son of Otrynteus, terrible in arms, r» Thou art brought low; thou meetest here thy death, Though thou wert born by the Gyga^an lake Where lie, by fishy Hyllus and the stream Of eddying Hermus, thy paternal fields." Thus boastfully he spake, while darkness came *n Over Iphition's eyes, and underneath The chariots of the Greeks who foremost fought His corse was mangled. Next Achilles smote Antenor's son, Demoleon, gallantly Breasting the onset of the Greeks. He pierced s« His temple through the helmet's brazen cheek; The brass stayed not the blow; the eager spear Brake through the bone, and crushed the brain within, And the brave youth lay dead. Achilles next Struck down Hippodamas; he pierced his back m Page 227 Book XX. 227 As, leaping from his car, the Phrygian fled Before him. With a moan he breathed away His life, as moans a bull when dragged around The altar of the Heliconian king By youths on whom the god that shakes the earth s,« Looks down well pleased. With such a moaning sound The fiery spirit left the Phrygian's frame. Then sprang Achilles with his spear to slay The godlike Polydorus, Priam's son, Whose father bade him not to join the war, ss For he was younger than the other sons, And dearest of them all. In speed of foot He had no peer. Yet, with a boyish pride To show his swiftness, in the foremost ranks He ranged the field, until he lost his life. s*, Him with a javelin the swift-footed son Of Peleus smote as he was hurrying by. The weapon pierced the middle of his back, Where, by its golden rings, the belt was clasped Above the double corselet; the keen blade s»s Came forth in front; the Trojan with a cry Fell forward on his knees, and, bending, clasped His bowels in his hands. When Hector saw His brother thus upon the earth, there came A darkness o'er his eyes, nor could he bear s» Longer to stand aloof, but, brandishing His spear, came forward like a rushing flame To meet the son of Peleus, who beheld Page 228 228 The Iliad. And bounded toward him, saying boastfully: "So, he is near whose hand hath given my heart s*, Its deepest wound, who slew my dearest friend. No more are we to shun each other now, Timidly stealing through the paths of war." And then he said to Hector with a frown: "Draw nearer, that thou mayst the sooner die." s» The crested Hertor, undismayed, replied: "Pelides, do not hope with empty words To frighten me, as if I were a boy. Insults and taunts J could with ease return. I know that thou art brave; I know that I «s In might am not thy equal ; but the event Rests in the laps of'.he great gods, and they May, though I lack thv prowess, give thy life Into my hands when I shall cast my spear. The weapon that I bear ;s keen like thine." ss» Thus having spoken, blandishing his spear, He sent it forth; but with a gentle breath Minerva turned it from thr glorious Greek, And laid it at the noble Hec'or's feet . Then did Achilles, resolute to slay sss His enemy, rush against him with a shout Of fury; but Apollo, with such nower As gods put forth, withdrew him thence, and spread A darkness round him. Thrice thf swift of foot, Achilles, rushed against him with his spear, And thrice he smote the cloud. Bui when once more, Page 229 Book XX. 229 In godlike might, he made the assault, he spake These winged words of menace and reproach : — "Hound as thou art, thou hast once more escaped Thy death; for it was near. Again the hand sss Of Phoebus rescues thee; to him thy vows Are made ere thou dost trust thyself amidst The clash of javelins. I shall meet thee yet And end thee utterly, if any god Favor me also. I will now pursue «?• And strike the other Trojan warriors down." He spake, and in the middle of the neck Smote Dryops with his spear. The Phrygian fell Before him at his feet. He left him there, And wounding with his spear Philetor's son, ys Demuchus, tall and valiant, in the knee, Stayed him until he slew him with his sword. Then from their chariot to the ground he cast Laogonus and Dardanus, the sons Of Bias, piercing with a javelin one, sso And cutting down the other with his sword. And Tros, Alastor's son, who came to him And clasped his knees, in hope that he would spare A captive, —spare his life, nor slay a-youth Of his own age, — vain hope! he little knew a That not by prayers Achilles could be moved, Nor was he pitiful, nor mild of mood. But hard of heart, — while Tros embraced his knees And passionately sued, Pelides thrust His sword into his side; the liver came ss» Page 230 230 The Iliad. Forth at the wound; the dark blood gushing filled The Phrygian's bosom; o'er his eyes there crept A darkness, and his life was at an end. Approaching Mulius next, Achilles smote The warrior at the ear; the brazen point ss Passed through the other ear; and then he slew Agenor's son, Echeclus, letting fall His heavy-hiked sword upon his head Just in the midst; the blade grew warm with blood, And gloomy death and unrelenting fate » Darkened the victim's eyes. Achilles next Wounded Deucalion, thrusting through his arm The brazen javelin, where the sinews met That strung the elbow. While with powerless arm The wounded Trojan stood awaiting death, ,*,s Achilles drave his falchion through his neck. Far flew the head and helm, the marrow flowed From out the spine, and stretched upon the ground Deucalion lay. Pelides still went on, O'ertaking Rigmus, the renowned son ««o Of Peireus, from the fruitful fields of Thrace, And smote him in the stomach with his lance. There hung the weapon fixed; the wounded man Fell from the car. At Areithous The charioteer, who turned his steeds to flee, a,s Achilles sent his murderous lance, and pierced His back, and dashed him from the car, and left His horses wild with fright. As when, among The deep dells of an arid mountain-side, Page 231 Book XXI. 231 A great fire burns its way, and the thick wood » Before it is consumed, and shifting winds Hither and thither sweep the flames, so ranged Achilles in his fury through the field From side to side, and everywhere o'ertook His victims, and the earth ran dark with blood. t*s As when a yeoman underneath the yoke Brings his broad-fronted oxen to tread out White barley on the level threshing-floor, The sheaves are quickly trodden small beneath The heavy footsteps of the bellowing beasts, So did the firm-paced coursers, which the son Of F"leus guided, trample with their feet Bucklers and corpses, while beneath the car Blood steeped the axle, and the chariot-seat Dripped on its rim with blood, that from below «» Was splashed upon them by the horses' hoofs And by the chariot-wheels. Such havoc made Pelides in his ardor for renown, Till his invincible hands were foul with blood.

XXI

.

OW when they reached the pleasant banks The eddying Xanthus runs, the river sprung From deathless Jove, Achilles drave his foes through which Page 232 232 The Iliad. Asunder. Part he chased across the plain Town ward, along the way by which the Greek; In terror fled the day before, pursued By glorious Hector. Panic-struck they ran Along that way, while, to restrain their flight, Before them Juno hung a veil of cloud And darkness. Meanwhile half the flying crowd •0 Leaped down to that deep stream and rolle! among Its silver eddies. With a mighty noise They plunged; the torrent dashed; the banks around Remurmured shrilly to the cries of those Who floated struggling in the current's whirl, ,s As when before the fierce, devouring flames A swarm of locusts, springing into air, Fly toward a river, while the fire behind Crackles with sudden fierceness, and in fright They fall into the waves, the roaring stream «, Of the deep-eddied Xanthus thus was filled Before Achilles with a mingled crowd Of steeds and men. The Jove-descended man Left leaning on the tamarisks his spear Upon the river's border, and leaped in, as Armed only with his sword, intent to deal Death on the fugitives; on every side He smote, and from the smitten by the sword Rose lamentable cries; the waves around Grew crimson with their blood. As when before », A dolphin of huge bulk the fishes flee Page 233 Book XXL 233 In fear, and crowd the creeks that lie around The sheltered haven, — for their foe devours All that he overtakes, — the Trojans thus Hid from his sight among the hollow rocks 3s Beside the rushing river. When his hand Was weary with the work of death, he took Twelve youths alive, whose blood was yet to pay The penalty for Menoetiades, His slaughtered friend. He led them from the stream, *, Passive with fear like fawns, and tied their hands Behind them with the well-twined cords that bound Their tunics. Then he gave them to his friends, Who led the captives to the roomy ships. Again Achilles rushed upon the foe 4s Intent on slaughter. One he met who climbed The river's bank, Dardanian Priam's son, Lycaon, whom in former days he made His captive, by surprise, when in the night He found him lopping with an axe the boughs s0 Of a wild fig-tree, that the trunk might form The circle of a wheel. Achilles came, An unexpected foe, and bore him off To sea, and sold him in the populous isle Of Lemnos. He was bought by Jason's son, ss The Imbrian prince, Eetion, who had been His host, and now redeemed him with large gifts, And sent him to Arisba's noble town. Yet thence he stole, and reached his father's house Page 234 234 The Iliad. Again, and there made merry with his friends a» Eleven days, but on the twelfth a god Delivered him again into the hands Of Peleus' son, who now would send his soul Repining down to Hades. When the chief, The swift of foot, beheld him stand unarmed, «s With neither helm nor shield nor spear, — for these He had thrown down, — faint with the sweaty toil Of clambering up the bank, and every limb Unstrung with weariness, then wrathfully Thus said Achilles to his mighty soul :— -« « O strange! my eyes behold a miracle. Sure, the brave sons of Troy whom I have slain Will rise up from the nether darkness yet, Since this man, whom I once reprieved from death And sold in Lemnos the divine, comes back. n Nor could the ocean's gray abyss of brine, Beyond which many long in vain to pass, Detajn him in that isle. But he shall taste The sharpness of my spear, that I may prove Whether he after that will reappear, », And whether the kind earth, which holds so well The valiant dead, can keep him in her womb." So pondered he and stood. The Trojan drew Close to him, with intent to clasp his knees, Fear-struck, yet hoping to avoid the doom »s Of bitler death. The great Achilles raised His ponderous spear to strike. Lycaon stooped, And, darting underneath the weapon, seized Page 235 Book XXI. 235 The hero's knees; behind him in the ground The spear stood fixed, though eager yet for blood ; ,* One arm was round his adversary's knees, The other held — and would not let it go — The spear, while thus with winged words he prayed : — "I clasp thy knees, Achilles; look on me Kindly and pity me, O foster-child 0s Of Jove. I am thy suppliant, and may claim Thy mercy. I partook with thee the fruits Of Ceres, when amid my fruitful fields Thou madest me a captive, carrying me From friends and kindred to the sacred isle «■ Of Lemnos. Thou didst sell me there, — my price A hundred beeves, — and thou shalt now receive, For ransom, thrice as many. It is yet But the twelfth morning since I came to Troy After much hardship, and a pitiless fate k,s Betrays me to thy hands. I must believe That Father Jove in wrath delivers me To thee again. Laothoe brought me forth To a brief life; that mother was the child Of aged Altes, — Altes ruling o'er no The warlike Leleges, by whom are tilled The heights of Pedasus, where Satnio flows, — And Priam wedded her with other maids. She bore two children to be slain by thee; One was the godlike Polydore, whom thou ns Didst smite with thy keen spear, in the front rank Page 236 236 The Iliad. Of those who fought on foot. His evil fate Must overtake me now, for, since a god Has brought me near thee, there is no escape. Yet let me tell thee this, and weigh it well, And let it save my life. I came not forth From the same womb with Hector, by whose hand Thy brave and gentle friend, Patroclus, died." The illustrious son of Priam endsd here His prayer, and heard a merciless reply:— i,s "Fool! never talk of ransom, — not a word. Before the evil day on which my friend Was slain, it pleased me oftentimes to spare The Trojans. Many a one I took alive And sold; but now no man of air their race, w Whom any god may bring within my reach, Shall leave the field alive, and least of all The sons of Priam. Die thou, then; and why Shouldst thou, my friend, lament? Patroclus died, And greatly he excelled thee. Seest thou not 13s How eminent in stature and in form Am I, whom to a prince renowned for worth A goddess mother bore; yet will there come To me a violent death at morn, at eve, Or at the midday hour, whenever he ,« Whose weapon is to take my life shall cast The spear or send an arrow from the string." He spake: the Trojan's heart and knees grew faint; His hand let go the spear; he sat and cowered Page 237 Book XXI. 237 With outstretched arms. Achilles-drew his sword, And smote his neck just at the collar-bone; 1# The two-edged blade was buried deep. He fell Prone on the earth; the black blood spouted forth And steeped the soil. Achilles by the foot Flung him to float among the river-waves, ,s0 And uttered, boastfully, these winged words: — "Lie there among the fishes, who shall feed Upon thy blood unscared. No mother there Shall weep thee lying on thy bier; thy corpse Scamander shall bear down to the broad sea, 1ss Where, as he sees thee darkening its face, Some fish shall hasten, darting through the waves, To feed upon Lycaon's fair white limbs. So perish ye, till sacred Troy be ours, You fleeing, while I follow close and slay. ,, This river cannot aid you, — this fair stream With silver eddies, to whose deity Ye offer many beeves in sacrifice, And fling into its gulfs your firm-paced steeds; But thus ye all shall perish, till I take «ss Full vengeance for Patroclus of the Greeks, Whom, while I stood aloof from war, ye slew." He spake: and, deeply moved with inward wrath, The River pondered how to render vain The prowess of Achilles, and avert •70 Destruction from the Trojans. Now the son Of Peleus rushed, his ponderous spear in hand, To slay Asteropasus, who was sprung Page 238 238 The Iliad. From Pelegon, and Pelegon was bom To the broad river Axius, of a maid, i7s The eldest-born of Acessamenus, Named Perilxra; for the river-god Was joined with her in love. Achilles sprang To meet the youth, as, rising from the stream, Armed with two spears, he stood, his heart made strong ,, And resolute by Xanthus, who had seen Indignantly so many Trojans die, — Youths whom Achilles slaughtered in his stream, And had no pity on them. When the twain Were near each other, standing face to face, *g The swift Achilles was the first to speak : — "Who and whence art thou that dost venture thus To meet me? They who seek to measure strength With me are sons of most unhappy men." And thus the illustrious son of Pelegon Made answer: "Brave Pelides, why inquire My lineage? I am from a distant coast, — Paeonia's fertile fields; I lead to war Paeonia's warriors with long spears, and this Is now the eleventh morning since I came us To join the war at Troy. I claim descent From Axius, the broad Axius, who pours forth The fairest river on the earth. His son Was Pelegon, expert to wield the spear, And I was born to Pelegon. And now, «» Illustrious son of Peleus, let us fight." Page 239 Book XXI. 239 He spake: Achilles raised the Pelian ash To smite; Asteropaeus aimed at him Both lances, for he used both hands alike. One struck the Grecian's shield, yet passed not through, Stopped by the god-given gold; the other gashed Lightly the elbow of his dexter arm; The black blood spouted forth, the spear passed on Beyond him, and, still eager for its prey, Stood fixed in earth. Achilles then, intent »10 To slay Asteropaeus, hurled at him His trusty spear. The weapon missed its mark, And, striking the high bank, was buried there Up to the middle of its ashen staff. Achilles drew the keen sword from his thigh, «$ And flew with fury toward his foe, who toiled In vain with sinewy arm to pluck that spear From out the bank; and thrice he shook the beam Fiercely, and thrice desisted, lacking strength, And last he sought, by bending it, to break The ashen weapon of tiacides. But ere it snapped Achilles took his life, Smiting him at the navel with the sword. Forth gushed the entrails to the ground, and o'er His dying eyes the darkness came; and then »s Achilles, leaping on his breast, tore off The armor, and exultingly exclaimed :— "Lie there! a perilous task it was for thee To combat with a son of Jove, though born Page 240 240 The Iliad. Thyself to a great River. I can boast »*» Descent from sovereign Jove. I owe mv birth To Peleus, ruler of the Myrmidons. His father was /Eacus, who was born To Jupiter, a god more potent far Than all the rivers flowing to the sea. «3s And mightier is the race of Jupiter Than that of any stream. Here close at hand Is a great river, if such aid can aught Avail thee; but to strive with Jupiter Is not permitted. Acheloiis, king «•*, Of rivers, cannot vie with him, nor yet The great and mighty deep from which proceed All streams and seas and founts and watery depths. He trembles at the bolt of mighty Jove . And his hoarse thunder crashing in the sky." us As thus he spake he plucked from out the bank His brazen spear, and left the lifeless chief Stretched in the sand, where the dark water steeped His limbs, and eels and fishes came and gnawed The warrior's reins. Achilles hastened on, »s» Pursuing the Pseonian knights, who now, When they beheld their bravest overthrown In desperate battle by the mighty arm And falchion of Pelides, took to flight Along the eddying river. There he slew »ss Mydon, Thersilochus, Astypylus, Mnesus, and Thrasius, and struck down in death ^inius and Ophelestes. Many more Page 241 Book XXL Of the Pseonians the swift-footed Greek Had slain, had not the eddying River, roused To anger, put a human semblance on, And uttered from its whirling deeps a voice :—- "O son of Peleus! thou who dost excel All other men in might and dreadful deeds,— For the gods aid thee ever, — if the son Of Saturn gives thee to destroy the race Of Trojans, drive them from me to the plain, And there perform thy terrible exploits. For now my pleasant waters, in their flow, Are choked with heaps of dead, and I no more Can pour them into the great deep, so thick The corpses clog my bed, while thou dost slay And sparest not. Now then, withhold thy hand, Prince of the people! I am horror-struck." Achilles the swift-footed made reply: "Be it as thou commandest, foster-child Of Jove, Scamander! Yet I shall not cease To slay these treaty-breakers till at length I shut them up within their town, and force Hector to meet me, that we may decide Which shall o'ercome the other, — he or I." He spake, and rushed upon the men of Troy, Terrible as a god, while from his bed The eddying River called to Phoebus thus : — "Why this, thou bearer of the silver bow, Thcu son of Jove? Thou heedest not the will Of Saturn's son, who strictly bade that thou VOL. 11. II p Page 242 242 The Iliad. Shouldst aid the Trojans till the latest gleam Of sunset, and till night is on the fields." And then Achilles, mighty with the spear, *>, From the steep bank leaped into the mid-stream, While, foul with ooze, the angry River raised His waves, and pushed along the heaps of dead Slain by Achilles. These, with mighty roar As of a bellowing ox, Scamander cast »ss Aground; the living with his whirling gulfs He hid, and saved them in his friendly streams. In tumult terribly the surges rose Around Achilles, beating on his shield, And made his feet to stagger, till he grasped »» A tall, fair-growing elm upon the bank. Down came the tree, and in its loosened roots Brought the earth with it; the fair stream was checked By the thick branches, and the prostrate trunk Bridged it from side to side. Achilles sprang *,s From the deep pool, and fled with rapid feet Across the plain in terror. Nor did then The mighty river-god refrain, but rose Against him with a darker crest, to drive The noble son of Peleus from the field, 310 And so deliver Troy. Pelides sprang A spear's cast backward, — sprang with all the speed Of the black eagle's wing, the hunter-bird, Fleetest and strongest of the fowls of air. Like him he darted; clashing round his breast, s» Page 243 Book XXI. 243 The brazen mail rang fearfully. Askance He fled; the water with a mighty roar Followed him close. As, when a husbandman Leads forth, from some dark spring of earth, a rill Among his planted garden-beds, and clears 3™ Its channel, spade in hand, the pebbles there Move with the current, which runs murmuring down The sloping surface and outstrips its guide, — So rushed the waves where'er Achilles ran, Swift as he was; for mightier are the gods 3»s Than men. As often as the noble son Of Peleus made a stand in hope to know Whether the deathless gods of the great heaven Conspired to make him flee, so often came A mighty billow of the Jove-born stream 330 And drenched his shoulders. Then again he sprang Away; the rapid torrent made his knees To tremble, while it swept, where'er he trod, The earth from underneath his feet. He looked To the broad heaven above him, and complained :— "Will not some god, O Father Jove, put forth 33« His power to save me in my hour of need From this fierce river? Any fate but this I am resigned to suffer. None of all The immortal ones is more in fault than she vn To whom I owe my birth; her treacherous words Deluded me to think that I should fall Beneath the walls of Troy by the swift shafts Of Phoebus. Would that Hector, the most brave Page 244 244 The Iliad. Of warriors reared upon the Trojan soil, Had slain me; he had slain a brave man then, And a brave man had stripped me of my arms. But now it is my fate to perish, caught In this great river, like a swineherd's boy, Who in the time of rains attempts to pass w A torrent, and is overwhelmed and drowned." He spake, and Neptune and Minerva came Quickly and stood beside him. In the form Of men they came, and took his hand, and cheered His spirit with their words. And thus the god ?ss Neptune, who makes the earth to tremble, said :— "Fear not, Pelides, neither let thy heart Be troubled, since thou hast among the gods, By Jove's consent, auxiliars such as I And Pallas. It is not thy doom to be jso Thus vanquished by a river. Soon its rage 'Will cease, as thou shalt see. Meantime we give This counsel; heed it well: let not thy hand Refrain from slaughter till the Trojan host Are all shut up — all that escape thy arm — *s Within the lofty walls of Troy. Then take The life of Hector, and return on board Thy galleys; we will make that glory thine." Thus having spoken, they withdrew and joined The immortals, while Achilles hastened on, 570 Encouraged by the mandate of the gods, Across the plain. The plain was overflowed With water; sumptuous arms were floating round, Page 245 Book XXI. 245 And bodies of slain youths. Achilles leaped, And stemmed with powerful limbs the stream, and Still 37s Went forward; for Minerva mightily Had strengthened him. Nor did Scamander fail To put forth all his power, enraged the more Against the son of Peleus; higher still His torrent swelled and tossed with all its waves, s*, And thus he called to Simois with a shout:— "O brother, join with me to hold in check This man, who threatens soon to overthrow King Priam's noble city; for no more The Trojan host resist him. Come at once ss And aid me; fill thy channel from its springs, And summon all thy brooks, and lift on high A mighty wave, and roll along thy bed, Mingled in one great torrent, trees and stones, That we may tame this savage man, who now 390 In triumph walks the field, and bears himself As if he were a god. His strength, I deem, Will not avail him, nor his noble form, Nor those resplendent arms, which yet shall lie Scattered along the bottom of my gulfs, 39s And foul with ooze. Himself too I shall wrap In sand, and pile the rubbish of my bed In heaps around him. Never shall the Greeks Know where to gather up his bones, o'erspread By me with river-slime, for there shall be ♦» His burial-place; no other tomb the Greeks Page 246 246 The Iliad. Will need when they perform his funeral rites." He spake, and wrathfully he rose against Achilles, — rose with turbid waves, and noise, And foam, and blood and bodies of the dead. *,s One purple billow of the Jove-born stream Swelled high and whelmed Achilles. Juno saw, And trembled lest the hero should be whirled Downward by the great river, and in haste She called to Vulcan, her beloved son :— »'-, "Vulcan, my son, arise! We deemed that thou And eddying Xanthus were of equal might In battle. Come with instant aid, and bring Thy vast array of flames, while from the deep I call a tempest of the winds, — the West »s And the swift South, — and they shall sweep along A fiery torrent to consume the foe, Warriors and weapons. Thou meantime lay waste The groves along the Xanthus; hurl at him Thy fires, nor let him with soft words or threats *«. Avert thy fury. Pause not from the work Of ruin till I shout and give the sign, And then shalt thou restrain thy restless fires." She spake, and Vulcan at her word sent forth His fierce, devouring flames. Upon the plain »;3 They first were kindled, and consumed the dead That strewed it, where Achilles struck them down. The ground was dried; the glimmering flood was stayed. As when the autumnal north-wind, breathing oVr Page 247 Book XXL 247 A newly watered garden, quickly dries «o The clammy mould, and makes the tiller glad, So did the spacious plain grow dry on which The dead were turned to ashes. Then the god Seized on the river with his glittering fires. The elms, the willows, and the tamarisks «« Fell, scorched to cinders, and the lotus-herbs, Rushes, and reeds that richly fringed the banks Of that fair-flowing current were consumed. The eels and fishes, that were wont to glide Hither and thither through the pleasant depths 4*, And eddies, languished in the fiery breath Of Vulcan, mighty artisan. The strength Of the great River withered, and he spake :— "O Vulcan, there is none of all the gods Who may contend with thee. I combat not 4« With fires like thine. Cease then. With my consent The noble son of Peleus may drive out The Trojans from their city. What have I To do with war, — the attack or the defence?" Thus in that fiery glow he spake, while seethed 4?, His pleasant streams. As over a strong fire A caldron filled with fat of pampered swine Glows bubbling on all sides, while underneath Burns the dry fuel, thus were his fair streams Scorched by the heat, and simmered, while the blast Sent forth by Vulcan, the great artisan, 4s4 Tormented him, and he besought the aid Of Juno with these supplicating words : — Page 248 248 The Iliad. "Why should thy son, O Juno, wreak on me His fury, more than on the other gods? «so My fault is less than theirs who give their aid To Troy; and I will cease, if thou command. Bid him desist, and here I pledge my oath Not to attempt to save the Trojan race From ruin, though their city sink in flames *s Before the torches of the warlike Greeks." This when the white-armed goddess Juno heard, She said to Vulcan, her beloved son :— "Dear son, refrain; it is not well that thus A god should suffer for the sake of men." 470 She spake, and Vulcan quenched his dreadful fires, And back the pleasant waters to their bed Went gliding. Xanthus had been made to yield, And the two combatants no longer strove Since Juno, though offended, bade them cease, m Yet was the conflict terrible among The other gods, as zeal for different sides Impelled them. With a loud uproar they met Each other in the field; the spacious earth Rebellowed to the noise, and the great heaven 4so - Returned it. To the ear of Jove it rose, Who, sitting on Olympus, laughed within His secret heart as he beheld the gods Contendmg, for not long they stood apart. Shield-breaking Mars began the assault; he rushed Toward Pallas, brandishing his brazen spear, 4» Page 249 Book XXI. 249 And thus accosted her with insolent words :— "Thou shameless one, thou whose effrontery Is boundless, why wilt thou provoke the gods To strife? Thy temper is most arrogant. «0 Rememberest thou the time when thou didst prompt Tydides Diomed to strike at me? It was thy hand that held his shining spear, And aimed it well, and gave the wound; but now Will I take vengeance on thee for that wrong." 4» He spake, and smote Minerva's fringed shield, The dreadful segis, which not even Jove Could pierce with thunderbolts. The murderous Mars Smote it with his huge spear. She only stepped Backward a space, and with her powerful hand s» Lifted a stone that lay upon the plain, Black, huge, and jagged, which the men of old Had placed there for a landmark. This she hurled At Mars, and struck him on the neck; he fell With nerveless limbs, and covered, as he lay, m Seven acres of the field: his armor clashed Around him in his fall; his locks all soiled Lay in the trodden dust . The goddess stood O'er him, and boasted thus with winged words : — "Fool that thou art, hast thou not learned how much s10 The might I boast excels thine own, that thus Thou measurest strength with me? Now dost thou feel Page 250 The Iliad. Thy mother's curse fulfilled, who meditates Thy chastisement, since thou hast left the Greeks And joined the treaty-breaking sons of Troy." s»s She spake, and turned away her glorious eyes. Jove's daughter, Venus, took the hand of Mars, And led him groaning thence, while hardly yet His strength came back. The white-armed Juno saw, And spake to Pallas thus, with winged words : -— s» "See, daughter of the /Egis-bearer, Jove, Unconquerable maid! that shameless one, Through all the tumult, from the thick of fight, Leads hence the murderous Mars; but follow her." She spake, and Pallas gladly hastened forth, And, overtaking Venus, dealt at her A mighty buffet on the breast; her heart Fainted, her knees gave way; and, as she lay Prostrate with Mars upon the fruitful earth, Exulting Pallas spake these winged words :— s30 "Would that all those who aid the cause of Troy And combat with the mailed Greeks were thus! Would that they were as hardy and as brave As Venus here, who ventured to the help Of Mars, and met the force of my right arm! s« Then had the stately Ilium been o'erthrown Long since, and we had rested from the war." She spake: the white-armed Juno gently smiled. And then King Neptune to Apollo said :— "Why, Phoebus, stand we thus aloof? it ill s4, Page 251 Book XXI. Becomes us, while the other gods engage In conflict. T were a shame should we return Up to Olympus and the brazen halls Of Jove with no blow struck. Begin, for thou Art younger born, and I, who both in years m And knowledge am before thee, must not make The assault. O silly god, and slow of thought 1 Hast thou indeed forgotten all the wrongs We suffered once in Troy, and only we Of all the gods, when, sent to earth by Jove, «0 We served a twelvemonth for a certain hire The proud Laomedon, by whom our tasks Were set? I built a city and a wall Of broad extent, and beautiful, and strong To stand assault; and, Phoebus, thou didst feed sss His stamping oxen, with curved horns, among The lawns of woody Ida seamed with glens. But when the welcome hours had brought the day Of our reward, the ruffian king refused The promised wages, and dismissed us both With menaces; to bind thee hand and foot He threatened, and to sell thee as a slave In distant isles, and to cut off the ears Of both of us. So we returned to heaven, Incensed at him who thus withheld the hire 9i He promised. Dost thou favor Troy for this? Wilt thou not rather act with us until These treaty-breakers, with their children all And their chaste matrons, perish utterly?" Page 252 252 The Iliad- Then thus the archer-king, Aoollo, spake: s7. "Thou wouldst not deem me wise, should I contend With thee, O Neptune, for the ;ike of men, Who flourish like the forest-leaves awhile, And feed upon the fruits of earth- and then Decay and perish. Let us quit the field, r» And leave the combat to the warring hosts." He spake, and turned, afraid to meet in arms His uncle; but the sylvan Dian he?.id,— His sister, mistress of the beasts that range The wilds, —and harshly thus upbraided him :— s*, "O mighty Archer, dost thou flee an-1 yield The victory to Neptune, who bears off A glory cheaply earned? Why dost thcu bear That idle bow, thou coxcomb? I shall hope No more to hear thee in our father's halls. 3»s And in the presence of the immortals, \xy\-\ That thou wilt fight with Neptune hand to kv.d." The archer-god, Apollo, answered not; But thus the imperial wife of Jupiter, Indignantly and with reproachful words, »0 Rebuked the quivered goddess of the chase "How is it that thou darest, shameless one, Resist me? Thou wilt find it hard, though tr.-,ned In archery, to match thy strength with mine, Though Jove has made thee among womankind •* A lioness, and though he gives thee power To slay whomever of thy sex thou wilt; Yet wilt thou find it easier to strike down Page 253 Book XXL 253 The mountain beasts of prey, and forest deer, Than combat with thy betters. If thou choose *«> To try the event of battle, then put forth Thy strength against me, and thou shalt be taught How greatly I excel in might of arm." Thus Juno spake, and grasped in her left hand Both Dian's wrists, and, plucking with her right **, The quiver from her shoulders, beat with it Her ears, and smiled as under her quick blows The sufferer writhed. To earth the arrows fell, And Dian weeping fled. As when a dove, Not fated to be overtaken yet, Flees from a hawk to find her hiding-place, The hollow rock, so Dian fled in tears, And left her arrows. To Latona, then, Heaven's messenger, the Argus-queller, spake: — "Far be it from me to contend with thee, «is Latona; perilous it were to meet A consort of the Cloud-compeller, Jove, In combat. Go and freely make thy boast Among the gods that thou hast vanquished me." He spake: Latona gathered from the ground » fhe bow and shafts which in that whirl of dust Had fallen here and there, and, bearing them, Followed her daughter, who meantime had reached Olympus and the brazen halls of Jove. And there, a daughter at her father's knees, ut She sat her down, while, as she wept, her robe Of heavenly texture trembled. Graciously Page 254 254 The Iliad. Jove smiled, and drew her toward him and inquired: "What dweller of the sky has dared do this, Dear child, as though some flagrant guilt were thine?" And thus replied the mistress of the chase *i, Crowned with the crescent: "Father, 't was thy queen, The white-armed Juno; she who causes strife And wrath among the gocls has done me wrong." So talked they, while to sacred Ilium came *n Phoebus Apollo; 't was his charge to watch The well-built city's ramparts, lest the Greeks That day should lay it waste against the will Of fate. The other gods went back to heaven, Some angry, some exulting. They sat down tm Beside the All-Father, him who darkens heaven With gathered clouds. Meantime Achilles chased And slew the Trojans and their firm-paced steeds. As, when the smoke rolls heavenward from a town (liven by the angry gods a prey to fire, «« Toil is the lot of all, and bitter woe The fate of many, such the woe and toil Caused by Achilles to the sons of Troy. The aged Priam from a lofty tower Beheld the large-limbed son of Peleus range The field, and all the Trojans helplessly Fleeing in tumult. With a cry of grief He came from that high station to the ground, And gave commandment to the sturdy men Who stood to watch the gates along the wall:— oss Page 255 Book XXI. 255 "Hold the gates open while the flying host Enter the city; for Achilles comes, Routing them, near at hand, and we may see Terrible havoc. But when all our troops Are once within the walls, and breathe again, «,• Shut the close-fitting portals; for I dread Lest that fierce warrior rush into our streets." He spake: they drew the bolts and opened wide The gates, and gave a refuge to the host. Then leaped Apollo forth to meet their flight And rescue them. All faint with burning thirst, And grimed with dust, they hurried o'er the plain, And toward the city and its lofty walls, While eagerly Achilles on their track Pressed with his spear; his heart was full of rage, 070 And all on fire his spirit with desire For glory. Then the Greeks had overthrown The towery Troy, if Phoebus had not moved Agenor, a young hero, nobly born. Blameless, and brave, Antenor's son, to meet «7s Achilles. Phoebus breathed into his heart Courage, as, standing by the youth, he leaned Against a beechen tree, and, wrapped from sight In darkness, watched to rescue him from death. Agenor stood as he beheld approach e> The mighty spoiler, and, perplexed in mind, Sighed heavily, and said to his great soul :— "Ah me! if with the routed troops I flee From fierce Achilles, he will overtake Page 256 256 The Iliad. And slay me; I shall die as cowards die. «s But if I leave the host to be pursued By Peleus' son, and by another way Flee from the wall across the plain, until I reach the lawns of Ida, and am hid Among its thickets, then I may at eve «90 Bathe in the river and return refreshed To Troy. But why give way to thoughts like these? For he may yet observe me as I haste From Ilium o'er the plain, and his swift feet May follow; there will then be no escape «;s From death and fate, since he in might of arm Excels all other men. If now I here Confront him before Troy, I cannot think That he is weapon-proof; one life alone Dwells in him, though Saturnian Jupiter 7~ Bestows on him the glory of the day." He spake, and firmly waited for the son Of Peleus; eagerly his fearless heart Longed for the combat. As a panther leaves The covert of the wood and comes to meet 70s A huntsman, nor is scared nor put to flight By noise of baying hounds, not even though A spear's thrust or a javelin flung from far Have wounded him, yet, wounded, he fights on, Until he grapples with his enemy 7,o Or perishes, — thus did the noble son Of the renowned Antenor press to try His prowess with Achilles, and disdained Page 257 Book XXI. 257 To flee before him. Holding his round shield Before his face, and with his lifted spear 7,s Aimed at the Greek, he shouted thus aloud :— "Renowned Achilles! thou dost fondly nope That thou to-day wilt overthrow the town Of the magnanimous Trojans. Many toils, Thou fool! must be endured ere that can be; 7» For we are many and are brave who dwell Within it, and shall well defend the town For our beloved parents and our wives And little ones. Here shall thou meet thy doom, Brave as thou art, and terrible in war." 7»s As thus he spake, his powerful hand dismissed The keen-edged spear, nor missed his aim; it struck The son of Peleus just below the knee. The tin of which the greave was newly forged Rang shrilly, and sent back the brazen point; iy, It could not pierce the armor which a god Had given. And then the son of Peleus aimed His weapon at Agenor. Phoebus came And snatched away his triumph, bearing off The godlike youth, Agenor, in a veil 7« Of darkness from the perils of the war. Then he decoyed Achilles from the host Of Troy; the archer of the skies put on Agenor's perfect semblance, and appeared Before the Greek, and fled; his hasty flight 7*, Was followed close. Achilles chased the god Ever before him, yet still near, across Q Page 258 258 The Iliad. The fruitful fields, to the deep-eddied stream Of Xanthus; for Apollo artfully Made it to seem that he should soon o'ertake His flying foe, and thus beguiled him on. Meantime the routed Trojans gladly thronged Into the city, filled the streets, and closed The portals. None now dared without the walls To wait for others, or remain to know Who had escaped with life, and who were slain In battle; eagerly they flung themselves Into the city, — every one whose feet And knees had borne him from the field alive.

XXII

.

THUS were they driven within the city walls Like frighted fawns, and there dispersing cooled Their sweaty limbs, and quenched their eager thirst, And rested on the battlements. The Greeks, Bearing their shields upon their shoulders, came s Close to the ramparts. Hector's adverse fate Detained him still without the walls of Troy, And near the Scaean gates. Meantime the god Apollo to the son of Peleus said :— "O son of Peleus! why pursue me thus » With thy swift feet, — a mortal man in chase Page 259 Book XXII. 259 Of an immortal? That I am a god Thou seest not yet, but turnest all thy rage On me, and, having put the host of Troy To rout, dost think of them no more. They find ,s A refuge in their town, while far astray Thou wanderest hither. Thou hast not the power To slay me; I am not of mortal birth." The swift Achilles angrily replied: "O archer-god, thou most unjust of all » The immortals! thou hast wronged me, luring me Aside; since many a warrior I had forced To bite the dust before they reached the gates Of Ilium but for thee, who from my grasp Hast snatched the glory and hast rescued them. »s Thou didst not fear my vengeance; yet if power Were given me, I would punish thee for this." He spake, and with heroic purpose turned Toward Ilium. As a steed that wins the race Flies at his utmost speed across the plain, y And whirls along the chariot, with such speed The son of Peleus moved his rapid feet. The aged monarch Priam was the first To see him as he scoured the plain, and shone Like to the star which in the autumn time « Rises and glows among the lights of heaven With eminent lustre at the dead of night, — Orion's Hound they call it, — bright indeed, And yet of baleful omen, for it brings Distressing heat to miserable men. *, Page 260 2(5o The Iliad. So shone the brass upon the warrior's breast As on he flew. The aged Priam groaned, And smote his head with lifted hands, and called Aloud, imploring his beloved son, Who eagerly before the city gate Waited his foe Achilles. Priam thus, With outstretched hands, besought him piteously :- "O wait not, Hector, my beloved son, To combat with Pelides, thus alone And far from succor, lest thou meet thy death, Slain by his hand, for he is mightier far Than thou art. \Yrould that he, the cruel one, Were but as much the favorite of the gods As he is mine! then should the birds of prey And dogs devour his carcass, and the grief That weighs upon my spirit would depart. I have been robbed by him of many sons, — Brave youths, whom he has slain or sold as slaves In distant isles; and now I see no more Among our host on whom the gates are closed My Polydorus and Lycaon, whom The peerless dame Laothoe bore to me. If yet they are within the Grecian camp, I will redeem their lives with brass and gold; For I have store, which Altes, the renowned And aged, gave his daughter. If they live No longer, but have passed to the abode Of Hades, bitter will our sorrow be, — Mine and their mother's, — but the popular grief Page 261 Book XXII. 26 r Will sooner be consoled if thou fall not, 70 Slain by Achilles. Come within the walls, My son, that thou mayst still be the defence Of Ilium's sons and daughters, nor increase The glory of Pelides with the loss Of th ine own life. Have pity upon me, 7s Who only live to suffer, — whom the son Of Saturn, on the threshold of my age, Hath destined to endure a thousand griefs, And then to be destroyed, — to see my sons Slain by the sword, my daughters dragged away «o Into captivity, their chambers made A spoil, our infants dashed against the ground By cruel hands, the consorts of my sons Borne off by the ferocious Greeks; and last, Perchance the very dogs which I have fed «s Here in my palaces and at my board, The guardians of my doors, when, by the spear Or sword, some enemy shall take my life, And at my threshold leave me stretched a corpse, Will rend me, and, with savage greediness, 50 Will lap my blood, and in the porch lie down. When one in prime of youth lies slain in war, Gashed with the spear, his wounds become him well, And honor him in all men's eyes; but when An aged man is slain, and his white head m And his white beard and limbs are foully torn By ravening dogs, there is no sadder sight." So the old monarch spake, and with his hands Page 262 262 The Iliad. Tore his gray hair, but moved not Hector thus. Then came, with lamentations and in tears, i-» The warrior's mother forward. One hand laid Her bosom bare; she pressed the other hand Beneath it, sobbed, and spake these winged words:— "Revere this bosom, Hector, and on me Have pity. If when thou wert but a babe 1..s I ever on this bosom stilled thy cries, Think of it now, beloved child; avoid That dreadful chief; withdraw within the walls, Nor madly think to encounter him alone, Son of my love and of my womb! If he «0 Should slay thee, I shall not lament thy death Above thy bier, — I, nor thy noble wife, — But far from us„the greedy dogs will throng To mangle thee beside the Grecian fleet." Thus, weeping bitterly, the aged pair n$ Entreated their dear son, yet moved him not. He stood and waited for his mighty foe Achilles, as a serpent at his den, Fed on the poisons of the wild, awaits The traveller, and, fierce with hate of man, i~ And glaring fearfully, lies coiled within. So waited Hector with a resolute heart, And kept his ground, and, leaning his bright shield Against a tower that jutted from the walls, Conferred with his great soul impatiently : — ns "Ah me! if I should pass within the walls, Then will Polydamas be first to cast Page 263 Book XXII. 263 Reproach upon me; for he counselled me To lead the Trojans back into the town That fatal night which saw Achilles rise ,*, To join the war again. I yielded not To his advice; far better if I had. Now, since my fatal stubbornness has brought This ruin on my people, I most dread The censure of the men and long-robed dames ns Of Ilium. Men less brave than I will say, 'Foolhardy Hector in his pride has thrown His people's lives away.' So will they speak, And better were it for me to return, Achilles slain, or, slain myself by him, ,*, To perish for my country gloriously. But should I lay aside this bossy shield And this stout helm, and lean against the wall This spear, and go to meet the gallant son Of Peleus, with a promise to restore us Helen and all the treasure brought with her To Troy by Paris, in his roomy ships, — All that the war was waged for, — that the sons Of Atreus may convey it hence, besides Wealth drawn from all the hoards within the town, And to be shared among the Greeks; for I i« Would bind the Trojans by a solemn oath To keep brick nothing, but divide the whole- AVhate'er of riches this fair town contains — Into two parts— But why should I waste thought On plans like these? I must not act the part ,f,. Page 264 264 The Iliad. Of suppliant to a man who may not show Regard or mercy, but may hew me down Defenceless, with my armor laid aside As if I were a woman. Not with him *» May I hold parley from a tree or rock, As youths and maidens with each other hold Light converse. Better't were to rush at once To combat, and the sooner learn to whom Olympian Jove decrees the victory." i«s Such were his thoughts. Achilles now drew near. Like crested Mars, the warrior-god, he came. On his right shoulder quivered fearfully The Pelian ash, and from his burnished mail There streamed a light as of a blazing fire, 170 Or of the rising sun. When Hector saw, He trembled, nor could venture to remain, But left the gates and fled away in fear. Pelides, trusting to his rapid feet, Pursued him. As, among the mountain wilds, ,re A falcon, fleetest of the birds of air, Darts toward a timid dove that wheels away To shun him by a sidelong flight, while he Springs after her again and yet again, And screaming follows, certain of his prey, — ,*, Thus onward flew Achilles, while as fast Fled Hector in dismay, with hurrying feet, Beside the wall. They passed the Mount of View, And the wind-beaten fig-tree, and they ran Along the public way by which the wall '«s Page 265 Book XXII. 265 Was skirted, till they came where from the ground The two fair springs of eddying Xanthus rise,— One pouring a warm stream from which ascends And spreads a vapor like a smoke from fire; The other, even in summer, sending forth 1*, A current cold as hail, or snow, or ice. And there were broad stone basins, fairly wrought, At which, in time of peace, before the Greeks Had landed on the plain, the Trojan dames And their fair daughters washed their sumptuous robes. ,« Past these they swept; one fled, and one pursued, — A brave man fled, a braver followed close, And swiftly both. Not for a common prize, A victim from the herd, a bullock's hide, Such as reward the fleet of foot, they ran, — *» The race was for the knightly Hector's life. As firm-paced coursers, that are wont to win, Fly toward the goal, when some magnificent prize, A tripod or a damsel, is proposed In honor of some hero's obsequies, ~s So these flew thrice on rapid feet around The city of Priam. All the gods of heaven Looked on, and thus the Almighty Father spake : — "Alas! I see a hero dear to me Pursued around the wall. My heart is grieved ™ For Hector, who has brought so many thighs Of bullocks to my altar on the side Of Ida ploughed with glens, or on the heights VOL. 11. 12 Page 266 266 The Iliad. Of Ilium. The renowned Achilles now Is chasing him with rapid feet around «s The city of Priam. Now bethink yourselves, And answer. Shall we rescue him from death? Or shall we doom him, valiant as he is, To perish by the hand of Peleus' son?" Minerva, blue-eyed goddess, answered thus: »» "O Father, who dost hurl the thunderbolt, And hide the sky in clouds, what hast thou said? Wouldst thou reprieve from death a mortal man, Whose doom is fixed? Then do it; but know this, That all the other gods will not approve." »s Then spake again the Cloud-compeller Jove: "Tritonia, my dear child, be calm. I spake Of no design. I would be kind to thee. Do as thou wilt, and be there no delay." He spake; and Pallas from the Olympian peaks, Encouraged by his words in what her thought n, Had planned already, downward shot to earth. Still, with quick steps, the fleet Achilles pressed On Hector's flight. As when a hound has roused A fawn from its retreat among the hills, ns And chases it through glen and forest ground. And to close thickets, where it skulks in fear Until he overtake it, Hector thus Sought vainly to elude the fleet pursuit Of Peleus' son. As often as he thought, »«0 By springing toward the gates of Troy, to gain Aid from the weapons of his friends who stood Page 267 Book XXII. 267 On the tall towers, so often was the Greek Before him, forcing him to turn away From Ilium toward the plain. Achilles thus mi Kept nearest to the city. As in dreams The fleet pursuer cannot overtake, Nor the pursued escape, so was it now; One followed but in vain, the other fled As fruitlessly. But how could Hector thus »s» Have put aside the imminent doom of death, Had not Apollo met him once again, For the last time, and given him strength and speed? The great Achilles nodded to his host A sign that no man should presume to strike «a At Hector with his weapon, lest perchance Another, wounding him, should bear away The glory, and Pelides only wear The second honors. When the twain had come For the fourth time beside Scamander's springs, *» The All-Father raised the golden balance high, And, placing in the scales two lots which bring Death's long dark sleep, — one lot for Peleus' son, And one for knightly Hector, — by the midst He poised the balance. Hector's fate sank down *s To Hades, and Apollo left the field. The blue-eyed goddess Pallas then approached The son of Peleus with these winged words : — "Renowned Achilles, dear to Jupiter! Now may we, as I hope, at last return w To the Achaian army and the fleet Page 268 268 T/ie IlUid. With glory, Hector slain, the terrible In war. Escape he cannot, even though The archer-god Apollo fling himself With passionate entreaty at the feet Of Jove the ^igis-bearer. Stay thou here And breathe a moment, while I go to him And lure him hither to encounter thee." She spake, and he obeyed, and gladly stood Propped on the ashen stem of his keen spear; While, passing on, Minerva overtook The noble Hector. In the outward form, And with the strong voice of Deiphobus, She stood by him and spake these winged words: "Hard pressed I find thee, brother, by the swift Achilles, who, with feet that never rest, Pursues thee round the walls of Priam's town. But let us make a stand and beat him back." And then the crested Hector spake in turn: "Deiphobus, thou ever hast been dear To me beyond my other brethren, sons Of Hecuba and Priam. Now still more I honor thee, since thou hast seen my plight, And for my sake hast ventured forth without The gates, while all the rest remain within." And then the blue-eyed Pallas spake again: "Brother! 't is true, my father, and the queen, My mother, and my comrades, clasped my knees In turn, and earnestly entreated me That I would not go forth, such fear had fallen Page 269 Book XXII. 269 On all of them; but I was grieved for thee. Now let us combat valiantly, nor spare The weapons that we bear, and we shall learn Whether Achilles, having slain us both, Will carry to the fleet our bloody spoil, 30s Or die himself, the victim of thy spear." The treacherous goddess spake, and led the way; And when the advancing chiefs stood face to face, The crested hero, Hector, thus began : — "No longer I avoid thee as of late, v O son of Peleus! Thrice around the walls Of Priam's mighty city have I fled, Nor dared to wait thy coming. Now my heart Bids me encounter thee; my time is ceme To slay or to be slain. Now let us call sis The gods to witness, who attest and guard The covenants of men. Should Jove bestow On me the victory, and I take thy life, Thou shalt meet no dishonor at my hands; But, stripping off the armor, I will send p» The Greeks thy body. Do the like by me." The swift Achilles answered with a frown: "Accursed Hector, never talk to me Of covenants. Men and lions plight no faith, Nor wolves agree with lambs, but each must plan v$ Evil against the other. So between Thyself and me no compact can exist, Or understood intent. First, one of us Must fall and yield his life-blood to the god Page 270 270 The Iliad. Of battles. Summon all thy valor now. 330 A skilful spearman thou hast need to be, And a bold warrior. There is no escape, For now doth Pallas doom thee to be slain By my good spear. Thou shalt repay to me The evil thou hast done my countrymen, — 3^ My friends whom thou hast slaughtered in thy rage." He spake, and, brandishing his massive spear, Hurled it at Hector, who beheld its aim From where he stood. He stooped, and over him The brazen weapon passed, and plunged to earth, wo U nseen by royal Hector, Pallas went And plucked it from the ground, and brought it back And gave it to the hands of Peleus' son, While Hector said to his illustrious foe :— "Godlike Achilles, thou hast missed thy mark; 3« Nor hast thou learned my doom from Jupiter, As thou pretendest. Thou art glib of tongue. And cunningly thou orderest thy speech, In hope that I who hear thee may forget My might and valor. Think not I shall flee, 3s0 That thou mayst pierce my back; for thou shalt send Thy spear, if God permit thee, through my breast As I rush on thee. Now avoid in turn My brazen weapon. Would that it might pass Clean through thee, all its length! The tasks of war For us of Troy were lighter for thy death, 3s« Thou pest and deadly foe of all our race!" He spake, and brandishing his massive spear, Page 271 Book XXII. 271 Hurled it, nor missed, but in the centre smote The buckler of Pelides. Far away *s0 It bounded from the brass, and he was vexed To see that the swift weapon from his hand Had flown in vain. He stood perplexed and sad; No second spear had he. He called aloud On the white-bucklered chief, Deiphobus, *s To bring another; but that chief was far, And Hector saw that it was so, and said :— "Ah me! the gods have summoned me to die. I thought my warrior-friend, Deiphobus, Was by my side; but he is still in Troy, w, And Pallas has deceived me. Now my death Cannot be far, — is near; there is no hope Of my escape, for so it pleases Jove And Jove's great archer-son, who have till now Delivered me. My hour at last is come; 37s Yet not ingloriously or passively I die, but first will do some valiant deed, Of which mankind shall hear in after time.'" He spake, and drew the keen-edged sword that hung, Massive and finely tempered, at his side, ?*, And sprang — as when an eagle high in heaven, Through the thick cloud, darts downward to the plain To clutch some tender lamb or timid hare, So Hector, brandishing that keen-edged sword, Sprang forward, while Achilles opposite » Page 272 272 The Iliad. Leaped toward him, all on fire with savage hate, And holding his bright buckler, nobly wrought, Before him. On his shining helmet waved The fourfold crest; there tossed the golden tufts With which the hand of Vulcan lavishly Had decked it. As in the still hours of night Hesper goes forth among the host of stars, The fairest light of heaven, so brightly shone, Brandished in the right hand of Peleus' son, The spear's keen blade, as, confident to slay The noble Hector, o'er his glorious form His quick eye ran, exploring where to plant The surest wound. The glittering mail of brass Won from the slain Patroclus guarded well Each part, save only where the collar-bones Divide the shoulder from the neck, and there Appeared the throat, the spot where life is most In peril. Through that part the noble son Of Peleus drave his spear; it went quite through The tender neck, and yet the brazen blade Cleft not the windpipe, and the power to speak Remained. The Trojan fell amid the dust, And thus Achilles boasted o'er his fall: — "Hector, when from the slain Patroclus thou Didst strip his armor, little didst thou think Of danger. Thou hadst then no fear of me, Who was not near thee to avenge his death. Fool! there was left within the roomy ships A mightier one than he, who should come forth, Page 273 Book XXII. 273 The avenger of his blood, to take thy life. 41s Foul dogs and birds of prey shall tear thy flesh; The Greeks shall honor him with funeral rites." And then the crested Hector faintly said: "I pray thee by thy life, and by thy knees, And by thy parents, suffer not the dogs 4*, To tear me at the galleys of the Greeks. Accept abundant store of brass and gold, Which gladly will my father and the queen, My mother, give in ransom. Send to them My body, that the warriors and the dames *>s Of Troy may light for me the funeral pile." The swift Achilles answered with a frown: "Nay, by my knees entreat me not, thou cur, Nor by my parents. I could even wish My fury prompted me to cut thy flesh 4*, In fragments, and devour it, such the wrong That I have had from thee. There will be none To drive away the dogs about thy head, Not though thy Trojan friends should bring to me Tenfold and twenty-fold the offered gifts, 41s And promise others, — not though Priam, sprung From Dardanus, should send thy weight in gold. Thy mother shall not lay thee on thy bier, To sorrow over thee whom she brought forth; But dogs and birds of prey shall mangle thee." 4*, And then the crested Hector, dying, said: "I know thee, and too clearly I foresaw I should not move thee, for thou hast a heart 12 • R Page 274 274 The Iliad. Of iron. Yet reflect that for my sake The anger of the gods may fall on thee, «s When Paris and Apollo strike thee down, Strong as thou art, before the Scsean gates." Thus Hector spake, and straightway o'er him closed The night of death; the soul forsook his limbs, And flew to Hades, grieving for its fate, — 4se So soon divorced from youth and youthful might. Then said the great Achilles to the dead:— "Die thou; and I, whenever it shall please Jove and the other gods, will meet my fate." He spake, and, plucking forth his brazen lance, «ss He laid it by, and from the body stripped The bloody mail. The thronging Greeks beheld With wonder Hector's tall and stately form, And no one came who did not add a wound; And, looking to each other, thus they said :— *v, "How much more tamely Hector now endures Our touch than when he set the fleet on fire!" Such were the words of those who smote the dead; But now, when swift Achilles from the corpse Had stripped the armor, he stood forth among «s The Achaian host, and spake these winged words:— "Leaders and princes of the Grecian host! Since we, my friends, by favor of the gods, Have overcome the chief who wrought more harm To us than all the rest, let us assault 47• The town, and learn what they of Troy intend, — Page 275 Book XXII. 27$ Whether their troops will leave the citadel Since he is slain, or hold it with strong hand, Though Hector is no more. But why give thought To plans like these while yet Patroclus lies m A corse unwept, unburied, at the fleet? I never will forget him while I live And while these limbs have motion. Though below In Hades they forget the dead, yet I Will there remember my beloved friend. «so Now then, ye youths of Greece, move on and chant A paean, while, returning to the fleet, We bring great glory with us; we have slain The noble Hector, whom, throughout their town, The Trojans ever worshipped like a god." *s He spake, and, plannmg in his mind to treat The noble Hector shamefully, he bored The sinews of his feet between the heel And ankle; drawing through them leathern thongs He bound them to the car, but left the head «0 To trail in dust. And then he climbed the car, Took in the shining mail, and lashed to speed The coursers. Not unwillingly they flew. Around the dead, as he was dragged along, The dust arose; his dark locks swept the ground ** That head, of late so noble in men's eyes, Lay deep amid the dust, for Jove that day Suffered the foes of Hector to insult His corse in his own land. His mother saw, And tore her hair, and flung her lustrous veil s* Page 276 276 The Iliad. Away, and uttered piercing shrieks. No less His father, who so loved him, piteously Bewailed him; and in all the streets of Troy The people wept aloud, with such lament As if the towery Ilium were in flames s0s Even to its loftiest roofs. They scarce could keep The aged king within, who, wild with grief, Struggled to rush through the Dardanian gates, And, rolling in the dust, entreated all Who stood around him, calling them by name : — yo "Refrain, my friends, though kind be your intent. Let me go forth alone, and at the fleet Of Greece will I entreat this man of blood And violence. He may perchance be moved With reverence for my age, and pity me s,s In my gray hairs; for such a one as I Is Peleus, his own father, by whose care This Greek was reared to be a scourge to Troy, And, more than all, a cause of grief to me, So many sons of mine in life's fresh prime s*, Have fallen by his hand. I mourn for them, But not with such keen anguish as I mourn For Hector. Sorrow for his death will bring My soul to Hades. Would that he had died Here in my arms! this solace had been ours, — s»s His most unhappy mother and myself Had stooped to shed these tears upon his bier." He spake, and wept, and all the citizens Wept with him. Hecuba among the dames Page 277 Book XXII. 277 Took up the lamentation, and began : — s*, "Why do I live, my son, when thou art dead, And I so wretched ? — thou who wert my boast Ever, by night and day, where'er I went, And whom the Trojan men and matrons called Their bulwark, honoring thee as if thou wert s» A god. They gtory in thy might no more, Since Fate and Death have overtaken thee." Weeping she spake. Meantime Andromache Had heard no tidings of her husband yet. No messenger had even come to say s4» That he was still without the gates. She sat In a recess of those magnificent halls, And wove a twofold web of brilliant hues, On which were scattered flowers of rare device; And she had given her bright-haired maidens charge To place an ample caldron on the fire, an That Hector, coming from the battle-field, Might find the warm bath ready. Thoughtless one! She knew not that the blue-eyed archer-queen, Far from the bath prepared for him, had slain ss0 Her husband by the hand of Peleus' son. She heard the shrieks, the wail upon the tower, Trembled in every limb, and quickly dropped The shuttle, saying to her bright-haired maids : — "Come with me, two of you, that I may learn s« What now has happened. 'T is my mother's voice That I have heard. My heart leaps to my mouth; My limbs fail under me. Some deadly harm Page 278 2/8 The Iliad. Hangs over Priam's sons; far be the hour When I shall hear of it. And yet I fear s*» Lest that Achilles, having got between .The daring Hector and the city gates, May drive him to the plain alone, and quell The desperate valor that was ever his; For never would he keep the ranks, but ranged s«s Beyond them, and gave way to no man's might." She spake, and from the royal mansion rushed Distractedly, and with a beating heart. Her maids went with her. When she reached the tower And throng of men, and, standing on the wall, s7° Looked forth, she saw her husband dragged away Before the city. Toward the Grecian fleet The swift steeds drew him. Sudden darkness came Over her eyes, and in a breathless swoon She sank away and fell. The ornaments 37s Dropped from her brow, — the wreath, the woven band, The net, the veil which golden Venus gave That day when crested Hector wedded her, Dowered with large gifts, and led her from her home, Eetion's palace. Round her in a throng s*, Her sisters of the house of Priam pressed, And gently raised her in that deathlike swoon. But when she breathed again, and to its seat The conscious mind returned, as in their arms She lay, with sobs and broken speech she said : — sss Page 279 Book XXII. 279 "Hector, — O wretched me ! — we both were born To sorrow; thou at Troy, in Priam's house, And I at Thebe in Eetion's halls, By woody Placos. From a little child He reared me there, — unhappy he, and I »0 Unhappy! O that I had ne'er been born! Thou goest down to Hades and the depths Of earth, and leavest me in thine abode, Widowed, and never to be comforted. Thy son, a speechless babe, to whom we two s95 Gave being, — hapless parents! — cannot have Thy loving guardianship now thou art dead, Nor be a joy to thee. Though he survive The cruel warfare which the sons of Greece Are waging, hard and evil yet will be 60. His lot hereafter; others will remove His landmarks and will make his fields their own. The day in which a boy is fatherless Makes him companionless; with, downcast eyes He wanders, and his cheeks are stained with tears. Unfed he goes where sit his father's friends, ** And plucks one by the cloak, and by the robe Another. One who pities him shall give A scanty draught, which only wets his lips, But not his palate; while another boy, «,0 Whose parents both are living, thrusts him thence With blows and vulgar clamor: 1 Get thee gone! Thy father is not with us at the feast.' Page 280 28o The Iliad. Then to his widowed mother shall return Astyanax in tears, who not long since «,i Was fed, while sitting in his father's lap, On marrow and the delicate fat of lambs. And ever when his childish sports had tired The boy, and sleep came stealing over him, He slumbered, softly cushioned, on a couch **, And in his nurse's arms, his heart at ease And satiate with delights. But now thy son Astyanax, — whom so the Trojans name Because thy valor guarded gate and tower, — Thy care withdrawn, shall suffer many things. ««s While far from those who gave thee birth, beside The roomy ships of Greece, the restless worms Shall make thy flesh their banquet when the dogs Have gorged themselves. Thy garments yet remain Within the palace, delicately wrought *s» And graceful, woven by the women's hands; And these, since thou shalt put them on no more, Nor wear them in thy death, I burn with fire Before the Trojan men and dames; and all Shall see how gloriously thou wert arrayed." *o Weeping she spake, and with her wept her maid..

XXIII

.

SO mourned they in the city; but the Greeks, When they had reached the fleet and Helles- pont, Dispersed, repairing each one to his ship, Save that Achilles suffered not his band Of Myrmidons to part in disarray. s And thus the chief enjoined his warrior friends :— "Myrmidons, gallant knights, my cherished friends! Let us not yet unyoke our firm-paced steeds, But bring them with the chariots, and bewail Patroclus with the honors due the dead, ,» And, when we have indulged in grief, release Our steeds and take our evening banquet here." He spake, and led by him the host broke forth In lamentation. Thrice around the dead, Weeping, they drave their steeds with stately manes, While Thetis in their hearts awoke the sense ,« Of hopeless loss; their tears bedewed the sands, And dropped upon their arms, so brave was he For whom they sorrowed. Peleus' son began The mourning; on the breast of his dead friend » He placed his homicidal hands, and said :— "Hail thou, Patroclus, even amid the shades! For now shall I perform what once I vowed: Page 282 282 The Iliad. That, dragging Hector hither, I will give His corse to dogs, and they shall rend his flesh; »s And at thy funeral pile there shall be slain Twelve noble Trojan youths, to avenge thy death." So spake he, meditating outrages To noble Hector's corse, which he had flung Beside the bier of Menoetiades, 30 Amid the dust. The Myrmidons unbraced Their shining brazen armor, and unyoked Their neighing steeds, and sat in thick array Beside the ship of swift /Eacides, While he set forth a sumptuous funeral feast. s Many a white ox, that day, beneath the axe Fell to the earth, and many bleating goats And sheep were slain, and many fattened swine, White-toothed, were stretched to roast before the flame Of Vulcan, and around the corse the earth «. Floated with blood. Meantime the Grecian chiefs To noble Agamemnon's royal tent Led the swift son of Peleus, though he went Unwillingly, such anger for the death Of his companion burned within his heart. 4s As soon as they had reached his tent, the king Bade the clear-throated heralds o'er the fire Place a huge tripod, that Pelides there Might wash away the bloody stains he bore. Yet would he not, and with an oath replied :— s0 "No! by the greatest and the best of gods, Page 283 Book XXIII. 283 By Jupiter, I may not plunge my head Into the bath before I lay my friend Patroclus on the fire, and heap his mound, And till my hair is shorn; for never more ss In life will be so great a sorrow mine. But now attend we to this mournful feast . And with the morn, O king of men, command That wood be brought, and all things duly done Which may beseem a warrior who goes down «0 Into the lower darkness. Let the flamec Seize fiercely and consume him from our sight, And leave the people to the tasks of war." He spake; they hearkened and obeyed, and all Prepared with diligent hands the meal, and each «* Sat down and took his portion of the feast. And when their thirst and hunger were allayed, Most to their tents betook them and to rest. But Peleus' son, lamenting bitterly, Lay down among his Myrmidons, beside v The murmuring ocean, in the open space, Where plashed the billows on the beach. And there, When slumber, bringing respite from his cares, Came softly and enfolded him, — for much His shapely limbs were wearied with the chase is Of Hector round the windy Ilium's walls,— The soul of his poor friend Patroclus came, Like him in all things,—stature, beautiful eyes, And voice, and garments which he wore in life. Page 284 284 The llia.i. Beside his head the vision stood and spake :— "Achilles, sleepest thou, forgetting me? Never of me unmindful in my life, Thou dost neglect me dead. O, bury me Quickly, and give me entrance through the gates Of Hades; for the souls, the forms of those Who live no more, repulse me, suffering not That I should join their company beyond The river, and I now must wander round The spacious portals of the House of Death. Give me thy hand, I pray; for never more Shall I return to earth when once the fire Shall have consumed me. Never shall we take Counsel together, living, as we sit Apart from our companions; the hard fate Appointed me at birth hath drawn me down. Thou too, O godlike man, wilt fall beneath The ramparts of the noble sons of Troy. Yet this I ask, and if thou wilt obey, This I command thee, — not to let my bones Be laid apart from thine. As we were reared , Under thy roof together, from the time When first Menoetius brought thee, yet a boy, From Opus, where I caused a sorrowful death ; — For by my hand, when wrangling at the dice, Another boy, son of Amphidamas, » Was slain without design, — and Peleus made His halls my home, and reared me tenderly, And made me thy companion ; — so at last Page 285 Book XXIII. 285 May one receptacle, the golden vase Given by thy gracious mother, hold our bones." no The swift Achilles answered: "O most loved And honored, wherefore art thou come, and why Dost thou command me thus? I shall fulfil Obediently thy wish; yet draw thou near, And let us give at least a brief embrace, ns And so indulge our grief." He said, and stretched His longing arms to clasp the shade. In vain; Away like smoke it went, with gibbering cry, Down to the earth. Achilles sprang upright, Astonished, clapped his hands, and sadly said : — ,*, "Surely there dwell within the realm below Both soul and form, though bodiless. All night Hath stood the spirit of my hapless friend Patroclus near me, sad and sorrowful, And asking many duties at my hands, i»s A marvellous semblance of the living man." He spake, and moved the hearts of all to grief And lamentation. Rosy-fingered Morn Dawned on them as around the hapless dead They stood and wept. Then Agamemnon sent ,», In haste from all the tents the mules and men To gather wood, and summoned to the task Meriones, himself a gallant chief, Attendant on the brave Idomeneus. These went with woodmen's axes and with ropes 13s Well twisted, and before them went the mules. O'er steep, o'er glen, by straight, by winding ways, Page 286 286 The Iliad. They journeyed till they reached the woodland wilds Of Ida fresh with springs, and quickly felled With the keen steel the towering oaks that came Crashing to earth. Then, splitting the great trunk. They bound them on the mules, that beat the earth With hasty footsteps through the tangled wood, Impatient for the plain. Each woodcutter Shouldered a tree, for so Meriones, Companion of the brave Idomeneus, Commanded, and at last they laid them down In order on the shore, where Peleus' son Planned that a mighty sepulchre should rise Both for his friend Patroclus and himself. is0 So brought they to the spot vast heaps of wood, And sat them down, a numerous crowd. But then Achilles bade his valiant Myrmidons Put on their brazen mail and yoke their steeds. At once they rose, and put their harness on, « And they who fought from chariots climbed their seats With those who reined the steeds. These led the van, And after them a cloud of men on foot By thousands followed. In the midst was borne Patroclus by his comrades. Cutting off «• Their hair, they strewed it, covering the dead. Behind the corpse, Achilles in his hands Sustained the head, and wept, for on that day He gave to Hades his most cherished friend. Page 287 Book XXIII. 2*7 Now when they reached the spot which Pelcus' son ,«3 Had chosen, they laid down the dead, and piled The wood-around him, while the swift of foot, The great Achilles, bent on other thoughts, Standing apart, cut off his amber hair, Which for the river Sperchius he had long 170 Nourished to ample growth, and, sighing, turned His eyes upon the dark-blue sea, and said :— "Sperchius, in vain my father made a vow That I, returning to my native shore, Should bring my hair, an offering to thee, 17s And slay a consecrated hecatomb, And burn a sacrifice of fifty rams, Beside the springs where in a sacred field Thy fragrant altar stands. Such was the vow Made by the aged man, yet hast thou not i*. Fulfilled his wish. And now, since I no more Shall see my native land, the land I love, Let the slain hero bear these locks away." He spake, and in his dear companion's hands He placed the hair, and all around were moved 13s To deeper grief; the setting sun had left The host lamenting, had not Peleus' son Addressed Atrides, standing at his side : — "Atrides, thou whose word the Greeks obey Mcst readily, all mourning has an end. ,io Dismiss the people from the pyre to take Their evening meal, while we with whom it rests Page 288 288 The Iliad. To pay these mournful duties to the dead Will close the rites; but let the chiefs remain.** This when the monarch Agamemnon heard, Instantly he dismissed to their good ships The people. They who had the dead in charge Remained, and heaped the wood, and built a pyre A hundred feet each way from side to side. ,» With sorrowful hearts they raised and laid the corse Upon the summit. Then they flayed and dressed Before it many fatlings of the flock, And oxen with curved feet and crooked horns. From these magnanimous Achilles took The fat, and covered with it carefully « The dead from head to foot. Beside the bier, And leaning toward it, jars of honey and oil He placed, and flung, with many a deep-drawn sigh. Twelve high-necked steeds upon the pile. Nine hounds There were, which from the table of the prince Were daily fed; of these Achilles struck The heads from two, and laid them on the wood, And after these, and last, twelve gallant sons Of the brave Trojans, butchered by the sword; For he was bent on evil. To the pile «s He put the iron violence of fire, And, wailing, called by name the friend he loved :— "Rejoice, Patrochis, even in the land Of souls. Lo! I perform the vow I made; Twelve gallant sons of the brave men of Troy »» Page 289 Book XXIII. 289 The fire consumes with thee. For Hector's corse, The flames shall not devour it, but the dogs." Such was his threat; but Hector was not made The prey of dogs, for Venus, born to Jove, Drave off by night and day the ravenous tribe, «s And with a rosy and ambrosial oil Anointed him, that he might not be torn When dragged along the earth. Above the spot And all around it, where the body lay, Phoebus Apollo drew a veil of clouds 3*, Reaching from heaven, that on his limbs the flesh And sinews might not stiffen in the sun. The flame seized not upon the funeral pile Of the dead chief. Pelides, swift of foot, Bethought him of another rite. He stood »3s Apart, and offered vows to the two winds, '•- Boreas and Zephyr. Promising to bring Fair offerings to their shrines, and pouring out Libations from a golden cup, he prayed That they would haste and wrap the pile in flames, And burn the dead to ashes. At his prayer mi Fleet Iris on a message to the Winds Took instant wing. They sat within the halls Of murmuring Zephyr, at a solemn feast. There Iris lighted on the threshold-stone. «s As soon as they beheld her, each arose And bade her sit beside him. She refused To seat her at the banquet, and replied :— "Not now; for I again must take my way VOI. 11. 13 8 Page 290 290 The Iliad. Over the ocean currents to the land Where dwell the /Ethiopians, who adore The gods with hecatombs, to take my share Of sacrifice. Achilles supplicates, With promise of munificent offerings, Boreas and sounding Zephyrus to come «ss And blow the funeral structure into flames On which, bewailed by all the Grecian host, Patroclus lies, and waits to be consumed." So spake she, and departed. Suddenly Arose the Winds with tumult, driving on The clouds before them. Soon they reached die deep; Beneath the violence of their sounding breath The billows heaved. They swept the fertile fields Of Troas, and descended on the pyre, And mightily it blazed with fearful roar. *ss All night they howled and tossed the flames. All night Stood swift Achilles, holding in his hand A double beaker; from a golden jar He dipped the wine, and poured it forth, and steeped The earth around, and called upon the soul *70 Of his unhappy friend. As one laments A newly married son upon whose corse The flames are feeding, and whose death has made His parents wretched, so did Peleus' son, Burning the body of his comrade, mourn, «73 As round the pyre he moved with frequent sighs. Page 291 Book XXIII. 291 Now when the star that ushers in the day Appeared, and after it the morning, clad In saffron robes, had overspread the sea, The pyre sank wasted, and the flames arose *, No longer, and the Winds, departing, flew Homeward across the Thracian sea, which tossed And roared with swollen billows as they went. And now Pelides from the pyre apart Weary lay down, and gentle slumber soon s Came stealing over him. Meantime the Greeks Gathered round Agamemnon, and the stir And bustle of their coming woke the chief, Who sat upright and thus addressed his friends :— "Atrides, and all ye who lead the hosts »» Of Greece! our task is, first to quench the pyre With dark red wine where'er the flames have spread, And next to gather, with discerning care, The bones of Menoetiades. And these May well be known; for in the middle space »n He lay, and round about him, and apart Upon the border, were the rest consumed, — The bodies of the captives and the steeds. Be his enclosed within a golden vase, And wrapped around with caul, a double fold, *» Till I too pass into the realm of Death. And be a tomb not over-spacious reared, But of becoming size, which afterward Ye whom we leave behind in our good ships, When we are gone, will build more broad and high." Page 292 The Iliad. So spake the swift Pelides, and the chiefs Complied; and first they quenched with dark red wine The pyre, where'er the flames had spread, and where Lay the deep ashes; then, with many tears, Gathered the white bones of their gentle friend, 3.0 And laid them in a golden vase, wrapped round With caul, a double fold. Within the tents They placed them softly, wrapped in delicate lawn, Then drew a circle for the sepulchre, And, laying its foundations to enclose vs The pyre, they heaped the earth, and, having reared A mound, withdrew. Achilles yet detained The multitude, and made them all sit down, A vast assembly. From the ships he brought The prizes,—caldrons, tripods, steeds, and mules, Oxen in sturdy pairs, and graceful maids, And shining steel. Then for the swiftest steeds A princely prize he offered first, — a maid Of peerless form, and skilled in household arts, And a two-handled tripod of a size s»s For two-and-twenty measures. He gave out The second prize, — a mare unbroken yet, Of six years old, and pregnant with a mule. For the third winner in the race he staked A caldron that had never felt the fire, Holding four measures, beautiful, and yet Untarnished. For the fourth, he offered gold, Two talents. For the fifth, and last, remained Page 293 Book XXIII. 293 A double vessel never touched by fire. He rose and stood, and thus addressed the Greeks : — us "Atrides, and ye other well-armed Greeks, These prizes lie within the chariot-course, And wait the charioteers. Were but these games In honor of another, then would I Contend, and win and carry to my tent 340 The first among these prizes. For my steeds, Ye know, surpass the rest in speed, since they Are of immortal birth, by Neptune given To Peleus, and by him in turn bestowed On me his son. But I and they will keep sis Aloof; they miss their skilful charioteer, Who washed in limpid water from the fount Their manes, and moistened them with softening oil. And now they mourn their friend, and sadly stand With drooping heads and manes that touch the ground. 3s0 Let such of you as trust in their swift steeds And their strong cars prepare to join the games." Pelides spake: the abler charioteers Arose, and, first of all, the king of men, Eumelus, eminent in horsemanship, 3ss The dear son of Admetus. Then arose The valiant son of Tydeus, Diomed, And led beneath the yoke the Trojan steeds Won from ^Eneas when Apollo saved That chief from death. The son of Atreus next, 3*, Page 294 294 The Iliad. The noble Menelaus, yellow-haired, Brought two swift coursers underneath the yoke, King Agamemnon's ^b;the, and with her His own Podargus. Kchepolus once, Anchises' son, sent ^fithfc as a gift To Agamemnon, that he might be free From following with the army to the heights Of Ilium, and enjoy the ease he loved; For Jove had given him wealth, and he abode On Sicyon's plains. Now, eager for the race, She took the yoke. Antilochus, the fourth, The gallant son of the magnanimous king, Neleian Nestor, harnessed next his steeds With stately manes. Swift coursers that were foaled At Pylus drew his chariot. To his side as His father came and stood, and spake and gave Wise counsels, though the youth himself was wise :— "Antilochus, I cannot doubt that Jove And Neptune both have loved thee, teaching thee, Young as thou art, all feats of horsemanship. #0 Small is the need to instruct thee. Thou dost know Well how to turn the goal, and yet thy steeds Are slow, and ill for thee may be the event. Their steeds are swift, yet have they never learned To govern them with greater skill than thou. s*s Now then, dear son, bethink thee heedfully Of all precautions, lest thou miss the prize. By skill the woodman, rather than by strength, Brings down the oak; by skill the pilot guides Page 295 Book XXIII. 295 His wind-tossed galley over the dark sea; 390 And thus by skill the charioteer o'ercomes His rival. He who trusts too much his steeds And chariot lets them veer from side to side Along the course, nor keeps a steady rein Straight on, while one expert in horsemanship, 39s Though drawn by slower horses, carefully Observes the goal, and closely passes it, Nor fails to know how soon to turn his course, Drawing the leathern reins, and steadily Keeps on, and watches him who goes before. *» Now must I show the goal which, easily Discerned, will not escape thine eye. It stands An ell above the ground, a sapless post, Of oak or larch, — a wood of slow decay By rain, and at its foot on either side *s Lies a white stone; there narrow is the way, But level is the race-course all around. The monument it is of one long dead, Or haply it has been in former days A goal, as the swift-footed Peleus' son 4«, Has now appointed it. Approach it near, Driving thy chariot close upon its foot, Then in thy seat lean gently to the left And cheer the right-hand horse, and ply the lash, And give him a loose rein, yet firmly keep 41s The left-hand courser close beside the goal, — So close that the wheel's nave may seem to touch The summit of the post; yet strike thou not Page 296 296 The Iliad. The stone beside it, lest thou lame thy steeds And break the chariot, to thy own disgrace «s And laughter of the others. My dear son, Be on thy guard; for if thou pass the goal Before the rest, no man in the pursuit Can overtake or pass thee, though he drave The noble courser of Adrastus, named 4» Arion the swift-footed, which a god Bade spring to life, or those of matchless speed - Reared here in Ilium by Laomedon." Neleian Nestor spake, and, having thus Given all the needful cautions, took his seat «*, In his own place. Meriones, the fifth, Harnessed his steeds with stately manes, and all Mounted their chariots. Lots were cast; the son Of Peleus shook the helmet, and the lot Of Nestor's son, Antilochus, leaped forth; 43s And next the lot of King Eumelus came; And Menelaus, mighty with the spear, Had the third lot; Meriones was next; And to the bravest of them all, the son Of Tydeus, fell the final lot and place. +» They stood in order, while Achilles showed The goal far off upon the level plain, And near it, as the umpire of the race, He placed the godlike Phoenix, who had been His father's armor-bearer, to observe «s With judging eye, and bring a true report. All raised at once the lash above their steeds, Page 297 Book XXIII. 297 \nd smote them with the reins, and cheered them on With vehement cries. Across the plain they swept, Far from the fleet; beneath them rose the dust, 4s0 A cloud, a tempest, and their tossing manes Were lifted by the wind. And now the cars Touched earth, and now were flung into the air. Erect the drivers stood, with beating hearts, Eager for victory, each encouraging 4ss His steeds, that flew beneath the shroud of dust. But when they turned their course, and swiftly ran Back to the hoary deep to close the' course, Well did the skill of every chief appear. They put their horses to the utmost speed, 4, And then did the quick-footed steeds that drew Eumelus bear him on beyond the rest. But with his Trojan coursers Diomed Came next, so near it seemed that they would mount The car before them, and upon the back. 4«s And ample shoulders of Eumelus smote Their steaming breath; for as they ran their heads Leaned over him. And then would Diomed Have passed him by, or would at least have made The victory doubtful, had not Phoebus struck, »0 In his displeasure, from the hero's hand The shining scourge. It fell, and to his eyes Started indignant tears; for now he saw The others gaining on him, while the speed Of his own steeds, which feared the lash no more, 47s Was slackened. Yet Apollo's stratagem i3• Page 298 298 The Iliad. Was not unseen by Pallas, who o'ertook The shepherd of the people, and restored The scourge he dropped, and put into his steeds New spirit. In her anger she approached «•, Eumelus, snapped his yoke, and caused his mares To start asunder from the track; the pole Was dashed into the ground, and from the seat The chief was flung beside the wheel, his mouth, Elbows, and nostrils torn, his forehead bruised. *s Grief filled his eyes with tears and choked his voice, While Diomed drave by his firm-paced steeds, Outstripping all the rest; for Pallas nerved Their limbs with vigor, and bestowed on him Abundant glory. After him the son Of Atreus, fair-haired Menelaus, came, While Nestor's son cheered on his father's steeds :— "On, on! press onward with your utmost speed! Not that I bid you strive against the steeds Of warlike Diomed, for Pallas gives «s Swiftness to them and glory to the man Who holds the reins; but let us overtake The horses of Atrides, nor submit • To be thus distanced, lest the victory Of the mare /Ethe cover you with shame. s~ Fleet as ye are, why linger? This at least I tell you, and my words will be fulfilled: Look not for kindly care at Nestor's hands, That shepherd of the people, but for death With the sharp steel, if through your fault we take m Page 299 Book XXIII. 299 A meaner prize. Then onward and away, With all your strength, for this is my design, — To pass by Menelaus where the way Is narrow, and he cannot thwart my plan." He spake, and they who feared their master's threat s™ Mended their speed awhile. The warlike son Of Nestor saw just then the narrow pass Within the hollow way, a furrow ploughed By winter floods, which there had torn the course And deepened it. Atrides, to avoid sis The clash of wheels, drave thither; thither too Antilochus — who turned his firm-paced steeds A little from the track in which they ran — Followed him close. Atrides saw with fear, And shouted to Antilochus aloud :— s*, "Antilochus, thou drivest rashly; rein Thy horses in. The way is narrow here, But soon will broaden, and thou then canst pass. Beware lest with thy chariot-wheels thou dash Against my own, and harm befall us both." v- He spake; but all the more Antilochus Urged on his coursers with the lash, as if He had not heard. As far as flies a quoit Thrown from the shoulder of a vigorous youth Who tries his strength, so far they ran abreast . s30 The horses of Atrides then fell back; He slacked the reins; for much he feared the steeds Would dash against each other in the way, Page 300 300 The Iliad. And overturn the sumptuous cars, and fling The charioteers contending for the prize Upon the dusty track. With angry words The fair-haired Menelaus chided thus: — "Antilochus, there is no man so prone As thou to mischief, and we greatly err, We Greeks, who call thee wise. Go now, and yet Thou shalt not take the prize without an oath." s»» Again he spake, encouraging his steeds: "Check not your speed, nor sorrowfully stand: Their feet and knees will fail with weariness Before your own; they are no longer young." ms He spake; the coursers, honoring his voice. Ran with fresh speed, and soon were near to those Of Nestor's son. Meantime the assembled Greeks Sat looking where the horses scoured the plain And filled the air with dust. Idomeneus, w, The lord of Crete, descried the coursers first, For on a height he sat above the crowd. He heard the chief encouraging his steeds, And knew him, and he marked before the rest A courser, chestnut-colored save a spot sss Upon the middle of the forehead, white, And round as the full moon. And then he stood Upright, and from his place harangued the Greeks:— "O friends, the chiefs and leaders of the Greeks, Am I the sole one that descries the steeds, s*, Or do ye also? Those who lead the race, I think, are not the same, and with them comes Page 301 Book xxnr. 301 A different charioteer. The mares, which late Were foremost, may have somewhere come to harm. I saw them first to turn the goal, and now s«3 I can no more discern them, though my sight Sweeps the whole Trojan plain from side to side. Either the charioteer has dropped the reins, And could not duly round the goal, or else Met with disaster at the turn, o'erthrown, s70 His chariot broken, and the affrighted mares Darting, unmastered, madly from the way. But rise: look forth yourselves. I cannot well Discern, but think the charioteer is one Who, born of an ^Etolian stock, commands s7s Among the Argives, —valiant Diomed, A son of Tydeus, tamer of wild steeds." And Ajax, swift of foot, O.leus* son, Answered with bitter words: "Idomeneus, Why this perpetual prating? Faraway s*, The mares with rapid hoofs are traversing The plain, and thou art not the youngest here Among the Argives, nor hast such sharp eyes Beneath thy brows, yet must thou chatter still. Among thy betters here it ill becomes #s A man like thee to be so free of tongue. The coursers of Eumelus, which at first Outran the rest, are yet before them all, And he is drawing near and holds the reins." The Cretan leader angrily rejoined: "Ajax, thou railer, first in brawls, yet known Page 302 302 The Iliad. As in all else below the other Greeks, A man of brutal mood, come, let us stake A tripod or a caldron, and appoint As umpire Agamemnon, to decide sw Which horses are the foremost in the race, That when thou losest thou mayst be convinced." He spake: Oilean Ajax, swift of foot, Started in anger from his seat, to cast Reproaches back, and long and fierce had been » The quarrel if Achilles had not risen, And said: "No longer let this strife go on, Idomeneus and Ajax! Ill such words Become you; ye would blame in other men What now ye do. Sit then among the rest, «oj And watch the race; for soon the charioteers Contending for the victory will be here, And each of you —for well ye know the steeds Of the Greek chieftains — for himself will see Whose hold the second place, and whose are first.™ He spake: Tydides rapidly drew near, «« Lashing the shoulders of his steeds, and they Seemed in the air as, to complete the course, They flew along, and flung the dust they trod Back on the charioteer. All bright with tin «1s And gold, the car rolled after them; its tires Made but a slender trace in the light dust, So rapidly they ran. And now he stopped Within the circle, while his steeds were steeped In sweat, that fell in drops from neck and breast. «*, This page contains an image. Page 303 Book XX JII. 3°3 Then from his shining seat he leaped, and laid His scourge against the yoke. Brave Sthenelus Came forward, and at once received the prize For Diomed, and bade his comrades lead The maid away, and in their arms bear off The tripod, while himself unyoked the steeds. Next the Neleian chief, Antilochus, Came with his coursers. More by fraud than speed He distanced Menelaus, yet that chief Drave his fleet horses near him. Just so far *m As runs the wheel behind a steed that draws His master swiftly o'er the plain, his tail Touching the tire with its long hairs, and small The space between them as the spacious plain Is traversed, Menelaus just so far as Was distanced by renowned Antilochus. For though at first he fell as far behind As a quoit's cast, yet was he gaining ground Rapidly, now that Agamemnon's mare, JE\\\h the stately maned, increased her speed, **, And Menelaus, had the race for both Been longer, would have passed his rival by, Nor left the victory doubtful. After him, A spear's throw distant, came Meriones, The gallant comrade of Idomeneus, «4s Whose full-maned steeds were slower than the rest, And he unskilled in contests such as these. And last of all Eumelus came. He drew His showy chariot after him, and drave Page 304 304 The Iliad. His steeds before him. Great Achilles saw a* With pity, and from where he stood among The Greeks aduressed him thus with wingd words: — "The ablest horseman brings his steeds the last, But let us, as is just, confer on him The second prize; Tydides takes the first." «ss He spake, and all approved his words; and now The mare, to please the Greeks, had been bestowed Upon Eumelus, if Antilochus, Son of magnanimous Nestor, had not risen To plead for justice with Achilles thus :— «0 "Achilles, I shall deem it grave offence If thou fulfil thy word; for thou wilt take My prize, because thou seest that this man's car And his fleet steeds have suffered injury, Though he be skilful. Yet he should have prayed To the good gods; then had he not been seen om Bringing his steeds the last. But if thou feel Compassion for him, and if so thou please, Large store of brass and gold is in thy tent, And thine are cattle, and handmaidens thine, «»o And firm-paced steeds; hereafter give of these A nobler largess, or bestow it now, And hear the Greeks applaud thee. But this prize I yield not; let the warrior who may claim To take it try with me his strength of arm." »7s He ceased : the noble son of Peleus smiled, And, pleased to see Antilochus succeed, — Page 305 Book xxnr. 30s For he was a beloved friend, — he spake These winged words: "Since, then, Antiiochus, Thou wilt that I bestow some recompense «* Upo:i Eumelus from my store, I give The brazen corselet which my arm in war Took from Asteropaaus, edged around With shining tin, —a gift of no mean price." He ceased, and sent his friend Automedon at To bring it from the tent. He went and brought The corselet, and Eumelus joyfully Received it from Achilles. Then arose, Among them Menelaus, ill at ease, And angry with Antiiochus. He took »* The sceptre from a herald's hand, who hushed The crowd to silence, and the hero spake :— "Antiiochus, who wert till now discreet, What hast thou done? Thou hast disgraced my skill And wronged my steeds by thrusting in thine own, «n Which were less fleet, before them. Now, ye chiefs And leaders of the Achaians, judge between This man and me, and judge impartially, Lest that some warrior of the Greeks should say That Menelaus, having overcome 700 Antiiochus by falsehood, led away The mare a prize; for his were slower steeds, But he the mightier man m feats of arms. Nay, I myself will judge; and none of all The Greeks will censure me, for what I do t0i T Page 306 306 The Iliad. Will be but just. Antilochus, step forth, Illustrious as thou art, and in due form, Standing before thy horses and thy car, And taking in thy hand the pliant scourge Which thou just now hast wielded, touch thy steeds, And swear by Neptune, whose embrace surrounds 71, The earth, that thou hast wittingly employed No stratagem to break my chariot's speed." And thus discreet Antilochus replied: "Have patience with me: I am younger far m Than thou, King Menelaus; thou art both My elder and my better. Thou dost know The faults to which the young are ever prone; The will is quick to act, the judgment weak. Bear with me then. The mare which I received r» I cheerfully make over to thy hands. And if thou wilt yet more of what I have, I give it willingly and instantly, Rather, O loved of Jove, than lose a place In thy good-will, and sin against the gods." 7»s The son of large-souled Nestor, speaking thus, Led forth the mare, and gave her to the hand Of Menelaus, o'er whose spirit came A gladness. As upon a field of wheat Bristling with ears gathers the freshening dew, i*, So was his spirit gladdened iu his breast, And he bespake the youth with winged words : — "Antilochus, now shall my anger cease, For hitherto thou hast not shown thyself Page 307 Book XXIII. 307 Foolish or fickle, though the heat of youth ns Just now hath led thee wrong. In time to come, Beware to practise stealthy arts on men Of higher rank than thou. No other Greek Would easily have made his peace with me. But thou hast suffered much, and much hast done, — Thou, and thy worthy father, and his son, iv Thy brother, — for my sake. I therefore yield To thy petition; yet I give to thee The mare, though mine she be, that these who stand Around us may perceive that I am not 74s Of unforgiving or unyielding mood." He spake, and to Noemon gave the mare,— Noemon, comrade of Antilochus, — To lead her thence, while for himself he took The shining caldron. Then Meriones, w, Fourth in the race, received the prize of gold, — Two talents. But the fifth prize and the last, The double goblet, still was left unclaimed; And this Achilles carried through the crowd Of Greeks, and placed in Nestor's hands, and said:— 73s "Receive thou this, O ancient man, to keep In memory of the funeral honors paid Patroclus, whom thou never more shalt see Among the Greeks. I give this prize, which thou Hast not contended for, since thou wilt wield 7 No more the cestus, nor wilt wrestle more, Nor hurl the javelin at the mark, nor join Page 308 3o8 The Iliad. The foot-race; age lies heavy on thy limbs." He spake, and gave the prize, which Nestor took, Well pleased, and thus with winged words re- plied :— 7«s "Son, thou hast spoken rightly, for these limbs Are strong no longer; neither feet nor hands Move on each side with vigor as of yore. Would I were but as young, with strength as great, As when the Epeians in Buprasium laid ttc King Amarynceus in the sepulchre, And funeral games were offered by his sons 1 Then of the Epeians there was none like me. Nor of the Pylian youths, nor yet among The brave /Etolians. In the boxing-match 77s I took the prize from Clytomedes, son Of Enops, and in wrestling overcame Ancaeus the Pleuronian, who rose up Against me. In the foot-race I outstripped, Fleet as he was, Iphiclus, and beyond Phyleus and Polydore I threw the spear. Only the sons of Actor won the race Against me with their chariot, and they won Through force of numbers. Much they envied me, And feared lest I should bear away the prize; tn For largest in that contest of the steeds Was the reward, and they were two, — one held, Steadily held, the reins, the other swung The lash. Such was I once. Now feats like these Belong to other, younger men, and I, 790 Page 309 Book XXIII. 309 Though eminent among the heroes once, Must do as sad old age admonishes. Go thou, and honor thy friend's funeral With games. Thy gift I willingly accept, Rejoicing that thy thoughts revert to one it* Who loves thee, and that thou forgettest net To pay the honor due to me among The Greeks. The gods will give thee thy reward." He ceased. The son of Peleus, having heard This praise from Nestor, left him, and passed through soo The mighty concourse of the Greeks. He laid Before them prizes for the difficult strife Between the boxers. To the middle space He led a mule, and bound him, six years old And strong for toil, unbroken and most hard *a To break, while to the vanquished he assigned A goblet. Rising, he addressed the host:— "Ye sons of Atreus and ye well-armed Greeks, We call for two of the most skilled to strive For these, by striking with the lifted fist;' >•0 And he to whom Apollo shall decree The victory, acknowledged by you all, Shall have this sturdy mule to lead away. The vanquished takes this goblet as his meed.* He spake. A warrior strong and huge of limb, Skilled in the cestus, named Epeius, son em Of Panopeus, rose at the word, and laid His hand upon the sturdy mule, and said :—- Page 310 The Iliad. "Let him appear whose lot will be to take The goblet. No man of the Grecian host •« Will get the mule by overcoming me In combat with the cestus, — so I deem. In that I claim to be the best man here. And should it not suffice that in the war Others surpass me? All cannot excel s In everything alike. I promise this, And shall fulfil my word, —that I will crush His body, and will break his bones. His frien" Should all remain upon the ground to bear Their comrade off when beaten by my hand." «*, He spake, and all were silent. Only rose Euryalus, whose father was the king Mecisteus of Talaion's line, the same Who went to Thebes and overcame, of old, In all the funeral games of CEdipus, sss The sons of Cadmus. To Euryalus Came Diomed, the spearman, bidding him Expect the victory which he greatly wished His friend might gain. Around his waist he drew A girdle, adding straps that from the hide «40 Of a wild bull were cut with dextrous care. And, fully now arrayed, the twain stepped forth Into the middle space, and both began The combat. Lifting their strong arms, they brought Their heavy hands together. Fearfully Was heard the crash of jaws; from every- limb Page 311 Book XXIII. 3t1 The sweat was streaming. As Euryalus Looked round, his noble adversary sprang And smote him on the cheek, — too rude a blow To be withstood; his shapely limbs gave way «s» Beneath him. As upon the weedy shore, When the fresh north wind stirs the water's face, A fish leaps forth to light, and then again The dark wave covers it, so sprang and fell The chief. Magnanimous Epeius gave s« His hands and raised him up; his friends came round And led him thence with dragging feet, and head That drooped from side to side, while from his mouth Came clotted blood. They placed him in the midst, Unconscious still, and sent and took the cup. st» Then, third in order, for the wrestling-match The son of Peleus brought and showed the Greeks Yet other prizes. To the conqueror A tripod for the hearth, of ample size, He offered; twice six oxen, as the Greeks «.% Esteemed it, were its price. And next he placed In view a damsel for the vanquished, trained In household arts; four beeves were deemed her price. Then rose Achilles, and addressed the Greeks: "Ye who would try your fortune in this strife, e,-o Arise." He spake, and mighty Ajax rose, The son of Telamon, and after him Page 312 3i2 The Iliad. The wise Ulysses, trained to stratagems. They, girding up their loins, came forth and stood In the mid space, and there with vigorous arms «rs They clasped each other, locked like rafters framed By some wise builder for the lofty roof Of a great mansion proof against the winds. Then their backs creaked beneath the powerful strain Of their strong hands; the sweat ran down their limbs; «*• Large whelks upon their sides and shoulders rose, Crimson with blood. Still eagerly they strove For victory and the tripod. Yet in vain Ulysses labored to supplant his foe, And throw him to the ground, and equally », Did Ajax strive in vain, for with sheer strength Ulysses foiled his efforts. When they saw That the Greeks wearied of the spectacle, The mighty Telamonian Ajax said : —- "Son of Laertes, nobly born and trained » To wise expedients, lift me up, or I Will lift up thee; and leave the rest to Jove." He spake, and raised Ulysses from the ground, Who dealt, with ready stratagem, a blow Upon the ham of Ajax, and the limb »k Gave way; the hero fell upon his back, And on his breast Ulysses, while the host Stood wondering and amazed. Ulysses strove, In turn, to lift his rival, but prevailed Page 313 Book XXIII. 313 Only to move him from his place; he caught 990 The knee of Ajax in his own, and both Came to the ground together, soiled with dust. They rose to wrestle still, but from his seat Achilles started, and forbade them thus : — "Contend no longer, nor exhaust your strength 90s With struggling; there is victory for both, And equal prizes. Now depart, and leave The field of contest to the other Greeks." He spake: they listened and obeyed, and wiped The dust away, and put their garments on. «i0 And then the son of Peleus placed in sight Prizes of swiftness, — a wrought silver cup That held six measures, and in beauty far Excelled all others known; the cunning hands Of the Sidonian artisans had given 9is Its graceful shape, and over the dark sea Men of Phoenicia brought it, with their wares, To the Greek harbors; they bestowed it there On Thoas. Afterward Euneiis, son Of Jason, gave it to the hero-chief, s,» Patroclus, to redeem a captive friend, Lycaon, Priam's son. Achilles now Brought it before the assembly as a prize, For which, in honor of the friend he loved, The swiftest runners of the host should strive. « Next, for the second in the race, he showed A noble fatling ox; and for the last, Gold, half a talent. Then he stood and said vol. 11. 14 Page 314 3i4 The Iliad. To the Achaians: "Those who would contend For these rewards, rise up." And then arose 930 Oilean Ajax, fleet of foot; and next Ulysses the sagacious; last upstood Antilochus, the son of Nestor, known As swiftest of the youths. In due array They stood; Achilles showed the goal. At once 93s Forward they sprang. Oilean Ajax soon Gained on the rest, but close behind him ran The great Ulysses. As a shapely maid Flinging the shuttle draws with careful hand The thread that fills the warp, and so brings near »*> The shuttle to her bosom, just so near To Ajax ran Ulysses, in the prints Made by his rival's feet, before the dust Fell back upon them. As he ran, his breath Smote on the head of Ajax. All the Greeks «■ Shouted applause to him, encouraging His ardor for the victory; but when now They neared the goal, Ulysses silently Prayed thus to Pallas: "Goddess, hear my prayer, And help these feet to win.'' The goddess heard, And lightened all his limbs, his feet, his hands; 9s1 And just as they were rushing on the prize, Ajax, in running, slipped and fell — the work Of Pallas — where in heaps the refuse lay From entrails of the bellowing oxen slain 9ss In honor of Patroclus by the hand Of swift Achilles. Mouth and nostrils both Page 315 Book XXIII. Were choked with filth. The much-enduring man Ulysses, coming first, received the cup, While Ajax took the ox, and as he stood 9, Holding the animal's horn and spitting forth The dirt, he said to those around: "T is plain The goddess caused my feet to slide; she aids Ulysses like a mother." So he said, And the Greeks laughed. And then Antilochus tfs Received the third reward, and with a smile Said to the Greeks: "I tell you all, my friends, What you must know already, that the gods Honor the aged ever. Ajax stands Somewhat in years above me, but this chief m Who takes the prize is of a former age And earlier race of men; they call him old, But hard it were for any Greek to vie With him in swiftness, save Achilles here." Such praise he gave Pelides, fleet of foot, Who answered: "Thy good word, Antilochus, Shall not be vainly spoken. I will add Yet half a talent to thy gold." He said, And gave the gold; Antilochus, well pleased, Received it. Then Pelides brought a spear s*, Of ponderous length into the middle space, And laid it down, and placed a buckler near And helmet, which hail been Sarpedon's arms, And which Patroclus won of him in war. Then stood Achilles and addressed the Greeks : — "I call on two, the bravest of the host, *» Page 316 316 The Iliad. To arm themselves and take their spears in hand, And in a contest for these weapons put Each other to the proof. Whoever first Shall wound his adversary, piercing through **, The armor to the delicate skin beneath, And draw the crimson blood, to him I give This beautiful sword of Thrace, with silver studs, Won from Asteropaeus. And let both Bear off these arms, a common gift, and both ws Shall sit and banquet nobly in my tent." He spake, and Telamonian Ajax rose, The large of limb; Tydides Diomed, The strong, rose also. When they had put on Their arms apart from all the host, they came, i00o All eager for the combat, to the lists, And fearful was their aspect. All the Greeks Looked on with dread and wonder, and when now Stood face to face the warriors, thrice they rushed Against each other; thrice they dealt their blows. i90s Then Ajax thrust through Diomed's round shield His weapon, but it wounded not; the mail Beyond it stopped the stroke. Tydides aimed Over his adversary's mighty shield A blow to reach his neck. The Greeks, alarmed ,oio For Ajax, shouted that the strife should cease, And both divide the prize. Achilles heard, But gave to Diomed the ponderous sword, Its sheath, and the fair belt from which it hung. Again Pelides placed before the host 101s Page 317 Book XXIII. 3i7 A mass of iron, shapeless from the forge, Which once the strong Eetion used to hurl; But swift Achilles, when he took his life, Brought it with other booty in his ships To Troas. Rising, he addressed the Greeks : — ,«,, "Stand forth, whoever will contend for this, And if broad fields and rich be his, this mass Will last him many years. The man who tends His flocks, or guides his plough, need not be sent To town for iron; he will have it here." ««»s He spake, and warlike Polypoetes rose. Uprose the strong Leonteus, who in form Was like a god. The son of Telamon Rose also, and Epeius nobly born; Each took his place. Epeius seized the mass, 103. And sent it whirling. All the Achaians laughed. The loved of Mars, Leonteus, flung it next, And after him the son of Telamon, The large-limbed Ajax, from his vigorous arm Sent it beyond the mark of both. But when iom The sturdy warrior Polypoetes took The mass in hand, as far as o'er his beeves A herdsman sends his whirling staff, so far This cast outdid the rest. A shout arose; The friends of sturdy Polypoetes took to*, The prize, and bore it to the hollow ships. Achilles for the archers brought forth steel, Tempered for arrow-heads, — ten axes, each With double edge, and single axes ten, — Page 318 3«8 The Iliad. And from a galley's azure prow took off >,* A mast, and reared it on the sands afar, And, tying to its summit by the foot A timorous dove, he bade them aim at her: "Whoever strikes the bird shall bear away The double axes to his tent; while he »so Who hits the cord, but not the bird, shall take The single axes, as the humbler prize." He ceased, and then arose the stalwart king, Teucer; then also rose Meriones, The valiant comrade of Idomeneus. «css The lots were shaken in a brazen helm, And Teucer's lot was first. He straightway sent A shaft with all his strength, but made no vow Of a choice hecatomb of firstling lambs To Phoebus, monarch-god. He missed the bird, 10«0 Such was the will of Phoebus, but he struck, Close to her foot, the cord that made her fast. The keen shaft severed it; the dove flew up Into the heavens; the fillet dropped to earth Amid the loud applauses of the Greeks. i»es And then Meriones made haste to take The bow from Teucer's hand. Long time he held. The arrow aimed, the while he made a vow To Phoebus, the great archer, promising A chosen hecatomb of firstling lambs; Then, looking toward the dove, as high in air She wheeled beneath the clouds, he pierced her breast Page 319 Book XXIII. 319 Beneath the wing; the shaft went through and fell, Fixed in the ground, beside Meriones, While the bird settled on the galley's mast •07s With drooping head and open wings. The breath Forsook her soon, and down from that high perch She fell to earth. The people all looked on, Admiring and amaze-d. Meriones Took up the double axes as his prize, i0, While Teucer bore the others to the fleet. And then Pelides brought into the midst A ponderous spear, and laid a caldron down Which never felt the fire, inwrought with flowers, Its price an ox. And then the spearmen rose. i«s Atrides Agamemnon, mighty king, First rose, and after him Meriones, The brave companion of Idomeneus; And thus to both the swift Achilles said:— "O son of Atreus, for we know how far ",» Thou dost excel all others, and dost cast The spear with passing strength and skill, bear thou This prize, as victor, to the roomy ships, And if it please thee, let us, as I wish, Give to our brave Meriones the spear." i«n He spake, and Agamemnon, king of men, Complied, and gave Meriones in hand The brazen spear, while to Talthybius, .. The herald, he consigned the greater prize.

XXIV

.

THE assembly was dissolved, the people all Dispersed to their swift galleys, and prepared With food and gentle slumber to refresh Their wearied frames. But still Achilles wept, Remembering his dear comrade. Sleep, whose sway . s Is over all, came not; he turned and tossed, Still yearning for his strong and valiant friend Patroclus. All that they had ever done Together, all the hardships they had borne, The battles fought with heroes, the wild seas «■ O'erpassed, came thronging on his memory. He shed warm tears, as now upon his sides, Now on his back, now on his face he lay. Then, starting from his couch, he wandered forth In sorrow by the margin of the deep. u Nor did the morn that rose o'er sea and shore Dawn unperceived by him; for then he yoked His fleet steeds to the chariot, and made fast The corse of Hector, that it might be dragged After the wheels. Three times around the tomb •0 Of Menoetiades he dragged the slain, Then turned and sought his tent, again to rest, And left him there stretched out amid the dust With the face downward. Yet Apollo, moved Page 321 Book XXIV. 32t With pity for the hero, kept him free ,s From soil or stain, though dead, and o'er him held The golden aegis, lest, when roughly dragged , Along the ground, the body might be torn. So in his anger did Achilles treat Unworthily the noble Hector's corse. *, The blessed gods themselves with pity looked Upon the slain, and bade the vigilant one, The Argus-queller, bear him thence by stealth. This counsel pleased the immortals all, except Juno and Neptune and the blue-eyed maid, c And these persisted in their wrath. To them Ilium, the hallowed city, and its king, Priam, and all his people, from the first Were hateful; 't was for Alexander's fault, Affronting the two goddesses what time *, They sought his cottage, and preferring her Who ministered to his calamitous love. But now, when the twelfth morning from that day Arose, Apollo spake among the gods : — "Cruel are ye, O gods, and prone to wrong. « For was not Hector wont before your shrines To burn the thighs of chosen bulls and goats? And now that he is dead ye venture not To rescue him, and let his wife and son And mother and King Priam look again y, Upon his face. Soon would they light the pile, And burn the dead, and pay the funeral rite. Ye seek to favor, O ye gods, that pest 14* u Page 322 322 The Iliad. Achilles, in whose breast there dwells no love Of justice, nor a temper to be moved By prayers, but who delights in savage deeds. And as a lion, conscious of vast strength And scornful of resistance, falls upon The shepherd's flock, and slays for his repast, Thus with Achilles neither mercy dwells Nor shame, which often profits, often harms Mankind. For when another man has met A greater grief than he, — has lost, perchance, A brother or a son, — he dries at length His tears, and ceases to lament; for fate Bestows the power to suffer patiently. But this Achilles, after he has spoiled The godlike Hector of his life in war, Hath bound him to his chariot, and hath dragged The corse around his dear companion's tomb. Unseemly is the deed, and small will be The good it brings him. Brave although he be. We may be angry with him when he thus Insults a portion of insensible earth." The white-armed Juno was incensed, and spake "So mightst thou say, God of the silver bow, Were equal honor to Achilles due And Hector. Hector is a mortal man, And suckled at a woman's breast. Not so Achilles; he was born of one of us, A goddess whom I nurtured and brought up And gave to Peleus. Ye were present all, Page 323 Book XXIV. 323 Ye gods, when they were wedded. Thou wert there To share the marriage banquet, harp in hand, Thou plotter with the vile, thou faithless one!" «s Then answered cloud-compelling Jove, and said: "Let not thy anger rise against the gods, O Juno, for the honor of the chiefs Shall not be equal. Yet of all the race Of mortals dwelling in the city of Troy m Was Hector dearest to the gods; to me He ever was; and never did he fail To offer welcome gifts. My altar ne'er Lacked fitting feast, libation, and the fume Of incense, — hallowed rites which are our due. m Yet seek we not to steal away the corse Of valiant Hector; that we could not do Without his slayer's knowledge, who by night And day is ever near to him and keeps Watch o'er him like a mother. Let some god •«» Call hither Thetis. I will counsel her Prudently, that Achilles may receive Ransom from Priam, and restore his son." He ceased, and with the swiftness of the storm Rose Iris up, to be his messenger. 103 Half way 'twixt Samos and the rugged coast Of Imbrus down she plunged to the dark sea, Entering the deep with noise. Far down she sank As sinks the ball of lead, that, sliding o'er A wild bull's horn, bears into ocean's depths no Death to the greedy fishes. There she found Page 324 324 The Iliad. Thetis within her roomy cave, among The goddesses of ocean, seated round In full assembly. Thetis in the midst Bewailed the fate of her own blameless SOn, r»s About to perish on the fertile soil Of Troy, and far from Greece. The swift of w ing, Iris, approached her and addressed her thus : — "Arise, O Thetis. Father Jupiter, Whose counsel stands forever, sends for thee." » And silver-footed Thetis answered him: "Why should that potent deity require My presence, who have many griefs, and shrink From mingling with immortals? Yet I go, Perforce, for never doth he speak in vain." ,•s So spake the goddess-queen, and, speaking, took Her mantle, — darker web was never worn, — And onward went. Wind-footed Iris led The way; the waters of the sea withdrew On either side. They climbed the steepy shore, And took their way to heaven. They found the son Of Saturn, him of the far-sounding voice, With all the blessed, ever-living gods Assembled round him. Close to Father Jove She took her seat, for Pallas yielded it, 'is And Juno put a beautiful cup of gold Into her hand, and spake consoling words. She drank and gave it back, and thus began The father of immortals and of men :— "Thou comest to Olympus, though in grief, tm Page 325 Book XXIV. 325 O goddess Thetis, and I know the cause That makes thee sad and will not from thy thoughts; Yet let me now declare why I have called Thee hither. For nine days the immortal gods Have been at strife concerning Hector's corse us And Peleus' son, the spoiler. They have asked The vigilant Argus-queller to remove The dead by stealth. But I must yet bestow Fresh honor on Achilles, and thus keep Thy love and reverence. Now descend at once ,s» Into the camp and carry to thy son My message: say that it offends the gods, And me the most, that in his spite he keeps The corse of Hector at the beaked ships, Refusing to restore it. He perchance 1ss Will listen, and, revering me, give back The slain. And I will send a messenger, Iris, to large-souled Priam, bidding him Hasten in person to the Grecian fleet, To ransom his beloved son, and bring no Achilles gifts that shall appease his rage." He spake: the goddess of the silver feet, Thetis, obeyed, and with precipitate flight Descended from the mountain-peaks. She came To her son's tent, and found him uttering moans i«s Continually, while his beloved friends Were busy round him; they prepared a feast, And had just slain within the tent a ewe Of ample size and fleece. She took her seat ,«» Page 326 The Iliad. Beside her son, and smoothed his brow, and said :— "How long, my son, wilt thou lament and grieve And pine at heart, abstaining from the feast And from thy couch? Yet well it is to seek A woman's love. Thy life will not be spared Long time to me, for death and cruel fate to Stand near thee. Listen to me; I am come A messenger from Jove, who bids me say The immortals are offended, and himself The most, that thou shouldst in thy spite detain The corse of Hector at the beaked ships, a» Refusing its release. Comply thou then, And take the ransom and restore the dead." And thus Achilles, swift of foot, replied: "Let him who brings the ransom come and take The body, if it be the will of Jove." iss Thus did the mother and the son confer Among the galleys, and between them passed Full many a winged word, while Saturn's son Bade Iris go with speed to sacred Troy: — "Fleet Iris, haste thee. Leave the Olympian seats, ,»» And send magnanimous Priam to the fleet, To ransom his dear son, and bear him back To Ilium. Let him carry gifts to calm The anger of Achilles. He should go Alone, no Trojan with him, save a man ns In years, a herald, who may guide the mules And strong-wheeled chariot, harnessed to bear back Page 327 Book XXIV. 327 Him whom the great Achilles has o'erthrown; And let him fear not death nor other harm, For we will send a guide to lead him safe, «» The Argus-queller, till he stand beside Achilles; and when once he comes within The warrior's tent, Achilles will not raise His hand to slay, but will restrain the rest. Nor mad, nor rash, nor criminal is he, »0s And will humanely spare a suppliant man." He spake, and Iris, the swift messenger, Whose feet are like the wind, went forth with speed, And came to Priam's palace, where she found Sorrow and wailing. Round the father sat «» His sons within the hall, and steeped with tears Their garments. In the midst the aged man Sat with a cloak wrapped round him, and much dust Strewn on his head and neck, which, when he rollcd Upon the earth, he gathered with his hands. tis His daughters and the consorts of his sons Filled with their cries the mansion, sorrowing For those, the many and brave, who now lay slain By Grecian hands. The ambassadress of Jove Stood beside Priam, and in soft, low tones, «« While his limbs shook with fear, addressed him thus: — "Be comforted, and have no fear; for I Am come, Dardanian Priam, not to bring Mischief, but blessing. I am sent to thee A messenger from Jove, who, though afar, «s Page 328 328 The Iliad. Pities thee and will aid thee. He who rules Olympus bids thee ransom thy slain son, The noble Hector, carrying gifts to calm The anger of Achilles. Thou shouldst go Alone, no Trojan with thee, save a man r» In years, a herald, who shall guide the mules And strong-wheeled chariot, harnessed to bring back Him whom the great Achilles has o'erthrown. And have no fear of death or other harm; A guide shall go with thee to lead thee safe, *ss The Argus-queller, till thou stand beside Achilles, and when once thou art within The warrior's tent, Achilles will not raise His hand to slay, but will restrain the rest. He is not mad, nor rash, nor prone to crime, f And will humanely spare a suppliant man." Thus the swift-footed Iris spake, and then Departed. Priam bade his sons prepare The strong-wheeled chariot, drawn by mules, and bind A coffer on it. He descended next ms Into a fragrant chamber, cedar-lined, High-roofed, and stored with many things of price, And calling Hecuba, his wife, he said : — "Dear wife, a message from Olympian Jove Commands that I betake me to the fleet, 0s0 And thence redeem my slaughtered son with gifts That may appease Achilles. Tell me now How this may seem to thee? for I am moved Page 329 Book XXIV. 329 By a strong impulse to approach the ships, And venture into the great Grecian camp." »ss He spake: his consort wept, and answered thus: "Ah me! the prudence which was once so praised By strangers and by those who own thy sway, Where is it now? Why wouldst thou go alone To the Greek fleet, to meet the eye of him *0 Who slew so many of thy gallant sons? An iron heart is thine. If that false man, Remorseless as he is, should see thee there And seize thee, neither pity nor respect Hast thou to hope from him. Let us lament *t Our Hector in these halls. A cruel fate Spun, when I brought him forth, his thread of life, — That far from us his corse should feed the hounds Near that fierce man, whose liver I could tear From out his bosom. Then the indignities »7» Done to my son would be repaid, for he Was slain, not shunning combat, coward-like, But fighting to defend the men of Troy And the deep-bosomed Trojan dames. He fell Without a thought of flight or of retreat." »7s And thus the aged, godlike king rejoined: "Keep me not back from going, nor be thou A bird of evil omen in these halls, For thou shalt not persuade me. This I say: If any of the dwellers of the earth, a, Soothsayer, seer, or priest, had said to me What I have heard, I well might deem the words Page 330 330 The Iliad. A lie, and heed them not. But since I heard Myself the mandate from a deity, And saw her face to face, I certainly m Will go, nor shall the message be in vain. And should it be my fate to perish there Beside the galleys of the mail-clad Greeks, So be it; for Achilles will forthwith Put me to death embracing my poor son, *r And satisfying my desire to weep." He spake, and, raising the fair coffer-lids, Took out twelve robes of state most beautiful, Twelve single cloaks, as many tapestried mats, And tunics next and mantles twelve of each, 0« And ten whole talents of pure gold, which first He weighed. Two burnished tripods from his store He added, and four goblets and a cup Of eminent beauty, which the men of Thrace Gave him when, as an envoy to their coast, »™ He came from Troy, — a sumptuous gift, and yet The aged king reserved not even this To deck his palace, such was his desire To ransom his dear son. And then he drave Away the Trojans hovering round his porch, sos Rebuking them with sharp and bitter words :— "Hence with you, worthless wretches! have ye not Sorrow enough at home, that ye are come To vex me thus? Or doth it seem to you Of little moment, that Saturnian Jove s» Page 331 Book XXIV. 331 Hath sent such grief upon me in the loss Of my most valiant son? Ye yet will know How great that loss has been; for it will be A lighter task for the beleaguering Greeks To work our ruin, now that he is dead. 3,s But I shall sink to Hades ere mine eyes Behold the city sacked and made a spoil." He spake, and with his staff he chased away The loiterers; forth before the aged man They went . With like harsh words he chid his sons. Helenus, Paris, noble Agathon, v Pammon, Antiphonus, Deiphobus, Polites, great in war, Hippothoiis, And gallant Dios, nine in all he called, And thus bespake them with reproachful words : — "Make haste, ye idle fellows, my disgrace! 3* Would ye had all been slain beside the fleet Instead of Hector! Woe is me! the most Unhappy of mankind am I, who had The bravest sons in all the town of Troy, o, And none of them, I think, are left to me. Mestor, divine in presence, Troilus, The gallant knight, and Hector, he who looked A god among his countrymen, — no son Of man he seemed, but of immortal birth, — 33s Those Mars has slain, but these who are my shame Remain, — these liars, dancers, excellent In choirs, whose trade is public robbery Of lambs and kids. Why haste ye not to get Page 332 332 The Iliad. My chariot ready, and bestow these things w, Within it, that my journey may begin?" He spake, and they, in fear of his rebuke, Lifted from out its place the strong-wheeled car, Framed to be drawn by mules, and beautiful, And newly built, and on it they made fast ws The coffer. From its pin they next took down The boxwood mule-yoke, fitted well with rings, And carved with a smooth boss. With this they brought A yoke-band nine ells long, which carefully Adjusting to the polished pole's far end, 3s» They cast the ring upon the bolt, and thrice Wound the long band on each side of the bolt Around the yoke, and made it fast, and turned The loose ends under. Then they carried forth The treasures that should ransom Hector's corse; « And having piled them in the polished car, They yoked the hardy, strong-hoofed mules which once The Mysians gave to Priam, princely gifts. To bear the yoke of Priam they led forth The horses which the aged man himself 3, Fed at the polished manger. These the king Yoked, aided by the herald, while in mind, Within the palace court, they both revolved Their prudent counsels. Hecuba, the queen, Came to them in deep sorrow. In her hand *s She bore a golden cup of delicate wine, Page 333 Book XXIV. 333 That they might make libations and depart. She stood before the steeds, and thus she spake :— "Take this, and pour to Father Jove, and pray That thou mayst safely leave the enemy's camp r.* For home, since't is thy will, though I dissuade, To go among the ships. Implore thou then The god of Ida and the gatherer Of the black tempest, Saturn's son, who looks Down on all Troy, to send his messenger, 3rs His swift and favorite bird, of matchless strength, On thy right hand, that, with thine eye on him, Thou mayst with courage journey to the ships Of the Greek horsemen. But if Jupiter All-seeing should withhold his messenger, 3, I cannot bid thee, eager as thou art, Adventure near the galleys of the Greeks." And thus the godlike Priam made reply: "Dear wife, indeed, I will not disobey Thy counsel; meet it is to raise our hands iss To Jove, and ask him to be merciful." He spake, and bade the attendant handmaid pour Pure water on his hands, for near him stood A maid who came and held a basin forth And ewer. When his hands were washed, he took The goblet from the queen, and then, in prayer, », Stood in the middle of the court, and poured The wine, and, looking heavenward, spake aloud :— "O Father Jove, most glorious and most great, Who rulest all from Ida, let me find »s Page 334 334 The Iliad. Favor and pity with Achilles. Send A messenger, thy own swift, favorite bird, Of matchless strength, on my right hand, that I, Beholding him, may confidently pass To where the fleet of the Greek horsemen lies!" ♦» Thus in his prayer he spake, and Jupiter, The All-disposer, hearkened, and sent forth An eagle, bird of surest augury, Named the Black Chaser, and by others called Percnos, with wings as broad as is the door **s Skilfully fashioned for the lofty hall Of some rich man, and fastened with a bolt. Such ample wings he spread on either side As townward on the right they saw him fly. They saw and they rejoiced ; their hearts grew light Within their bosoms. Then the aged king 4» Hastened to mount the polished car, and drave Through vestibule and echoing porch. The mules, Harnessed to draw the four-wheeled car, went first, Driven by the sage Idaeus ; after them, vs The horses, urged by Priam with the lash Rapidly through the city. All his friends Followed lamenting, as for one who went To meet his death. And now when they had reached The plain descending from the town, the sons ♦» And sons-in-law of Priam all returned To Ilium, and the twain proceeded on, Yet not unmarked by all-beholding Jove, Who, moved with pity for the aged man, Page 335 Book XXIV. 335 Turned to his well-beloved son and said :— «s "Hermes, who more than any other god Delightest to consort with human kind, And willingly dost listen to their prayers, Haste, guide King Priam to the Grecian fleet, Yet so that none may see him, and no Greek »*, Know of his coming, till he stand before Pelides." Thus he spake: the messenger Who slew the Argus hearkened and obeyed; And hastily beneath his feet he bound The fair, ambrosial, golden sandals worn «s To bear him over ocean like the wind, And o'er the boundless land. His wand he took Wherewith he seals in sleep the eyes of men, And opens them at will. With this in hand, The mighty Argus-queller flew, and soon 4*, Was at the Troad and the Hellespont. Like to some royal stripling seemed the god, In youth's first prime, when youth has most of grace. And there the Trojans twain, when they had passed The tomb of Ilus, halted with their mules 4« And horses, that the beasts might drink the stream; For twilight now was creeping o'er the earth. The herald looked, and saw that Mercury Was near, and thus, addressing Priam, said:— "Be on thy guard, O son of Dardanus, 4s0 For here is cause for wariness. I see A warrior, and I think he seeks our lives. Now let us urge our steeds and fly, or else Page 336 336 The fluid. Descend and clasp his knees, and sue for grace." He spake, and greatly.was the aged king «» Bewildered by his words; with hair erect He stood, and motionless, while Mercury Drew near, and took the old man's hand, and asked : — "Whither, O father, guidest thou thy mules And steeds in the dim night, while others sleep? «*• Fearest thou nothing from the warlike Greeks, Thy foes, who hate thee, and are near at hand? Should one of them behold thee bearing off These treasures in the swiftly darkening night, What wouldst thou do? Thou art not young, and he Who comes with thee is old; ye could not make Defence against the foe. Fear nought from me, And I will save thee, since thou art so like To my own father, from all other harm." Priam, the godlike ancient, answered thus: »o "Thou sayest true, dear son; but sure some god Holds over me his kind, protecting hand, Who sends a guide like thee to join me here, So noble art thou both in form and air, And gracious are thy thoughts, and blessed they m Who gave thee birth." With that the messenger, The Argus-queller, spake again, and said: "Most wisely hast thou spoken, aged man. But tell, and truly, why thou bearest hence This store of treasures among stranger men? * Is it that they may be preserved for thee? Page 337 Book XXIV. Or are ye all deserting in alarm Your hallowed Troy? for such a man of might Was thy brave son who died, that I may say The Greeks in battle had no braver man." And Priam, godlike ancient, spake in turn: "Who then art thou, and of what parents born, Excellent youth, who dost in such kind words Speak of the death of my unhappy son?" The herald, Argus-queller, answered him: "I see that thou wouldst prove me, aged man, By questions touching Hector, whom I oft Have seen with mine own eyes in glorious fight, Putting the Greeks to rout and slaying them By their swift ships with that sharp spear of his. We stood and marvelled, for Achilles, wroth With Agamemnon, would not suffer us To join the combat. I attend on him; The same good galley brought us to this shore, And I am one among his Myrmidons. Polyctor is my father, who is rich, And now as old as thou. Six are his sons Beside me, I the seventh. In casting lots With them, it fell to me that I should come To Ilium with Achilles. I am here In coming from the fleet, for with the dawn The dark-eyed Greeks are planning to renew The war around the city. They have grown Impatient of long idleness; their chiefs Seek vainly to restrain their warlike rage." vol. n. 15 v Page 338 338 The Iliad. Then spake the godlike ancient, Priam, thus: "If thou indeed dost serve Pelides, tell, And truly tell me, whether yet my son Is at the fleet, or has Achilles cast, Torn limb from limb, his body to the hounds?" s's The herald, Argus-queller, thus replied: "O aged monarch, neither have the hounds Devoured thy son, nor yet the birds of prey; But near the galleys of Achilles still He lies neglected and among the tents. s» Twelve mornings have beheld him lying there, Nor hath corruption touched him, nor the worms That make the slain their feast begun to feed. 'T is true that, when the holy morning dawns Achilles drags him fiercely round the tomb Of his dear friend; yet that disfigures not The dead. Shouldst thou approach him, thou wouldst see With marvelling eyes how fresh and dewy still The body lies, the blood all cleansed away, Unsoiled in every part, and all the wounds a» Closed up wherever made; for many a spear Was thrust into his sides. Thus tenderly The blessed gods regard thy son, though dead, For dearly was he loved by them in life." He spake; the aged man was comforted, sis And said: "'T is meet, O son, that we should pay Oblations to the immortals; for my son While yet alive neglected not within Page 339 Book XXIV. 339 His palace the due worship of the gods Who dwell upon Olympus; therefore they s» Are mindful of him, even after death. Take this magnificent goblet; be my guard, And guide me, by the favor of the gods, Until I reach Pelides in his tent." Again the herald, Argus-queller, spake: s4s "Thou seekest yet to try me, aged man, Who younger am than thou. Yet think thou not That I, without the knowledge of my chief, Will take thy gifts; for in my heart I fear Achilles, nor would wrong him in the least, ss» Lest evil come upon me. Yet I go Willingly with thee, as thy faithful guide. Were it as far as Argos the renowned, In a swift galley, or on foot by land, Yet none would dare to harm thee while with me." So Hermes spake, and leaped into the car, sss And took into his hands the lash and reins, And breathed into the horses and the mules Fresh vigor. Coming to the wall and trench About the ships, they found the guard engaged s*, With their night-meal. The herald Argicide Poured sleep upon them all, and quickly flung The gates apart, and pushed aside the bars, And led in Priam, with the costly gifts Heaped on the car. They went until they reached The lofty tent in which Achilles sat, s* Reared by the Myrmidons to lodge their king, Page 340 340 The Iliad. With timbers of hewn fir, and over-roofed With thatch, for which the meadows had been mown, And fenced for safety round with rows of stakes. ?7« One fir-tree bar made fast its gate, which three Strong Greeks were wont to raise aloft, and three Were needed to take down the massive beam. Achilles wielded the vast weight alone; Beneficent Hermes opened it before The aged man, and brought the treasures in, Designed for swift Achilles. Then he left The car and stood upon the ground, and said :— "O aged monarch, I am Mercury, An ever-living god; my father, Jove, s-a Bade me attend thy journey. I shall now Return, nor must Achilles look on me; It is not meet that an immortal god Should openly befriend a mortal man. Enter, approach Pelides, clasp his knees; s»s Entreat him by his father, and his son, And fair-haired mother; so shall he be moved." Thus having spoken, Hermes took his way Back to the Olympian summit. Priam then Sprang from the chariot to the ground. He left Idseus there to guard the steeds and mules, And, hastening to the tent where, dear to Jove, Achilles lodged, he found the chief within, While his companions sat apart, save two, — Automedon the brave, and Alcimus, *,s Who claimed descent from Mars. These stood near by, Page 341 Book XXIV. 341 And ministered to Peleus' son, who then Was closing a repast, and had just left The food and wine, and still the table stood. Unmarked the royal Priam entered in, And, coming to Achilles, clasped his knees, And kissed those fearful slaughter-dealing hands, By which so many of his sons had died. And as, when some blood-guilty man, whose hand In his own land has slain a fellow-man, «0s Flees to another country, and the abode Of some great chieftain, all men look on him Astonished, — so, when godlike Priam first Was seen, Achilles was amazed, and all Looked on each other, wondering at the sight . «10 And thus King Priam supplicating spake :— "Think of thy father, an old man like me, Godlike Achilles! On the dreary verge Of closing life he stands, and even now Haply is fiercely pressed by those who dwell «1s Around him, and has none to shield his age From war and its disasters. Yet his heart Rejoices when he hears thou yet dost live, And every day he hopes that his dear son Will come again from Troy. My lot is hard, For I was father of the bravest sons In all wide Troy, and none are left me now. Fifty were with me when the men of Greece Arrived upon our coast; nineteen of these Owned the same mother, and the rest were born c»s Page 342 342 The Iliad. Withm my palaces. Remorseless Mars Already had laid lifeless most of these, And Hector, whom I cherished most, whose arm Defended both our city and ourselves, Him didst thou lately slay while combating 030 For his dearcountry. For his sake I come To the Greek fleet, and to redeem his corse I bring uncounted ransom. O, revere The gods, Achilles, and be merciful, Calling to mind thy father! happier he «3s Than I; for I have borne what no man else That dwells on earth could bear, — have laid my lips Upon the hand of him who slew my son." He spake: Achilles sorrowfully thought Of his own father. By the hand he took a*, The suppliant, and with gentle force removed The old man from him. Both in memory Of those they loved were weeping. The old king, With many tears, and rolling in the dust Before Achilles, mourned his gallant son. «« Achilles sorrowed for his father's sake, And then bewailed Patroclus, and the sound Of lamentation filled the tent. At last Achilles, when he felt his heart relieved By tears, and that strong grief had spent its force, *0 Sprang from his seat; then lifting by the hand The aged man, and pitying his white head And his white chin, he spake these winged words :— "Great have thy sufferings been, unhappy king I Page 343 Book XXIV. 343 How couldst thou venture to approach alone «ss The Grecian fleet, and show thyself to him Who slew so many of thy valiant sons? j__ An iron heart is thine. But seat thyself, . .• And let us, though afflicted grievously, Allow our woes to sleep awhile, for grief «o Indulged can bring no good. The gods ordain The lot of man to suffer, while themselves Are free from care. Beside Jove's threshold stand Two casks of gifts for man. One cask contains The evil, one the good, and he to whom «s The Thunderer gives them mingled sometimes falls Into misfortune, and is sometimes crowned With blessings. But the man to whom he gives The evil only stands a mark exposed To wrong, and, chased by grim calamity, '70 Wanders the teeming earth, alike unloved By gods and men. So did the gods bestow Munificent gifts on Peleus from his birth, For eminent was he among mankind For wealth and plenty; o'er the Myrmidons «n He ruled, and, though a mortal, he was given A goddess for a wife. Yet did the gods Add evil to the good, for not to him Was born a family of kingly sons Within his house, successors to his reign. «0 One short-lived son is his, nor am I there To cherish him in his old age; but h :re Do I remain, far from my native land, Page 344 344 The Iliad. In Troy, and causing grief to thee and thine. Of thee too, aged king, they speak, as one «»s Wi'cose wealth was large in former days, when all lifenrLesbos, seat of Macar, owns was thine, And all in Phrygia and the shores that bound The Hellespont; men said thou didst excel All others in thy riches and thy sons. **, But since the gods have brought this strife on thee War and perpetual slaughter of brave men Are round thy city. Yet be firm of heart, Nor grieve forever. Sorrow for thy son Will profit nought; it cannot bring the dead «w To life again, and while thou dost afflict Thyself for him fresh woes may fall on thee." A.nd thus the godlike Priam, aged king, Made answer: "Bid me not be seated here, Nursling of Jove, while Hector lies among r» Thy tents unburied. Let me ransom him At once, that I may look on him once more With my own eyes. Receive the many gifts We bring thee, and mayst thou possess them long, And reach thy native shore, since by thy grace -m I live and yet behold the light of day." Achilles heard, and, frowning, thus rejoined: "Anger me not, old man; 't was in my thought To let thee ransom Hector. To my tent The mother came who bore me, sent from Jove, 710 The daughter of the Ancient of the Sea, And I perceive, nor can it be concealed, Page 345 Book XXIV. 345 O Priam, that some god hath guided thee To our swift galleys; for no mortal man, Though in his prime of youthful strength, would dare To come into the camp; he could not pass 716 The guard, nor move the beams that bar our gates. So then remind me of my griefs no more, Lest, suppliant as thou art, I leave thee not Unharmed, and thus transgress the laws of Jove." 7*, He spake: the aged man in fear obeyed. And then Pelides like a lion leaped Forth from the door, yet not alone he went; For of his comrades two — Automedon, The hero, and his comrade Alcimus, m He whom Achilles held in most esteem After the slain Patroclus — followed him. The mules and horses they unyoked, and led The aged monarch's clear-voiced herald in, And bade him sit. Then from the polished car 7* They took the costly ransom of the corse Of Hector, save two cloaks, which back they laid With a fair tunic, that their chief might give The body shrouded to be borne to Troy. And then he called the maidens, bidding them 73s Wash and anoint the dead, yet far apart From Priam, lest, with looking on his son, The grief within his heart might rise uncurbed To anger, and Achilles in his rage Might stay him and transgress the laws of Jove. And when the handmaids finished, having washed «5" Page 346 346 The Iliad. The body and anointed it with oil, And wrapped a sumptuous cloak and tunic round The limbs, Achilles lifted it himself And placed it on a bier. His comrades gave 74s Their aid, and raised it to the polished car. When all was done, Achilles groaned, and called By name the friend he dearly loved, and said :— "O my Patroclus, be not wroth with me Shouldst thou in Hades hear that I restore t» Hector to his dear father, since I take A ransom not unworthy; but of this I yield to thee the portion justly thine." So spake the godlike warrior, and withdrew Into his tent, and took the princely seat 7ss From which he had arisen, opposite To that of Priam, whom he thus bespake : — "Behold thy son is ransomed, aged man, As thou hast asked, and lies upon his bier. Thou shalt behold him with the early dawn, 7* And bear him hence. Now let us break our fast, For even Niobe, the golden-haired, Refrained not from her food, though children twelve Perished within her palace, — six young sons And six fair daughters. Phoebus slew the sons 7«s With arrows from his silver bow, incensed At Niobe, while Dian, archer queen, Struck down the daughters; for the mother dared To make herself the peer of rosy-cheeked Latona, who, she boastfully proclaimed, 770 Page 347 Book XXIV. 347 Had borne two children only, while herself Had brought forth many. Yet, though only two, The children of Latona took the lives Of all her own. Nine days ihe corses lay In blood, and there was none to bury them, m For Jove had changed the dwellers of the place To stone; but on the tenth the gods of heaven Gave burial to the dead. Yet Niobe, Though spent with weeping long, did not refrain From food. And now forever mid the rocks 7*, And desert hills of Sipylus, where lie, Fame says, the couches of the goddess-nymphs, Who lead the dance where Acheloiis flows, Although she be transformed to stone, she broods Over the woes inflicted by the gods. 7«s But now, O noble Ancient, let us sit At our repast, and thou mayst afterward Mourn thy beloved son, while bearing him Homeward, to be bewailed with many tears." Achilles, the swift-footed, spake, and left 790 His seat, and, slaying a white sheep, he bade His comrades flay and dress it. Then they carved The flesh in portions which they fixed on spits, And roasted carefully, and drew them back. And then Automedon distributed 79$ The bread in shapely canisters around The table, while Achilles served the flesh, And all put forth their hands and shared the feast. But when their thirst and hunger were appeased, Page 348 348 The Iliad. Dardanian Priam fixed a wondering look Upon Achilles, who in nobleness Of form was like the gods. Achilles fixed A look of equal wonder on his guest, Dardanian Priam, for he much admired His gracious aspect and his pleasant speech. *,s And when at length they both withdrew their gaze, Priam, the godlike Ancient, spake, and said : — "Nursling of Jove, dismiss me speedily To rest, that we may lie, and be refreshed With gentle slumbers. Never have these eyes sio Been closed beneath their lids, since by thy hand My Hector lost his life; and evermore I mourn and cherish all my griefs, and writhe Upon the ground within my palace courts; But I have taken food at last, and drunk *,s Draughts of red wine, untasted till this hour." Achilles bade the attending men and maids Place couches in the porch, and over them Draw sumptuous purple mats on which to lay Embroidered tapestries, and on each of these Spread a broad, fleecy mantle, covering all. Forth went the train with torches in their hands, And quickly spread two couches. Then the swift Achilles pleasantly to Priam said : — "Sleep, excellent old man, without the tent, Lest some one of our counsellors arrive, Such as oft come within my tent to sit And talk of warlike matters. Seeing thee Page 349 Book XXIV. 349 In the dark hours of night, he might relate The tale to Agamemnon, king of men, »*, And hinder thus the ransom of thy son. But say, and truly say, how many days Requirest thou to pay the funeral rites To noble Hector, so that I may rest As many, and restrain the troops from war." Then answered godlike Priam, aged king: "Since, then, thou wilt, Achilles, that we pay The rites of burial to my noble son, I own the favor. Well thou knowest how We Trojans are constrained to keep within «40 The city walls, for it is far to bring Wood from the mountains, and we fear to dare The journey. Nine days would we mourn the dea 1 Within our dwellings, and upon the tenth Would bury him, and make a solemn feast, m And the next day would rear his monument, And on the twelfth, if needful, fight again." And swift Achilles, godlike chief, rejoined: "Be it, O reverend Priam, as thou wilt, And for that space will I delay the war." «s» He spake, and that the aged king might feel No fear, he grasped his right hand at the wrist; And then King Priam and the herald went To sleep within the porch, but wary still. Achilles slumbered in his stately tent, tss The rosy-cheeked Briseis at his side, And all the other gods and men who fought Page 350 Tlu Iliad. In chariots gave themselves to slumber, save Beneficent Hermes; sleep came not to him, For still he meditated how to bring tem King Priam back from the Achaian fleet Unnoticed by the watchers at the gate. So at the monarch's head he stood, and spake:— "O aged king, thou givest little heed To danger, sleeping thus amid thy foes, «j Because Achilles spares thee. Thou hast paid Large ransom for thy well-beloved son, And yet the sons whom thou hast left in Troy Would pay three times that ransom for thy life, Should Agamemnon, son of Atreus, learn — Or any of the Greeks — that thou art here." He spake: the aged king in fear awaked The herald. Hermes yoked the steeds and mules, And drave them quickly through the camp un- marked By any there. But when they reached the ford »7s Where Xanthus, progeny of Jupiter, Rol's the smooth eddies of his stream, the god Deputed for the Olympian height, and Morn In s.iffron robes o'erspread the Earth with light. »n Townward they urged the steeds, and as they went Sorrowed and wailed: the mules conveyed the dead, And they were seen by none of all the men And graceful dames of Troy save one alone. Cassandra, beautiful as Venus, stood On Pergamus, and from its height discerned «s Page 351 Book XXIV. 351 Her wither, standing on the chariot-seat, And knew the herald, him whose voice so oft Summoned the citizens, and knew the dead Stretched on a litter drawn by mules. She raised Her voice, and called to all the city thus :— B90 "O Trojan men and women, hasten forth To look on Hector, if ye e'er rejoiced To see him coming from the field alive, The pride of Troy, and all who dwell in her." She spake, and suddenly was neither man *» Nor woman left within the city bounds. Deep grief was on them all; they went to meet, Near to the gates, the monarch bringing home The dead. And first the wife whom Hector loved Rushed with his reverend mother to the car «oo As it rolled on, and, plucking out their hair, Touched with their hands the forehead of the dead, While round it pressed the multitude, and wept, And would have wept before the gates all day, Even to the set of sun, in bitter grief y0s For Hector's loss, had not the aged man Addressed the people from his chariot-seat: "Give place to me, and let the mules pass on, And ye may weep your fill when once the dead Is laid within the palace." As he spake, 910 The throng gave way and let the chariot pass; And having brought it to the royal halls, On a fair couch they laid the corse, and placed Singers beside it, leaders of the dirge, Page 352 352 The Iliad. Who sang a sorrowful, lamenting strain, s*s And all the women answered it with sobs. White-armed Andromache in both her hands Took warlike Hector's head, and over it Began the lamentation midst them all: — "Thou hast died young, my husband, leaving me In this thy home a widow, and one son, vi An infant yet. To an unhappy pair He owes his birth, and never will, I fear, Bloom into youth ; for ere that day will Troy Be overthrown, since thou, its chief defence, mt Art dead, the guardian of its walls and all Its noble matrons and its speechless babes, Yet to be carried captive far away, And I among them, in the hollow barks; And thou, my son, wilt either go with me, «*, Where thou shalt toil at menial tasks for some Pitiless master; or perhaps some Greek Will seize thy little arm, and in his rage Will hurl thee from a low^r and dash thee dead, Remembering how thy lather, Hector, slew 93s His brother, son, or father; for the hand Of Hector forced full many a Greek to bite The dust of earth. Not slow to smite was he In the fierce conflict; therefore all who dwell Within the city sorrow for his fall. »» Thou bringest an unutterable grief, O Hector, on thy parents, and on me The sharpest sorrows. Thou didst not stretch forth Page 353 Book XXIV. 353 Thy hands to me, in dying, from thy couch, Nor speak a word to comfort me, which I «s Might ever think of night and day with tears." So spake the weeping wife: the women all Mingled their wail with hers, and Hecuba Took up the passionate lamentation next:— "O Hector, thou who wert most fondly loved •,-.0 Of all my sons! While yet thou wert alive, Dear wert thou to the gods, who even now, When death has overtaken thee, bestow Such care upon thee. All my other sons Whom swift Achilles took in war he sold »ss At Samos, Imbrus, by the barren sea, And Lemnos harborless. But as for thee, When he had taken with his cruel spear Thy life, he dragged thee round and round the tomb Of his young friend, Patroclus, whom thy hand 9*, Had slain, yet raised he not by this the dead; And now thou liest in the palace here, Fresh and besprinkled as with early dew, Like one just slain with silent arrows aimed By Phoebus, bearer of the silver bow." s*s Weeping she spake, and woke in all who heard Grief without measure. Helen, last of all, Took up the lamentation, and began : — "O Hector, who wert dearest to my heart Of all my husband's brothers, — for the wife 970 Am I of godlike Paris, him whose fleet Brought me to Troy, — would I had sooner died.' w Page 354 354 The Iliad. And now the twentieth year is past since first I came a stranger from my native shore, Yet have I never heard from thee a word Of anger or reproach. And when the sons Of Priam, and his daughters, and the wives Of Priam's sons, in all their fair array, Taunted me grievously, or Hecuba Herself, — for Priam ever was to me 9*, A gracious father, — thou didst take my part With kindly admonitions, and restrain Their tongues with soft address and gentle words. Therefore my heart is grieved, and I bewail Thee and myself at once, — unhappy me! s*3 For now I have no friend in all wide Troy, — None to be kind to me: they hate me all." Weeping she spake: the mighty throng again Answered with wailing. Priam then addressed The people: "Now bring wood, ye men of Troy, s», Into the city. Let there be no fear Of ambush from the Greeks, for when of late I left Achilles at the dark-hulled barks, He gave his promise to molest no more The men of Troy till the twelfth morn shall rise." ns He spake, and speedily they yoked the mules And oxen to the wains, and came in throngs Before the city walls. Nine days they toiled To bring the trunks of trees, and when the tenth Arose to light the abodes of men, they brought «*» The corse of vidian* Hecfor from the town Page 355 Book XXIV. 355 With many tears, and laid it on the wood High up, and flung the fire to light the pile. Now when the early rosy-fingered Dawn Looked forth, the people gathered round the pile i0«s Of glorious Hector. When they all had come Together, first they quenched the funeral fires, Wherever they had spread, with dark-red wine, And then his brothers and companions searched For the white bones. In sorrow and in tears, 1010 That streaming stained their cheeks, they gathered them, And placed them in a golden um. O'er this They drew a covering of soft purple robes, And laid it in a hollow grave, and piled Fragments of rock above it, many and huge. «s In haste they reared the tomb, with sentries set On every side, lest all too soon the Greeks Should come in armor to renew the war. When now the tomb was built, the multitude Returned, and in the halls where Priam dwelt «»» Nursling of Jove, were feasted royally. Such was the mighty Hector's burial rite.